<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"
     xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
     xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
     xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
     xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
     xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
     >
  <channel>
    <title>Gregory Szorc's Digital Home</title>
    <link>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog</link>
    <description>Rambling on</description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 09 Nov 2022 06:09:29 GMT</pubDate>
    <generator>Blogofile</generator>
    <sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
    <sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
    <item>
      <title>Bulk Analyze Linux Packages with Linux Package Analyzer</title>
      <link>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2022/01/09/bulk-analyze-linux-packages-with-linux-package-analyzer</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Jan 2022 21:10:00 PST</pubDate>
      <category><![CDATA[packaging]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[Rust]]></category>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2022/01/09/bulk-analyze-linux-packages-with-linux-package-analyzer</guid>
      <description>Bulk Analyze Linux Packages with Linux Package Analyzer</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I've frequently wanted to ask random questions about Linux packages and
binaries:</p>
<ul>
<li>Which packages provide a file X?</li>
<li>Which binaries link against a library X?</li>
<li>Which libraries/packages define/export a symbol X?</li>
<li>Which binaries reference an undefined symbol X?</li>
<li>Which features of ELF are in common use?</li>
<li>Which x86 instructions are in a binary?</li>
<li>What are the most common ELF section names and their sizes?</li>
<li>What are the differences between package X in distributions A and B?</li>
<li>Which ELF binaries have the most relocations?</li>
<li>And many more.</li>
</ul>
<p>So, I built
<a href="https://github.com/indygreg/PyOxidizer/tree/main/linux-package-analyzer">Linux Package Analyzer</a>
to facilitate answering questions like this.</p>
<p>Linux Package Analyzer is a Rust crate providing the <code>lpa</code> CLI tool. <code>lpa</code> currently
supports importing Debian and RPM package repositories (the most popular Linux
packaging formats) into a local SQLite database so subsequent analysis can be
efficiently performed offline. In essence:</p>
<ol>
<li>Run <code>lpa import-debian-repository</code> or <code>lpa import-rpm-repository</code> and point
   the tool at the base URL of a Linux package repository.</li>
<li>Package indices are fetched.</li>
<li>Discovered <code>.deb</code> and <code>.rpm</code> files are downloaded.</li>
<li>Installed files within each package archive are inspected.</li>
<li>Binary/ELF files have their executable sections disassembled.</li>
<li>Results are stored in a local SQLite database for subsequent analysis.</li>
</ol>
<p>The LPA-built database currently stores the following:</p>
<ul>
<li>Imported packages (name, version, source URL).</li>
<li>Installed files within each package (path, size).</li>
<li>ELF file information (parsed fields from header, number of relocations,
  important metadata from the <code>.dynamic</code> section, etc).</li>
<li>ELF sections (number, type, flags, address, file offset, etc).</li>
<li>Dynamic libraries required by ELF files.</li>
<li>ELF symbols (name, demangled name, type constant, binding, visibility,
  version string, etc).</li>
<li>For x86 architectures, counts of unique instructions in each ELF file and
  counts of instructions referencing specific registers.</li>
</ul>
<p>Using a command like <code>lpa import-debian-repository --components main,multiverse,restricted,universe
--architectures amd64 http://us.archive.ubuntu.com/ubuntu impish</code>, I can import
the (currently) ~96 GB of package data from 63,720 packages defining Ubuntu 21.10
to a local ~12 GB SQLite database and answer tons of random questions. Interesting
insights yielded so far include:</p>
<ul>
<li>The entirety of the package ecosystem for amd64 consists of
  63,720 packages providing 6,704,222 files (168,730 of them ELF binaries)
  comprising 355,700,362,973 bytes in total.</li>
<li>Within the 168,730 ELF binaries are 5,286,210 total sections having
  606,175 distinct names. There are also 116,688,943 symbols
  in symbol tables (debugging info is not included and local symbols not
  imported or exported are often not present in symbol tables) across
  19,085,540 distinct symbol names. The sum of all the unique symbol names
  is 1,263,441,355 bytes and 4,574,688,289 bytes if you count occurrences
  across all symbol tables (this might be an over count due to how ELF string
  tables work).</li>
<li>The longest demangled ELF symbol is 271,800 characters and is defined in
  the file <code>usr/lib/x86_64-linux-gnu/libmshr.so.2019.2.0.dev0</code> provided by
  the <code>libmshr2019.2</code> package.</li>
<li>The longest non-mangled ELF symbol is 5,321 characters and is defined in
  multiple files/packages, as it is part of a library provided by GCC.</li>
<li>Only 145 packages have files with
  <a href="https://sourceware.org/glibc/wiki/GNU_IFUNC">indirect functions (IFUNCs)</a>.
  If you discard duplicates (mainly from GCC and glibc), you are left with
  ~11 packages. This does not appear to be a popular ELF feature!</li>
<li>With 54,764 references in symbol tables, <code>strlen</code> appears to be the most
  (recognized) widely used libc symbol. It even bests <code>memcpy</code> (52,726) and
  <code>free</code> (42,603).</li>
<li><code>MOV</code> is the most frequent x86 instruction, followed by <code>CALL</code>. (I could
  write an entire blog post about observations about x86 instruction use.)</li>
</ul>
<p>There's a trove of data in the SQLite database and the <code>lpa</code> commands only
expose a fraction of it. I reckon a lot of interesting tweets, blog posts,
research papers, and more could be derived from the data that <code>lpa</code> assembles.</p>
<p><code>lpa</code> does all of its work in-process using pure Rust. The Debian and RPM
repository interaction is handled via the
<a href="https://crates.io/crates/debian-packaging">debian-packaging</a> and
<a href="https://crates.io/crates/rpm-repository">rpm-repository</a> crates (which I
wrote). ELF file parsing is handled by the (amazing)
<a href="https://crates.io/crates/object">object</a> crate. And x86 disassembling via
the <a href="https://crates.io/crates/iced-x86">iced-x86</a> crate. Many tools similar
to <code>lpa</code> call out to other processes to interface with <code>.deb</code>/.<code>rpm</code> packages,
parse ELF files, disassemble x86, etc. Doing this in pure Rust makes life so
much simpler as all the functionality is self-contained and I don't have to
worry about run-time dependencies for random tools. This means that <code>lpa</code>
should <em>just work</em> from Windows, macOS, and other non-Linux environments.</p>
<p>Linux Package Analyzer is very much in its infancy. And I don't really
have a grand vision for it. (I built it and some of the packaging code it
is built on) in support of some even grander projects I have cooking.) Please
file bugs, feature requests, and pull requests
<a href="https://github.com/indygreg/PyOxidizer">in GitHub</a>. The project is currently
part of the PyOxidizer repo (because I like monorepos). But I may pull it and
other os/packaging/toolchain code into a new monorepo since target audiences
are different.</p>
<p>I hope others find this tool useful!</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rust Implementation of Debian Packaging Primitives</title>
      <link>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2022/01/03/rust-implementation-of-debian-packaging-primitives</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jan 2022 16:00:00 PST</pubDate>
      <category><![CDATA[packaging]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[Rust]]></category>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2022/01/03/rust-implementation-of-debian-packaging-primitives</guid>
      <description>Rust Implementation of Debian Packaging Primitives</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Does your Linux distribution use tools with <code>apt</code> in their name to manage
system packages? If so, your system packages are using Debian packaging.</p>
<p>Most tools interfacing with Debian packages (<code>.deb</code> files) and repositories
use functionality provided by the <a href="https://salsa.debian.org/apt-team/apt">apt</a>
repository. This repository provides libraries like <code>libapt</code> as well as
tools like <code>apt-get</code> and <code>apt</code>. Most of the functionality is implemented in
C++.</p>
<p>I wanted to raise awareness that I've begun implementing Debian packaging
primitives in pure Rust. The <code>debian-packaging</code> crate is
<a href="https://crates.io/crates/debian-packaging">published on crates.io</a>. For
now, it is developed inside the
<a href="https://github.com/indygreg/PyOxidizer">PyOxidizer repository</a> (because I
like monorepos).</p>
<p>So far, a handful of useful functionality is implemented:</p>
<ul>
<li>Parsing and serializing <a href="https://www.debian.org/doc/debian-policy/ch-controlfields.html">control files</a></li>
<li>Reading repository indices files and parsing their content.</li>
<li>Reading HTTP hosted repositories.</li>
<li>Publishing repositories to the filesystem and S3.</li>
<li>Writing changelog files.</li>
<li>Reading and writing <code>.deb</code> files.</li>
<li>Copying repositories.</li>
<li>Creating repositories.</li>
<li>PGP signing and verification operations.</li>
<li>Parsing and sorting version strings.</li>
<li>Dependency syntax parsing.</li>
<li>Dependency resolution.</li>
</ul>
<p>Hopefully the <a href="https://docs.rs/debian-packaging/0.9.0/debian_packaging/">documentation</a>
contains all you would want to know for how to use the crate.</p>
<p>The crate is designed to be used as a library so any Rust program can
(hopefully) easily tap the power of the Debian packaging ecosystem.</p>
<p>As with most software, there are likely several bugs and many features not yet
implemented. But I have bulk downloaded the entirety of some distribution's
repositories without running into obvious parse/reading failures. So I'm
reasonably confident that important parts of the code (like control file parsing,
repository indices file handling, and <code>.deb</code> file reading) work as advertised.</p>
<p>Hopefully someone out there finds this work useful!</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
