<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed
  xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:thr="http://purl.org/syndication/thread/1.0"
  xml:lang="en"
   >
  <title type="text">Gregory Szorc's Digital Home</title>
  <subtitle type="text">Rambling on</subtitle>

  <updated>2013-04-15T17:04:03Z</updated>
  <generator uri="http://blogofile.com/">Blogofile</generator>

  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" />
  <id>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/feed/atom/</id>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/feed/atom/" />
  <entry>
    <author>
      <name></name>
      <uri>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog</uri>
    </author>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Omnipresent mach]]></title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2013/03/03/omnipresent-mach" />
    <id>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2013/03/03/omnipresent-mach</id>
    <updated>2013-03-03T12:30:00Z</updated>
    <published>2013-03-03T12:30:00Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Mozilla" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Firefox" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="mach" />
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Omnipresent mach]]></summary>
    <content type="html" xml:base="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2013/03/03/omnipresent-mach"><![CDATA[<p>Matt Brubeck recently landed an awesome patch for mach in
<a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=840588">bug 840588</a>:
it allows mach to be used by any directory. I'm calling it
<em>omnipresent mach</em>.</p>
<p>Essentially, Matt changed the <em>mach</em> driver (the script in the root
directory of mozilla-central) so instead of having it look in hard-coded
relative paths for all its code, it walks up the directory tree and
looks for signs of the source tree or the object directory.</p>
<p>What this all means is that if you have the <em>mach</em> script installed in
your $PATH and you just type <em>mach</em> in your shell from within any source
directory or object directory, <em>mach</em> should just work. So, no more
typing <em>./mach</em>: just copy <em>mach</em> to <em>~/bin</em>, <em>/usr/local/bin</em> or some
other directory on your $PATH and you should just be able to type
<em>mach</em>.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, there are bound to be bugs here. Since <em>mach</em>
traditionally was only executed with the current working directory as
the top source directory, some commands are not prepared to handle a
variable current working directory. Some commands will likely get
confused when it comes resolving relative paths, etc. If you find
an issue, please report it! A temporary workaround is to just invoke
mach from the top source directory like you've always been doing.</p>
<p>If you enjoy the feature, thank Matt: this was completely his idea and
he saw it through from conception to implementation.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
</feed>
