<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed
  xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:thr="http://purl.org/syndication/thread/1.0"
  xml:lang="en"
   >
  <title type="text">Gregory Szorc's Digital Home</title>
  <subtitle type="text">Rambling on</subtitle>

  <updated>2024-12-03T19:27:50Z</updated>
  <generator uri="http://blogofile.com/">Blogofile</generator>

  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" />
  <id>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/feed/atom/</id>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/feed/atom/" />
  <entry>
    <author>
      <name>Gregory Szorc</name>
      <uri>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog</uri>
    </author>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Achieving A Completely Open Source Implementation of Apple Code Signing and Notarization]]></title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2022/08/08/achieving-a-completely-open-source-implementation-of-apple-code-signing-and-notarization" />
    <id>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2022/08/08/achieving-a-completely-open-source-implementation-of-apple-code-signing-and-notarization</id>
    <updated>2022-08-08T08:08:08Z</updated>
    <published>2022-08-08T08:08:08Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Apple" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Rust" />
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Achieving A Completely Open Source Implementation of Apple Code Signing and Notarization]]></summary>
    <content type="html" xml:base="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2022/08/08/achieving-a-completely-open-source-implementation-of-apple-code-signing-and-notarization"><![CDATA[<p>As I've previously blogged in
<a href="/blog/2021/04/14/pure-rust-implementation-of-apple-code-signing/">Pure Rust Implementation of Apple Code Signing</a>
(2021-04-14) and
<a href="/blog/2022/04/25/expanding-apple-ecosystem-access-with-open-source,-multi-platform-code-signing/">Expanding Apple Ecosystem Access with Open Source, Multi Platform Code signing</a>
(2022-04-25), I've been hacking on an open source implementation of Apple code
signing and notarization using the Rust programming language. This takes the form
of the <code>apple-codesign</code> crate / library and its <code>rcodesign</code> CLI executable.
(<a href="https://gregoryszorc.com/docs/apple-codesign/stable/">Documentation</a> /
<a href="https://github.com/indygreg/apple-platform-rs/tree/main/apple-codesign">GitHub project</a> /
<a href="https://crates.io/crates/apple-codesign">crates.io</a>).</p>
<p>As of that most recent post in April, I was pretty happy with the relative
stability of the implementation: we were able to sign, notarize, and staple
Mach-O binaries, directory bundles (<code>.app</code>, <code>.framework</code> bundles, etc), XAR
archives / flat packages / <code>.pkg</code> installers, and DMG disk images. Except for
the <a href="https://gregoryszorc.com/docs/apple-codesign/0.17.0/apple_codesign_quirks.html">known limitations</a>,
if Apple's official <code>codesign</code> and <code>notarytool</code> tools support it, so do we.
<strong>This allows people to sign, notarize, and release Apple software from non-Apple
operating systems like Linux and Windows.</strong> This opens up new avenues for
Apple platform access.</p>
<p>A major limitation in previous versions of the <code>apple-codesign</code> crate was our
reliance on Apple's <a href="https://help.apple.com/itc/transporteruserguide/">Transporter</a>
tool for notarization. Transporter is a Java application made available for macOS,
Linux, and Windows that speaks to Apple's servers and can upload assets to their
notarization service. I used this tool at the time because it seemed to
be officially supported by Apple and the path of least resistance to standing
up notarization. But Transporter was a bit wonky to use and an extra
dependency that you needed to install.</p>
<p>At WWDC 2022, Apple <a href="https://developer.apple.com/videos/play/wwdc2022/10109/">announced</a>
a new <a href="https://developer.apple.com/documentation/notaryapi">Notary API</a> as
part of the App Store Connect API. In what felt like a wink directly at me,
Apple themselves even calls out the possibility for leveraging this API to
notarize from Linux! I knew as soon as I saw this that it was only a matter
of time before I would be able to replace Transporter with a pure Rust client
for the new HTTP API. (I was already thinking about using the unpublished HTTP
API that <code>notarytool</code> uses. And from the limited reversing notes I have from
before WWDC it looks like the new official Notary API is very similar - possibly
identical to - what <code>notarytool</code> uses. So kudos to Apple for opening up this
access!)</p>
<p><strong>I'm very excited to announce that we now have a pure Rust implementation
of a client for Apple's Notary API in the <code>apple-codesign</code> crate. This means we
can now notarize Apple software from any machine where you can get the Rust
crate to compile. This means we no longer have a dependency on the 3rd party
Apple Transporter application. Notarization, like code signing, is 100% open
source Rust code.</strong></p>
<p>As excited as I am to announce this new feature, <strong>I'm even more excited that
it was largely implemented by a contributor, Robin Lambertz /
<a href="https://github.com/roblabla">@roblabla</a>!</strong> They
<a href="https://github.com/indygreg/PyOxidizer/issues/591">filed a GitHub feature request</a>
while WWDC 2022 was still ongoing and then <a href="https://github.com/indygreg/PyOxidizer/pull/593">submitted a PR</a>
a few days later. It took me a few months to get around to reviewing it
(I try to avoid computer screens during summers), but it was a fantastic
PR given the scope of the change. It never ceases to bring joy to me when
someone randomly contributes greatness to open source.</p>
<p>So, as of the just-released <a href="https://github.com/indygreg/PyOxidizer/releases/tag/apple-codesign%2F0.17.0">0.17 release</a>
of the <code>apple-codesign</code> Rust crate and its corresponding <code>rcodesign</code> CLI tool, you can now
<code>rcodesign notary-submit</code> to speak to Apple's Notary API using a pure Rust client. No
more requirements on 3rd party, proprietary software. All you need to sign and
notarize Apple applications is the self-contained <code>rcodesign</code> executable and a Linux,
Windows, macOS, BSD, etc machine to run it on.</p>
<p>I'm stoked to finally achieve this milestone! There are probably thousands of
companies and individuals who have wanted to release Apple software from
non-macOS operating systems. (The existence and popularity of tools like
<a href="https://fastlane.tools/">fastlane</a> seems to confirm this.) The historical
lack of an Apple code signing and notarization solution that worked outside
macOS has prevented this. Well, that barrier has officially fallen.</p>
<p>Release notes, documentation, and (self-signed) pre-built executables of the
<code>rcodesign</code> executable for major platforms are available on the
<a href="https://github.com/indygreg/PyOxidizer/releases/tag/apple-codesign%2F0.17.0">0.17 release page</a>.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <author>
      <name>Gregory Szorc</name>
      <uri>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog</uri>
    </author>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Expanding Apple Ecosystem Access with Open Source, Multi Platform Code Signing]]></title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2022/04/25/expanding-apple-ecosystem-access-with-open-source,-multi-platform-code-signing" />
    <id>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2022/04/25/expanding-apple-ecosystem-access-with-open-source,-multi-platform-code-signing</id>
    <updated>2022-04-25T08:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-04-25T08:00:00Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Apple" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Rust" />
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Expanding Apple Ecosystem Access with Open Source, Multi Platform Code Signing]]></summary>
    <content type="html" xml:base="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2022/04/25/expanding-apple-ecosystem-access-with-open-source,-multi-platform-code-signing"><![CDATA[<p>A little over one year ago, I
<a href="/blog/2021/04/14/pure-rust-implementation-of-apple-code-signing/">announced a project to implement Apple code signing in pure Rust</a>.
There have been quite a number of developments since that post and I thought
a blog post was in order. So here we are!</p>
<p>But first, some background on why we're here.</p>
<h2>Background</h2>
<p>(Skip this section if you just want to get to the technical bits.)</p>
<p>Apple runs some of the largest and most profitable software application
ecosystems in existence. Gaining access to these ecosystems has traditionally
required the use of macOS and membership in the Apple Developer Program.</p>
<p>For the most part this makes sense: if you want to develop applications for
Apple operating systems you will likely utilize Apple's operating systems
and Apple's official tooling for development and distribution. Sticking to
the paved road is a good default!</p>
<p>But many people want more... flexibility. Open source developers, for example,
often want to distribute cross-platform applications with minimal effort.
There are entire programming language ecosystems where the operating system
you are running on is abstracted away as an implementation detail for many
applications. <strong>By creating a de facto requirement that macOS, iOS, etc
development require the direct access to macOS and (often above market priced)
Apple hardware, the distribution requirements imposed by Apple's software
ecosystems are effectively exclusionary and prevent interested parties
from contributing to the ecosystem.</strong></p>
<p>One of the aspects of software distribution on Apple platforms that trips
a lot of people up is code signing and notarization. Essentially, you need
to:</p>
<ol>
<li>Embed a cryptographic signature in applications that effectively attests
   to its authenticity from an Apple Developer Program associated account.
   (This is signing.)</li>
<li>Upload your application to Apple so they can inspect it, verify it meets
   requirements, likely store a copy of it. Apple then issues their own
   cryptographic signature called a <em>notarization ticket</em> which then needs
   to be <em>stapled</em>/attached to the application being distributed so Apple
   operating systems can trust it. (This is notarization.)</li>
</ol>
<p>Historically, these steps required Apple proprietary software run exclusively
from macOS. This means that even if you are in a software ecosystem like Rust,
Go, or the web platform where you can cross-compile apps without direct access
to macOS (testing is obviously a different story), you would still need macOS
somewhere if you wanted to sign and notarize your application. And signing and
notarization is effectively required on macOS due to default security settings.
On mobile platforms like iOS, it is impossible to distribute applications that
aren't signed and notarized unless you are running a jailbreaked device.</p>
<p>A lot of people (myself included) have grumbled at these requirements.
Why should I be forced to involve an Apple machine as part of my software
release process if I don't need macOS to build my application? Why do I have
to go through a convoluted dance to sign and notarize my application at
release time - can't it be more streamlined?</p>
<p>When I looked at this space last year, I saw some obvious inefficiencies
and room to improve. So as I said then, I <em>foolishly</em> set out to reimplement
Apple code signing so developers would have more flexibility and opportunity
for distributing applications to Apple's ecosystems.</p>
<p><strong>The ultimate goal of this work is to expand Apple ecosystem access to more
developers.</strong> A year later, I believe I'm delivering a product capable of
doing this.</p>
<h2>One Year Later</h2>
<p><strong>Foremost, I'm excited to announce release of
<a href="https://github.com/indygreg/PyOxidizer/releases/tag/apple-codesign/0.14.0">rcodesign 0.14.0</a>.
This is the first time I'm publishing pre-built binaries (Linux, Windows, and macOS)
of <code>rcodesign</code>. This reflects my confidence in the relative maturity of the
software.</strong></p>
<p>In case you are wondering, yes, the macOS <code>rcodesign</code> executable is self-signed:
it was signed by a GitHub Actions Linux runner using a code signing certificate
exclusive to a YubiKey. That YubiKey was plugged into a Windows 11 desktop next to
my desk. The <code>rcodesign</code> executable was not copied between machines as part of the
signing operation. Read on to learn about the sorcery that made this possible.</p>
<p>A lot has changed in the <a href="https://github.com/indygreg/apple-platform-rs/tree/main/apple-codesign">apple-codesign</a>
project / Rust crate in the last year! Just look at the
<a href="https://github.com/indygreg/apple-platform-rs/blob/main/apple-codesign/CHANGELOG.rst">changelog</a>!</p>
<p>The project was renamed from <code>tugger-apple-codesign</code>.</p>
<p>(If you installed via <code>cargo install</code>, you'll need to
<code>cargo install --force apple-codesign</code> to force Cargo to overwrite the <code>rcodesign</code>
executable with one from a different crate.)</p>
<p>The <code>rcodesign</code> CLI executable is still there and more powerful than ever.
You can still sign Apple applications from Linux, Windows, macOS, and any other
platform you can get the Rust program to compile on.</p>
<p>There is now <a href="https://pyoxidizer.readthedocs.io/en/latest/apple_codesign.html">Sphinx documentation for the project</a>.
This is published on readthedocs.io alongside PyOxidizer's documentation (because
I'm using a monorepo). There's some general documentation in there, such as a
guide on how to
<a href="https://pyoxidizer.readthedocs.io/en/latest/apple_codesign_custom_assessment_policies.html">selectively bypass Gatekeeper</a>
by deploying your own alternative code signing PKI to parallel Apple's. (This
seems like something many companies would want but for whatever reason I'm
not aware of anyone doing this - possibly because very few people understand
how these systems work.)</p>
<p>There are bug fixes galore. When I look back at the state of <code>rcodesign</code>
when I first blogged about it, I think of how naive I was. There were a myriad
of applications that wouldn't pass notarization because of a long tail of bugs.
There are still known issues. But <strong>I believe many applications will
successfully sign and notarize now.</strong> I consider failures novel and worthy of
bug reports - so please <a href="https://pyoxidizer.readthedocs.io/en/latest/apple_codesign_debugging.html">report them</a>!</p>
<p>Read on to learn about some of the notable improvements in the past year (many
of them occurring in the last two months).</p>
<h2>Support for Signing Bundles, DMGs, and <code>.pkg</code> Installers</h2>
<p>When I announced this project last year, only Mach-O binaries and trivially
simple <code>.app</code> bundles were signable. And even then there were a ton of subtle
issues.</p>
<p><code>rcodesign sign</code> can now sign more complex bundles, including many nested
bundles. There are reports of iOS app bundles signing correctly! (However, we
don't yet have good end-user documentation for signing iOS apps. I will gladly
accept PRs to improve the documentation!)</p>
<p>The tool also gained support for signing <code>.dmg</code> disk image files and <code>.pkg</code>
flat package installers.</p>
<p>Known limitations with signing are now
<a href="https://pyoxidizer.readthedocs.io/en/latest/apple_codesign_quirks.html">documented</a>
in the Sphinx docs.</p>
<p><strong>I believe <code>rcodesign</code> now supports signing all the major file formats used
for Apple software distribution.</strong> If you find something that doesn't sign
and it isn't documented as a known issue with an existing GitHub issue tracking
it, please report it!</p>
<h2>Support for Notarization on Linux, Windows, and macOS</h2>
<p>Apple publishes a Java tool named
<a href="https://help.apple.com/itc/transporteruserguide/">Transporter</a> that enables you
to upload artifacts to Apple for notarization. They make this tool available for
Linux, Windows, and of course macOS.</p>
<p>While this tool isn't open source (as far as I know), usage of this tool enables
you to notarize from Linux and Windows while still using Apple's official
tooling for communicating with their servers.</p>
<p><code>rcodesign</code> now has support for invoking Transporter and uploading artifacts
to Apple for notarization. We now support notarizing bundles, <code>.dmg</code> disk
images, and <code>.pkg</code> flat installer packages. I've successfully notarized all
of these application types from Linux.</p>
<p>(I'm capable of implementing
an alternative uploader in pure Rust but without assurances that Apple won't
bring down the ban hammer for violating terms of use, this is a bridge I'm
not yet willing to cross. The requirement to use Transporter is literally the
only thing standing in the way of making <code>rcodesign</code> an all-in-one single
file executable tool for signing and notarizing Apple software and I <strong>really</strong>
wish I could deliver this user experience win without reprisal.)</p>
<p><strong>With support for both signing and notarizing all application types, it is
now possible to release Apple software without macOS involved in your release
process.</strong></p>
<h2>YubiKey Integration</h2>
<p>I try to use my YubiKeys as much as possible because a secret or private key
stored on a YubiKey is likely more secure than a secret or private key sitting
around on a filesystem somewhere. If you hack my machine, you can likely
gain access to my private keys. But you will need physical access to my
YubiKey and to compel or coerce me into unlocking it in order to gain access
to its private keys.</p>
<p><strong><code>rcodesign</code> now has support for using YubiKeys for signing operations.</strong></p>
<p>This does require an off-by-default <code>smartcard</code> Cargo feature. So if
building manually you'll need to e.g.
<code>cargo install --features smartcard apple-codesign</code>.</p>
<p>The YubiKey integration comes courtesy of the amazing
<a href="https://crates.io/crates/yubikey">yubikey</a> Rust crate. This crate will speak
directly to the smartcard APIs built into macOS and Windows. So if you have an
<code>rcodesign</code> build with YubiKey support enabled, YubiKeys should
<em>just work</em>. Try it by plugging in your YubiKey and running
<code>rcodesign smartcard-scan</code>.</p>
<p>YubiKey integration has its
<a href="https://pyoxidizer.readthedocs.io/en/latest/apple_codesign_smartcard.html">own documentation</a>.</p>
<p>I even implemented some commands to make it easy to manage the code signing
certificates on your YubiKey. For example, you can run
<code>rcodesign smartcard-generate-key --smartcard-slot 9c</code> to generate a new private
key directly on the device and then
<code>rcodesign generate-certificate-signing-request --smartcard-slot 9c --csr-pem-path csr.pem</code>
to export that certificate to a Certificate Signing Request (CSR), which you can
exchange for an Applie-issued signing certificate at developer.apple.com. <strong>This
means you can easily create code signing certificates whose private key was
generated directly on the hardware device and can never be exported.</strong>
Generating keys this way is widely considered to be more secure than storing
keys in software vaults, like Apple's Keychains.</p>
<h2>Remote Code Signing</h2>
<p>The feature I'm most excited about is what I'm calling
<a href="https://pyoxidizer.readthedocs.io/en/latest/apple_codesign_remote_signing.html">remote code signing</a>.</p>
<p>Remote code signing allows you to delegate the low-level cryptographic signature
operations in code signing to a separate machine.</p>
<p>It's probably easiest to just demonstrate what it can do.</p>
<p><strong>Earlier today I signed a macOS universal Mach-O executable from a GitHub-hosted
Linux GitHub Actions runner using a YubiKey physically attached to the
Windows 11 machine next to my desk at home. The signed application was not
copied between machines.</strong></p>
<p>Here's how I did it.</p>
<p>I have a GitHub Actions workflow that calls <code>rcodesign sign --remote-signer</code>.
I manually triggered that workflow and started watching the near real time
job output with my browser. Here's a screenshot of the job logs:</p>
<p><img alt="GitHub Actions initiating remote code signing" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/indygreg/PyOxidizer/058f718641ad47b39ccf54346f0f0ad6e91bd09b/apple-codesign/docs/apple_codesign_actions_sjs_join.png" /></p>
<p><code>rcodesign sign --remote-signer</code> prints out some instructions (including a
wall of base64 encoded data) for what to do next. Importantly, it requests that
someone else run <code>rcodesign remote-sign</code> to continue the signing process.</p>
<p>And here's a screenshot of me doing that from the Windows terminal:</p>
<p><img alt="Windows terminal output from running remote-sign command" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/indygreg/PyOxidizer/058f718641ad47b39ccf54346f0f0ad6e91bd09b/apple-codesign/docs/apple_codesign_actions_signer_output.png" /></p>
<p>This log shows us connecting and authenticating with the YubiKey along
with some status updates regarding speaking to a remote server.</p>
<p>Finally, here's a screenshot of the GitHub Actions job output after
I ran that command on my Windows machine:</p>
<p><img alt="GitHub Actions initiating machine output" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/indygreg/PyOxidizer/058f718641ad47b39ccf54346f0f0ad6e91bd09b/apple-codesign/docs/apple_codesign_actions_initiator_output.png" /></p>
<p><em>Remote signing</em> enabled me to sign a macOS application from a GitHub Actions
runner operated by GitHub while using a code signing certificate securely
stored on my YubiKey plugged into a Windows machine hundreds of kilometers away
from the GitHub Actions runner. Magic, right?</p>
<p>What's happening here is the 2 <code>rcodesign</code> processes are communicating
with each other via websockets bridged by a central relay server.
(I operate a
<a href="https://pyoxidizer.readthedocs.io/en/latest/apple_codesign_remote_signing_design.html#default-remote-code-signing-server">default server free of charge</a>.
The server is open source and a Terraform module is available if you want
to run your own server with hopefully just a few minutes of effort.)
When the initiating machine wants to create a signature, it sends a
message back to the <em>signer</em> requesting a cryptographic signature. The
signature is then sent back to the initiator, who incorporates it.</p>
<p><strong>I designed this feature with automated releases from CI systems (like
GitHub Actions) in mind. I wanted a way where I could streamline the
code signing and release process of applications without having to give
a low trust machine in CI ~unlimited access to my private signing key.
But the more I thought about it the more I realized there are likely
many other scenarios where this could be useful. Have you ever emailed
or Dropboxed an application for someone else to sign because you don't
have an Apple issued code signing certificate? Now you have an alternative
solution that doesn't require copying files around!</strong> As long as you
can see the log output from the initiating machine or have that output
communicated to you (say over a chat application or email), you can
remotely sign files on another machine!</p>
<h3>An Aside on the Security of Remote Signing</h3>
<p>At this point, I'm confident the more security conscious among you have
been grimacing for a few paragraphs now. Websockets through a central
server operated by a 3rd party?! Giving remote machines access to perform
code signing against arbitrary content?! Your fears and skepticism are
100% justified: I'd be thinking the same thing!</p>
<p>I fully recognize that a service that facilitates remote code signing makes
for a very lucrative attack target! If abused, it could be used to coerce
parties with valid code signing certificates to sign unwanted code, like
malware. There are many, many, many <em>wrong</em> ways to implement such a feature.
I pondered for hours about the threat modeling and how to make this feature
as secure as possible.</p>
<p><a href="https://pyoxidizer.readthedocs.io/en/latest/apple_codesign_remote_signing_design.html">Remote Code Signing Design and Security Considerations</a>
captures some of my high level design goals and security assessments.
And <a href="https://pyoxidizer.readthedocs.io/en/latest/apple_codesign_remote_signing_protocol.html">Remote Code Signing Protocol</a>
goes into detail about the communications protocol, including the
crypto (actual cryptography, not the fad) involved. The key takeaways are
the protocol and server are designed such that a malicious server or
man-in-the-middle can not forge signature requests. Signing sessions expire
after a few minutes and 3rd parties (or the server) can't inject malicious
messages that would result in unwanted signatures. There is an initial
handshake to derive a session ephemeral shared encryption key and from
there symmetric encryption keys are used so all meaningful messages between
peers are end-to-end encrypted. About the worst a malicious server could do
is conduct a denial of service. This is by design.</p>
<p>As I argue in <a href="https://pyoxidizer.readthedocs.io/en/latest/apple_codesign_remote_signing_design.html#security-analysis-in-the-bigger-picture">Security Analysis in the Bigger Picture</a>,
I believe that my implementation of <em>remote signing</em> is <strong>more</strong> secure than
many common practices because common practices today entail making copies
of private keys and giving low trust machines (like CI workers) access to
private keys. Or files are copied around without cryptographic chain-of-custody
to prove against tampering. Yes, <em>remote signing</em> introduces a vector for remote
access to <em>use</em> signing keys. But practiced as I intended, <em>remote signing</em> can
eliminate the need to copy private keys or grant ~unlimited access to them.
From a threat modeling perspective, I think the net restriction in key
access makes <em>remote signing</em> more secure than the private key management
practices by many today.</p>
<p><strong>All that being said, the giant asterisk here is I implemented my own
cryptosystem to achieve end-to-end message security. If there are bugs in
the design or implementation, that cryptosystem could come crashing down,
bringing defenses against message forgery with it.</strong> At that point, a
malicious server or privileged network actor could potentially coerce
someone into signing unwanted software. But this is likely the extent of
the damage: an offline attack against the signing key should not be
possible since signing requires presence and since the private key is
never transmitted over the wire. Even without the end-to-end encryption,
the system is <em>arguably</em> more secure than leaving your private key
lingering around as an easily exfiltrated CI secret (or similar).</p>
<p>(I apologize to every cryptographer I worked with at Mozilla who beat into me
the commandment that <em>thou shall not roll their own crypto</em>: I have sinned
and I feel remorseful.) </p>
<p>Cryptography is hard. And I'm sure I made plenty of subtle mistakes.
<a href="https://github.com/indygreg/PyOxidizer/issues/552">Issue #552</a> tracks
getting an audit of this protocol and code performed. And the aforementioned
<a href="https://pyoxidizer.readthedocs.io/en/latest/apple_codesign_remote_signing_protocol.html">protocol design docs</a>
call out some of the places where I question decisions I've made.</p>
<p><strong>If you would be interested in doing a security review on this feature,
please get in touch on issue #552 or
<a href="mailto:gregory.szorc@gmail.com">send me an email</a>. If there's one immediate
outcome I'd like from this blog post it would be for some white hat^Hknight
to show up and give me peace of mind about the cryptosystem implementation.</strong></p>
<p><strong>Until then, please assume the end-to-end encryption is completely flawed.</strong>
Consider asking someone with <em>security</em> or <em>cryptographer</em> in their job title
for their opinion on whether this feature is safe for you to use. Hopefully
we'll get a security review done soon and this caveat can go away!</p>
<p>If you do want to use this feature,
<a href="https://pyoxidizer.readthedocs.io/en/latest/apple_codesign_remote_signing.html">Remote Code Signing</a>
contains some usage documentation, including how to use it with GitHub
Actions. (I could also use some help productionizing a reusable GitHub Action
to make this more turnkey! Although I'm hesitant to do it before I know the
cryptosystem is sound.)</p>
<p>That was a long introduction to <em>remote code signing</em>. But I couldn't
in good faith present the feature without addressing the security aspect.
Hopefully I didn't scare you away! <strong>Traditional / local signing should
have no security concerns</strong> (beyond the willingness to run software written
by somebody you probably don't know, of course).</p>
<h2>Apple Keychain Support</h2>
<p>As of today's 0.14 release we now have early support for signing with code signing
certificates stored in Apple Keychains! If you created your Apple code signing
certificates in Keychain Access or Xcode, this is probably where you code
signing certificates live.</p>
<p>I held off implementing this for the longest time because I didn't perceive
there to be a benefit: if you are on macOS, just use Apple's official tooling.
But with <code>rcodesign</code> gaining support for remote code signing and some other
features that could make it a compelling replacement for Apple tooling on
all platforms, I figured we should provide the feature so we stop discouraging
people to export private keys from Keychains.</p>
<p>This integration is very young and there's still a lot that can be done,
such as automatically using an appropriate signing certificate based on
what you are signing. Please file feature request issues if there's
a must-have feature you are missing!</p>
<h2>Better Debugging of Failures</h2>
<p>Apple's code signing is complex. It is easy for there to be subtle differences
between Apple's tooling and <code>rcodesign</code>.</p>
<p><code>rcodesign</code> now has <code>print-signature-info</code> and <code>diff-signatures</code> commands to
dump and compare YAML metadata pertinent to code signing to make it easier to
compare behavior between code signing implementations and even multiple
signing operations.</p>
<p>The documentation around
<a href="https://pyoxidizer.readthedocs.io/en/latest/apple_codesign_debugging.html">debugging and reporting bugs</a>
now emphasizes using these tools to help identify bugs.</p>
<h2>A Request For Users and Feedback</h2>
<p>I now believe <code>rcodesign</code> to be generally usable. I've thrown a lot of
random software at it and I feel like most of the big bugs and major missing
features are behind us.</p>
<p>But I also feel it hasn't yet received wide enough attention to have confidence
in that assessment.</p>
<p><strong>If you want to help the development of this tool, the most important
actions you can take are to attempt signing / notarization operations with it
and report your results.</strong></p>
<p>Does <code>rcodesign</code> spark joy? Please leave a comment in the
<a href="https://github.com/indygreg/PyOxidizer/discussions/556">GitHub discussion for the latest release</a>!</p>
<p>Does <code>rcodesign</code> not work? I would very much appreciate a bug report!
Details on how to file good bugs are
<a href="https://pyoxidizer.readthedocs.io/en/latest/apple_codesign_debugging.html">in the docs</a>.</p>
<p>Have general feedback? UI is confusing? Documentation is insufficient?
Leave a comment in the aforementioned discussion. Or
<a href="https://github.com/indygreg/PyOxidizer/issues/new">create a GitHub issue</a> if
you think it is actionable. I can't fix what I don't know about!</p>
<p>Have private feedback? <a href="mailto:gregory.szorc@gmail.com">Send me an email</a>.</p>
<h2>Conclusion</h2>
<p>I could write thousands of words about all I learned from hacking on this
project.</p>
<p>I've learned way too much about too many standards and specifications in the
crypto space. RFCs 2986, 3161, 3280, 3281, 3447, 4210, 4519, 5280, 5480,
5652, 5869, 5915, 5958, and 8017 plus probably a few more. How cryptographic
primitives are stored and expressed: ASN.1, OIDs, BER, DER, PEM, SPKI,
PKCS#1, PKCS#8. You can show me the raw parse tree for an ASN.1 data structure
and I can probably tell you what RFC defines it. I'm not proud of this. But
I will say actually knowing what every field in an X.509 certificate does
or the many formats that cryptographic keys are expressed in seems empowering.
Before, I would just search for the <code>openssl</code> incantation to do something.
Now, I know which ASN.1 data structures are involved and how to manipulate
the fields within.</p>
<p>I've learned way too much around minutia around how Apple code signing
actually works. The mechanism is way too complex for something in the security
space. There was at least one high profile Gatekeeper bug in the past year
allowing improperly signed code to run. I suspect there will be more: the
surface area to exploit is just too large.</p>
<p><strong>I think I'm proud of building an open source implementation of Apple's code
signing. To my knowledge nobody else has done this outside of Apple. At least
not to the degree I have.</strong> Then factor in that I was able to do this without
access (or willingness) to look at Apple source code and much of the progress was
achieved by diffing and comparing results with Apple's tooling. Hours of
staring at diffoscope and comparing binary data structures. Hours of trying
to find the magical settings that enabled a SHA-1 or SHA-256 digest to agree.
It was tedious work for sure. I'll likely never see a financial return on
the time equivalent it took me to develop this software. But, I suppose I
can nerd brag that I was able to implement this!</p>
<p><strong>But the real reward for this work will be if it opens up avenues to more
(open source) projects distributing to the Apple ecosystems.</strong> This has
historically been challenging for multiple reasons and many open source
projects have avoided official / proper distribution channels to avoid the
pain (or in some cases because of philosophical disagreements with the premise
of having a walled software garden in the first place). I suspect things
will only get worse, as I feel it is inevitable Apple clamps down on signing
and notarization requirements on macOS due to the rising costs of malware
and ransomware. <strong>So having an alternative, open source, and multi-platform
implementation of Apple code signing seems like something important that
should exist in order to provide opportunities to otherwise excluded
developers. I would be humbled if my work empowers others. And this is
all the reward I need.</strong></p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <author>
      <name>Gregory Szorc</name>
      <uri>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog</uri>
    </author>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bulk Analyze Linux Packages with Linux Package Analyzer]]></title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2022/01/09/bulk-analyze-linux-packages-with-linux-package-analyzer" />
    <id>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2022/01/09/bulk-analyze-linux-packages-with-linux-package-analyzer</id>
    <updated>2022-01-09T21:10:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-09T21:10:00Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="packaging" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Rust" />
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Bulk Analyze Linux Packages with Linux Package Analyzer]]></summary>
    <content type="html" xml:base="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2022/01/09/bulk-analyze-linux-packages-with-linux-package-analyzer"><![CDATA[<p>I've frequently wanted to ask random questions about Linux packages and
binaries:</p>
<ul>
<li>Which packages provide a file X?</li>
<li>Which binaries link against a library X?</li>
<li>Which libraries/packages define/export a symbol X?</li>
<li>Which binaries reference an undefined symbol X?</li>
<li>Which features of ELF are in common use?</li>
<li>Which x86 instructions are in a binary?</li>
<li>What are the most common ELF section names and their sizes?</li>
<li>What are the differences between package X in distributions A and B?</li>
<li>Which ELF binaries have the most relocations?</li>
<li>And many more.</li>
</ul>
<p>So, I built
<a href="https://github.com/indygreg/PyOxidizer/tree/main/linux-package-analyzer">Linux Package Analyzer</a>
to facilitate answering questions like this.</p>
<p>Linux Package Analyzer is a Rust crate providing the <code>lpa</code> CLI tool. <code>lpa</code> currently
supports importing Debian and RPM package repositories (the most popular Linux
packaging formats) into a local SQLite database so subsequent analysis can be
efficiently performed offline. In essence:</p>
<ol>
<li>Run <code>lpa import-debian-repository</code> or <code>lpa import-rpm-repository</code> and point
   the tool at the base URL of a Linux package repository.</li>
<li>Package indices are fetched.</li>
<li>Discovered <code>.deb</code> and <code>.rpm</code> files are downloaded.</li>
<li>Installed files within each package archive are inspected.</li>
<li>Binary/ELF files have their executable sections disassembled.</li>
<li>Results are stored in a local SQLite database for subsequent analysis.</li>
</ol>
<p>The LPA-built database currently stores the following:</p>
<ul>
<li>Imported packages (name, version, source URL).</li>
<li>Installed files within each package (path, size).</li>
<li>ELF file information (parsed fields from header, number of relocations,
  important metadata from the <code>.dynamic</code> section, etc).</li>
<li>ELF sections (number, type, flags, address, file offset, etc).</li>
<li>Dynamic libraries required by ELF files.</li>
<li>ELF symbols (name, demangled name, type constant, binding, visibility,
  version string, etc).</li>
<li>For x86 architectures, counts of unique instructions in each ELF file and
  counts of instructions referencing specific registers.</li>
</ul>
<p>Using a command like <code>lpa import-debian-repository --components main,multiverse,restricted,universe
--architectures amd64 http://us.archive.ubuntu.com/ubuntu impish</code>, I can import
the (currently) ~96 GB of package data from 63,720 packages defining Ubuntu 21.10
to a local ~12 GB SQLite database and answer tons of random questions. Interesting
insights yielded so far include:</p>
<ul>
<li>The entirety of the package ecosystem for amd64 consists of
  63,720 packages providing 6,704,222 files (168,730 of them ELF binaries)
  comprising 355,700,362,973 bytes in total.</li>
<li>Within the 168,730 ELF binaries are 5,286,210 total sections having
  606,175 distinct names. There are also 116,688,943 symbols
  in symbol tables (debugging info is not included and local symbols not
  imported or exported are often not present in symbol tables) across
  19,085,540 distinct symbol names. The sum of all the unique symbol names
  is 1,263,441,355 bytes and 4,574,688,289 bytes if you count occurrences
  across all symbol tables (this might be an over count due to how ELF string
  tables work).</li>
<li>The longest demangled ELF symbol is 271,800 characters and is defined in
  the file <code>usr/lib/x86_64-linux-gnu/libmshr.so.2019.2.0.dev0</code> provided by
  the <code>libmshr2019.2</code> package.</li>
<li>The longest non-mangled ELF symbol is 5,321 characters and is defined in
  multiple files/packages, as it is part of a library provided by GCC.</li>
<li>Only 145 packages have files with
  <a href="https://sourceware.org/glibc/wiki/GNU_IFUNC">indirect functions (IFUNCs)</a>.
  If you discard duplicates (mainly from GCC and glibc), you are left with
  ~11 packages. This does not appear to be a popular ELF feature!</li>
<li>With 54,764 references in symbol tables, <code>strlen</code> appears to be the most
  (recognized) widely used libc symbol. It even bests <code>memcpy</code> (52,726) and
  <code>free</code> (42,603).</li>
<li><code>MOV</code> is the most frequent x86 instruction, followed by <code>CALL</code>. (I could
  write an entire blog post about observations about x86 instruction use.)</li>
</ul>
<p>There's a trove of data in the SQLite database and the <code>lpa</code> commands only
expose a fraction of it. I reckon a lot of interesting tweets, blog posts,
research papers, and more could be derived from the data that <code>lpa</code> assembles.</p>
<p><code>lpa</code> does all of its work in-process using pure Rust. The Debian and RPM
repository interaction is handled via the
<a href="https://crates.io/crates/debian-packaging">debian-packaging</a> and
<a href="https://crates.io/crates/rpm-repository">rpm-repository</a> crates (which I
wrote). ELF file parsing is handled by the (amazing)
<a href="https://crates.io/crates/object">object</a> crate. And x86 disassembling via
the <a href="https://crates.io/crates/iced-x86">iced-x86</a> crate. Many tools similar
to <code>lpa</code> call out to other processes to interface with <code>.deb</code>/.<code>rpm</code> packages,
parse ELF files, disassemble x86, etc. Doing this in pure Rust makes life so
much simpler as all the functionality is self-contained and I don't have to
worry about run-time dependencies for random tools. This means that <code>lpa</code>
should <em>just work</em> from Windows, macOS, and other non-Linux environments.</p>
<p>Linux Package Analyzer is very much in its infancy. And I don't really
have a grand vision for it. (I built it and some of the packaging code it
is built on) in support of some even grander projects I have cooking.) Please
file bugs, feature requests, and pull requests
<a href="https://github.com/indygreg/PyOxidizer">in GitHub</a>. The project is currently
part of the PyOxidizer repo (because I like monorepos). But I may pull it and
other os/packaging/toolchain code into a new monorepo since target audiences
are different.</p>
<p>I hope others find this tool useful!</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <author>
      <name>Gregory Szorc</name>
      <uri>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog</uri>
    </author>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rust Implementation of Debian Packaging Primitives]]></title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2022/01/03/rust-implementation-of-debian-packaging-primitives" />
    <id>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2022/01/03/rust-implementation-of-debian-packaging-primitives</id>
    <updated>2022-01-03T16:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-03T16:00:00Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="packaging" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Rust" />
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Rust Implementation of Debian Packaging Primitives]]></summary>
    <content type="html" xml:base="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2022/01/03/rust-implementation-of-debian-packaging-primitives"><![CDATA[<p>Does your Linux distribution use tools with <code>apt</code> in their name to manage
system packages? If so, your system packages are using Debian packaging.</p>
<p>Most tools interfacing with Debian packages (<code>.deb</code> files) and repositories
use functionality provided by the <a href="https://salsa.debian.org/apt-team/apt">apt</a>
repository. This repository provides libraries like <code>libapt</code> as well as
tools like <code>apt-get</code> and <code>apt</code>. Most of the functionality is implemented in
C++.</p>
<p>I wanted to raise awareness that I've begun implementing Debian packaging
primitives in pure Rust. The <code>debian-packaging</code> crate is
<a href="https://crates.io/crates/debian-packaging">published on crates.io</a>. For
now, it is developed inside the
<a href="https://github.com/indygreg/PyOxidizer">PyOxidizer repository</a> (because I
like monorepos).</p>
<p>So far, a handful of useful functionality is implemented:</p>
<ul>
<li>Parsing and serializing <a href="https://www.debian.org/doc/debian-policy/ch-controlfields.html">control files</a></li>
<li>Reading repository indices files and parsing their content.</li>
<li>Reading HTTP hosted repositories.</li>
<li>Publishing repositories to the filesystem and S3.</li>
<li>Writing changelog files.</li>
<li>Reading and writing <code>.deb</code> files.</li>
<li>Copying repositories.</li>
<li>Creating repositories.</li>
<li>PGP signing and verification operations.</li>
<li>Parsing and sorting version strings.</li>
<li>Dependency syntax parsing.</li>
<li>Dependency resolution.</li>
</ul>
<p>Hopefully the <a href="https://docs.rs/debian-packaging/0.9.0/debian_packaging/">documentation</a>
contains all you would want to know for how to use the crate.</p>
<p>The crate is designed to be used as a library so any Rust program can
(hopefully) easily tap the power of the Debian packaging ecosystem.</p>
<p>As with most software, there are likely several bugs and many features not yet
implemented. But I have bulk downloaded the entirety of some distribution's
repositories without running into obvious parse/reading failures. So I'm
reasonably confident that important parts of the code (like control file parsing,
repository indices file handling, and <code>.deb</code> file reading) work as advertised.</p>
<p>Hopefully someone out there finds this work useful!</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <author>
      <name>Gregory Szorc</name>
      <uri>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog</uri>
    </author>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pure Rust Implementation of Apple Code Signing]]></title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2021/04/14/pure-rust-implementation-of-apple-code-signing" />
    <id>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2021/04/14/pure-rust-implementation-of-apple-code-signing</id>
    <updated>2021-04-14T13:45:00Z</updated>
    <published>2021-04-14T13:45:00Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="PyOxidizer" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Apple" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Rust" />
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Pure Rust Implementation of Apple Code Signing]]></summary>
    <content type="html" xml:base="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2021/04/14/pure-rust-implementation-of-apple-code-signing"><![CDATA[<p>A few weeks ago I (foolishly?) set out to implement Apple code signing
(what Apple's <code>codesign</code> tool does) in pure Rust.</p>
<p>I wanted to quickly announce on this blog the existence of the project and
the news that as of a few minutes ago, the <code>tugger-apple-codesign</code> crate
implementing the code signing functionality is now
<a href="https://crates.io/crates/tugger-apple-codesign">published on crates.io</a>!</p>
<p>So, you can now sign Apple binaries and bundles on non-Apple hardware by
doing something like this:</p>
<pre><code>$ cargo install tugger-apple-codesign
$ rcodesign sign /path/to/input /path/to/output
</code></pre>
<p>Current features include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Robust support for parsing embedded signatures and most related data
  structures. <code>rcodesign extract</code> can be used to extract various signature
  data in raw or human readable form.</li>
<li>Parse and verify RFC 5652 Cryptographic Message Syntax (CMS) signature
  data.</li>
<li>Sign binaries. If a code signing certificate key pair is provided,
  a CMS signature will be created. This includes support for Time-Stamp Protocol
  (TSP) / RFC 3161 tokens. If no key pair is provided, you get an ad-hoc
  signature.</li>
<li>Signing bundles. Nested bundles and binaries will automatically be signed.
  Non-code resources will be digested and a <code>CodeResources</code> XML file will be
  produced.</li>
</ul>
<p>The most notable missing features are:</p>
<ul>
<li>No support for obtaining signing keys from keychains. If you want to sign
  with a cryptographic key pair, you'll need to point the tool at a PEM encoded
  key pair and CA chain.</li>
<li>No support for parsing the Code Signing Requirements language. We can parse the
  binary encoding produced by <code>csreq -b</code> and convert it back to this DSL. But we
  don't parse the human friendly language.</li>
<li>No support for notarization.</li>
</ul>
<p>All of these could likely be implemented. However, I am not actively working on
any of these features. If you would like to contribute support, make noise in
the <a href="https://github.com/indygreg/apple-platform-rs/issues">GitHub issue tracker</a>.</p>
<p>The Rust API, CLI, and documentation are still a bit rough around the edges. I
haven't performed thorough QA on aspects of the functionality. However, the
tool is able to produce signed binaries that Apple's canonical <code>codesign</code> tool
says are well-formed. So I'm reasonably confident some of the functionality
works as intended. If you find bugs or missing features, please
<a href="https://github.com/indygreg/apple-platform-rs/issues">report them on GitHub</a>. Or even
better: submit pull requests!</p>
<p>As part of this project, I also created and published the
<a href="https://crates.io/crates/cryptographic-message-syntax">cryptographic-message-syntax</a>
crate, which is a pure Rust partial implementation of RFC 5652, which defines
the cryptographic message signing mechanism. This RFC is a bit dated and seems
to have been superseded by RPKI. So you may want to look elsewhere before
inventing new signing mechanisms that use this format.</p>
<p>Finally, it appears the Windows code signing mechanism (Authenticode) also uses
RFC 5652 (or a variant thereof) for cryptographic signatures. So by implementing
Apple code signatures, I believe I've done most of the legwork to implement
Windows/PE signing! I'll probably implement Windows signing in a new crate whenever
I hook up automatic code signing to PyOxidizer, which was the impetus for this work
(I want to make it possible to build distributable Apple programs without Apple
hardware, using as many open source Rust components as possible).</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <author>
      <name>Gregory Szorc</name>
      <uri>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog</uri>
    </author>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rust is for Professionals]]></title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2021/04/13/rust-is-for-professionals" />
    <id>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2021/04/13/rust-is-for-professionals</id>
    <updated>2021-04-13T08:20:00Z</updated>
    <published>2021-04-13T08:20:00Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Programming" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Rust" />
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Rust is for Professionals]]></summary>
    <content type="html" xml:base="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2021/04/13/rust-is-for-professionals"><![CDATA[<p>A professional programmer delivers value through the authoring and maintaining
of software that solves problems. (There are other important ways for
professional programmers to deliver value but this post is about
programming.)</p>
<p>Programmers rely on various tools to author software. Arguably the most
important and consequential choice of tool is the programming language.</p>
<p>In this post, I will articulate why I believe Rust is a highly compelling
choice of a programming language for software professionals. I will state
my case that Rust disposes software to a lower defect rate, reduces total
development and deployment costs, and is exceptionally satisfying to use.
In short, I hope to convince you to learn and deploy Rust.</p>
<h2>My Background and Disclaimers</h2>
<p>Before I go too far, I'm targeting this post towards <em>professional programmers</em> -
people who program (or support programming through roles like management) as
their primary line of work or who spend sufficient time programming outside of
work. I consider myself a <em>professional programmer</em> both because I am a full-time
engineer in the software industry and because I contribute to some significant
open source projects outside of my day job.</p>
<p>The statement <em>Rust is for Professionals</em> does not imply any logical variant
thereof. e.g. I am not implying <em>Rust is not for non-professionals</em>. Rather,
the subject/thesis merely defines the audience I want to speak to: people who
spend a lot of time authoring, maintaining, and supporting software and are
invested in its longer-term outcomes.</p>
<p>I think opinion pieces about programming languages benefit from knowing
the author's experience with programming. I first started hacking on code in
the late 1990's. I've been a full-time software developer since 2007 after
graduating with a degree in Computer Engineering (after an aborted attempt
at Biomedical Engineering - hence my affinities for hardware and biological
sciences). I've programmed in the following languages: C, C++ (only until
C++11), C#, Erlang, Go, JavaScript, Java, Lua, Perl, PHP, Python, Ruby,
Rust, shell, SQL, and Verilog. Notably missing from this list is a Lisp and
a Haskell/Scala type language. Of these languages, I've spent the most time
with C, C#, JavaScript, Perl, PHP, Python, and Rust.</p>
<p>I'm not that strong in computer science or language theory: many colleagues
can talk circles around me when it comes to describing computer science
and programming language concepts like algorithms, type theory, and common terms
used to describe languages. (I have failed many technical interviews because of
my limitations here.) In contrast, I perceive my technical strengths as applying
an engineering rigor and practicality to problem solving. I care vastly more
about how/why things work the way they do and the practical consequences of
decisions/choices we make when it comes to software. I find that I tend to
think about 2nd and 3rd order effects and broader or longer-term consequences
more often than others. Some would call this <em>systems engineering</em>.</p>
<p>I've programmed all kinds of different software. Backend web services,
desktop applications, web sites, Firefox browser internals, the Mercurial
version control tool, build systems, system/machine management. Notably missing
are mobile programming (e.g. iOS/Android) and serious embedded systems (I've
hacked around with Raspberry Pis and Arduinos, but those seem very friendly
compared to other embedded devices). My strongest affinity is probably towards
<em>systems software</em> and general purpose tools: I enjoy building software that
other people use to build things. <em>Infrastructure</em> if you will.</p>
<p>Finally, I am expressing my personal opinion in this post. I do not speak for
any employer, present or former. While I would love to see more Rust at my
current employer, this post is not an attempt to influence what happens behind
my employer's walls: there a better ways to conduct successful
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nemawashi">nemawashi / </a> than a public
blog post. I am not affiliated with the Rust Project in any capacity
beyond a very infrequent code contributor and issue filer: I view myself as a
normal Rust user. I did work at Mozilla - the company who bankrolled most of
Rust's initial development. I even briefly worked in the same small Vancouver
office as Graydon Hoare, Rust's primary credited inventor! While I was keen for
Rust to succeed because it was affiliated with my then employer, I was most
definitely not a Rust evangelist or fan boy while at Mozilla. I have little
to personally benefit from this post: I'm writing it because I enjoy writing
and I believe the message is important.</p>
<p>With that out of the way, let's talk about Rust!</p>
<h2>Rust Makes Me Irrationally Giddy</h2>
<p>When I look back at my professional self when I was in my 20s, I feel like I was
young and dumb and overly exuberant about computers, technology, new software, and
the like. An older, more grizzled professional, I now accept the reality that it is
a miracle computers and software work as well as they do as often as they do. Point
at any common task on a computer and an iceberg of complexity and nuance lingers
under the surface. Our industry is abound in the repetition of proven sub-optimal
ideas. You see practices cargo culted across the decades (like the
<a href="http://exple.tive.org/blarg/2019/10/23/80x25/">80 character terminal/line width</a> and
<a href="http://exple.tive.org/blarg/2020/11/26/punching-holes/">null-terminated strings</a>,
which can both be traced back to Hollerith punchcards from the late 19th century).
You witness cycles of pendulum swings, the same fads and trends, just with different
labels (microservices are the new SOA, YAML is the new XML, etc). I can definitely
relate to people in this industry who want to drop everything and move to a farm or
something (but I grew up in Indiana and had cows living down the street, so I
know this lifestyle isn't for me).</p>
<p><strong>Rust is the first programming language I've encountered in years that makes
me excited. And not just normal excited: irrationally excited. Like the kind
of excitement you have for something when you are naive about its limitations
and don't know any better (like many blockchain/cryptocurrency advocates). I
feel like the discovery of Rust is transporting me back to my younger self,
before I discovered the ugly realities of how computers and software work, and
is giving me hope that better tools, better ways of building software could
actually exist. To channel my inner Marie Kondo: Rust sparks joy.</strong></p>
<p>When I started learning Rust in earnest in 2018, I thought this was a fluke. <em>It
is just the butterflies you get when you think you fall in love,</em> I told myself.
<em>Give it time: your irrational excitement will fade.</em> But after using Rust for
~2.5 years now, my positive feelings about it have only grown <em>stronger</em>. There's
a reason Rust has
<a href="https://insights.stackoverflow.com/survey/2020#technology-most-loved-dreaded-and-wanted-languages-loved">claimed the top spot in Stack Overflow's most loved languages survey</a>
for 5 years and running. And not by the skin of its teeth: Rust is blowing
the competition out of the water. 19% over TypeScript and Python. 23% over Kotlin
and Go. If this were a Forrester report for a company-offered product, Rust
would be the <em>clear market leader</em> and marketers and salespeople would be using
this result to sign up new customers in droves and print money hand over fist.</p>
<p>Let me tell you why Rust excites me.</p>
<h2>Rust is Different (In a Good Way)</h2>
<p>After you've learned enough programming languages, you start to see common
patterns. Manual versus garbage collected memory management. Control flow
primitives like <code>if</code>, <code>else</code>, <code>do</code>, <code>while</code>, <code>for</code>, <code>unless</code>. Nullable types.
Variable declaration syntax. The list goes on.</p>
<p>To me, Rust introduced a number of new concepts, like <code>match</code> for control
flow, enums as algebraic types, the borrow checker, the <code>Option</code> and <code>Result</code>
types/enums and more. There were also behaviors of Rust that were different
from languages I knew: variables are immutable by default, <code>Result</code> types
must be checked they aren't an error to avoid a compiler warning, refusing
to compile if there are detectable memory access issues, and tons more.</p>
<p>Many of the new concepts weren't novel to Rust. But considering I've had exposure
to many popular programming languages, the fact many were new to me means these
aren't common features in <em>mainstream</em> languages. <strong>Learning Rust felt like fresh
air to me: here was a language designed to be general purpose and make inroads into
industry adoption while also willing to buck many of the trends of conventional
language design from the last several decades.</strong></p>
<p>When going against conventional practice, it is very easy to unintentionally
alienate yourself from potential users. Design a programming language too unlike
anything in common use and you are going to have a difficult time attracting
users. This is a problem with many <em>academic</em>/<em>opinionated</em> programming
languages (or so I hear). Rust does venture away from the tried and popular.
And that does contribute to a steeper learning curve. However, there is enough
familiarity in Rust's core language to give you a foothold when learning Rust.
(And Rust's <a href="https://www.rust-lang.org/learn">official learning resources</a> are
terrific.)</p>
<p>I feel like Rust's language designers set out to take a first principles
approach to the language using modern ideas and ignoring old, disproven ones,
realized they needed to ground the language in familiarity to achieve market
penetration, and produced reasonable compromises to yield something that was
new and novel but familiar enough to not completely alienate its large
potential user base.</p>
<p>If you don't like being exposed to new ideas and ways of working, Rust's
approach is probably a negative to you. But if you are like me and enjoy
continuously expanding your knowledge and testing new ideas, Rust's
novelty and willingness to <em>be different</em> is a much welcomed attribute.</p>
<h2>Rust: Toolbox Included</h2>
<p>It used to be that programming languages were just compilers or interpreters.
In recent years, we've seen more and more programming languages bundled
with other tools, such as build/packaging tools, code formatters, linters,
documentation generators, language servers, centralized package repositories,
and more.</p>
<p>I'm not sure what spurred this trend (maybe it was Go?), but I think it is
a good move. Programming languages are ecosystems and the compiler/interpreter
is just one part of a complex system. If you care about end-user experience
and adoption (especially if you are a new language), you want an as turnkey
on-boarding experience as possible. I think that's easier to pull off when
you offer a cohesive, multi-tool strategy to attract and retain users.</p>
<p>We refer to programming languages with a comprehensive standard library as
<em>batteries included</em>. I'm going to refer to programming languages with
additional included tools beyond the compiler/interpreter as <em>toolbox
included</em>.</p>
<p><strong>Rust, is very much a <em>toolbox included</em> language.</strong> (Unless you are installing
it via your Linux distribution: in that case Linux packagers have likely
unbundled all the tools into separate packages, making the experience a bit
more end-user hostile, as Linux packagers tend to do for reasons that
merit their own blog post. If you want to experience Rust the way its
maintainers intended - the <em>Director's Cut</em> if you will - install Rust via
<a href="https://rustup.rs/">rustup</a>.)</p>
<p>In addition to the Rust compiler (<code>rustc</code>) and the Rust standard library,
the following components are all officially developed and offered as part
of the Rust programming language <a href="https://github.com/rust-lang">on GitHub</a>:</p>
<ul>
<li>Cargo - Rust's package manager and build system.</li>
<li>Clippy - A Rust linter.</li>
<li><a href="https://doc.rust-lang.org/rustdoc/what-is-rustdoc.html">rustdoc</a> -
  Documentation generator for Rust projects.</li>
<li>rustfmt - A Rust code formatter.</li>
<li>rls - A Rust <a href="https://langserver.org/">Language Server Protocol</a> implementation.</li>
<li><a href="https://crates.io/">crates.io</a> - Rust's official, public package registry.</li>
<li>rustup - Previously mentioned Rust installer.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/vscode-rust">vscode-rust</a> - Visual Studio Code
  extension adding support for Rust. (JetBrains has their own high quality
  extension for their IDEs, which they develop themselves.)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/book">The Rust Programming Language</a> Book</li>
<li>And many more.</li>
</ul>
<p>As an end-user, having all these tools and resources at my fingertips,
maintained by the official Rust project is an absolute joy.</p>
<p>For the local tools, <code>rustup</code> ensures they are upgraded as a group, so I don't
have to worry about managing them. I periodically run <code>rustup update</code> to
ensure my Rust <em>toolbox</em> is up-to-date and that's all I have to do.</p>
<p>Contrast with say Node.js, <a href="https://xkcd.com/1987/">Python</a>, and Ruby, where
the package manager is on a separate release cadence from the core language
and I have to think about managing multiple tools. (Rust will likely have
to cross this bridge once there are multiple implementations of Rust or
multiple popular package managers. But until then, things are very simple.)</p>
<p>Further contrast with languages like JavaScript/Node.js, Python, and Ruby,
where tools like a code formatter, linter, and documentation generator
aren't always developed under the core project umbrella. As an end-user,
you have to know to seek out these additional value-add tools. Furthermore,
you have to know which ones to use and how to configure them. The
fragmentation also tends to yield varying levels of quality and end-user
experience, to the detriment of end-users. The Rust toolbox, by contrast,
feels simple and polished.</p>
<p><strong>Rust's <em>toolbox included</em> approach enables me to follow unified practices
(arguably best practices) while expending minimal effort.</strong> As a result,
the following tend to be very similar across nearly every Rust project you'll
run into:</p>
<ul>
<li>Code formatting. (Nearly everyone uses <code>rustfmt</code>.)</li>
<li>Adherence to common coding and style conventions. (Nearly everyone uses
  <code>clippy</code>.)</li>
<li>Project documentation. (Nearly everyone uses <code>rustdoc</code>.)</li>
</ul>
<p>Cargo could warrant its own dedicated section. But I'll briefly touch on it
here.</p>
<p>Cargo is Rust's official package manager and build system. With <code>cargo</code>, you
can:</p>
<ul>
<li>Create new Rust projects with a common project layout.</li>
<li>Build projects.</li>
<li>Run project tests.</li>
<li>Update project dependencies.</li>
<li>Generate project documentation (via <code>rustdoc</code>).</li>
<li>Install other Rust projects from source.</li>
<li>Publish packages to Rust package registries.</li>
</ul>
<p>As a build system, Cargo is generally a breeze to work with. Configuration
files are TOML. Adding dependencies is often a 1 line addition to a
<code>Cargo.toml</code> file. Dependencies often <em>just work</em> on the first try. It's
not like say C/C++, where taking on a new dependency can easily consume
a day or two to get it integrated in your build system and compatible with
your source code base. <strong>I can't emphasize enough how much joy it brings
to be able to leverage an <em>it just works</em> build tool for systems-level
programming: I'm finding myself doing things in Rust like parsing ELF, PE,
and Mach-O binaries because it is so easy to integrate low-level functionality
like this into any Rust program.</strong> Cargo is <em>boring</em>. And when it comes to
build systems, that's a massive compliment!</p>
<p>No other language I've used has as comprehensive and powerful of a
<em>toolbox</em> as Rust does. This <em>toolbox</em> is highly leveraged by the Rust
community, resulting is remarkable consistency across projects. This
consistency makes it easier to understand, use, and contribute back to
other Rust projects. Contrast this with say C/C++, where large code bases
often employ multiple tools in the same space on different parts of the
same code base, leading to cognitive dissonance and overhead.</p>
<p>As a professional programmer, Rust's powerful and friendly <em>toolbox</em>
enables me to build Rust software more easily than with other languages.
I spend less time wrangling tools and more time coding. That translates
to less overhead delivering value through software. Other languages
would be wise to emulate aspects of Rust's model.</p>
<h2>Rust is Humane</h2>
<p>Of all the programming languages I've used, Rust seems to empathize
with its users the most.</p>
<p>There's a few facets to this.</p>
<p>A lot of care seems to have gone into the end-user experience of the
Rust <em>toolbox</em>.</p>
<p>The Rust compiler often gives extremely actionable error and warning
messages. If something is wrong, it tells me why it is wrong, often
pointing out exactly where in source code the problem resides, drawing
carets to the source code where things went wrong. In many cases,
the compiler will emit a suggested fix, which I can incorporate
automatically by pressing a few keys in my IDE. Contrast this with
C/C++ and even Go, which tend to have either too-terse-to-be-actionable
or too-verbose-to-make-sense-of feedback. By comparison, output from
other compilers often comes across as condescending, as if they are
saying <em>git gud, idiot</em>. Rust's compiler output tends to come across
as <em>I'm sorry you had a problem: how can I help?</em> I feel like the
compiler actually cares about my [valuable] time and satisfaction.
It wants to keep me in
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flow_(psychology)">flow</a>.</p>
<p>Then there's <a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust-clippy">Clippy</a>, a
Rust linter maintained as part of the Rust project.</p>
<p>One thing I love about Clippy is - like the compiler - many of the lints
contain suggestions, which I can incorporate automatically through my
IDE. So many other linters just tell you what is wrong and don't seem
to go the extra mile to be respectful of my time by offering to fix it
for me.</p>
<p><strong>Another aspect of Clippy I love is it is like having an invisible Rust
mentor continuously providing constructive feedback to help me level-up my
Rust.</strong> I don't know how many times I've written Rust code similarly to how I
would write code in other languages and Clippy suggests a more <em>Rustic</em>
solution. Most of the time I'm like <em>oh, I didn't know about that: that's
a much better pattern/solution than what I wrote!</em></p>
<p>Do I agree with Clippy all the time? Nope. But I do find its signal to
noise ratio is exceptionally high compared to other linters I've used.
And Clippy is trivial to configure and override, so disagreements are
easy to manage. Like the Rust compiler, I feel that Clippy is respectful
of my time and has the long term maintainability and correctness of my
software at heart.</p>
<p>Then there's the Rust Community - the people behind the core Rust projects.
<strong>The Rust Community is one of the most professional and welcoming I've
seen.</strong> Their <a href="https://www.rust-lang.org/policies/code-of-conduct">Code of Conduct</a>
is sufficiently comprehensive and actionable. They have their vigorous
debates like any other community. But the conversation is civil. Bad
apples are discarded when they crop up.</p>
<p>At a talk I made about PyOxidizer at a Rust meetup a few years back,
I made a comment in passing about a negative comment I encountered on
a Rust sub-Reddit. After the talk, a moderator of that sub who was in
the audience (unbeknownst to me) approached for more information so they
could investigate, which they did.</p>
<p>I once tweeted about a somewhat confusing, not-very-actionable compiler
error I encountered. A few minutes later, some compiler developers were
conversing in replies. A few hours later, a pull request was created and
a much better error message was merged in short order. I'm not a special
one-off here either: I've stumbled across Stack Overflow questions and
other forums where Rust core developers see that someone is encountering
a confusing issue, question the process that got them to that point, and
then make refinements to minimize it from happening in the future. The
practice is very similar to what empathetic product managers and user
experience designers do.</p>
<p>Not many other communities (or companies for that matter) seem to
demonstrate such a high level of compassion and empathy for their
users. To be honest, I'm not sure how Rust manages to pull it off,
as this tends to be very expensive in terms of people time and it can
be very easy to not prioritize. One thing is for certain: <strong>the Rust Community
is loaded with empathetic people who care about the well-being of users
of their products. And it shows from the interaction in forums to
the software tools they produce. To everyone who has contributed in the
Rust Community: thank you for all that you have done and for setting an
example for the rest of us to live up to.</strong></p>
<h2>Rust is Surprisingly High Level</h2>
<p>One of the reasons I avoided learning Rust for years is that I perceived
it was too low level and therefore tedious. Rust was being advertised as
a <em>systems programming language</em> and you would hear stories of <em>fighting
the borrow checker</em>. I assumed I'd need to be thinking a lot about memory
and ownership. I assumed the cost to author and maintain Rust code would be
high. I thought Rust would be <em>a safer C/C++</em>, with many of the software
development lifecycle caveats that apply. And for the software I was
writing at a time, the value proposition of Rust seemed weak. I thought
a combination of C and say Python was <em>good enough</em>. When I started
writing <a href="https://github.com/indygreg/PyOxidizer">PyOxidizer</a>, I initially
thought only the run-time code calling into the Python interpreter C APIs
would be written in Rust and the rest would be Python.</p>
<p>How wrong I was!</p>
<p><strong>When I actually started coding Rust, I was shocked at how high-level it
felt.</strong> Now, depending on the space of your software, Rust code can be
very low-level and tedious (not unlike C/C++). However, <strong>for the
vast majority of code I author, Rust feels more like Python than C</strong>. And
even the lower-level code feels much higher level than C or even C++.</p>
<p>In my mind, <strong>the expressiveness of Rust comes very close to higher-level,
dynamic languages (like JavaScript, Python, and Ruby) while maintaining
the raw speed of C/C++ all without sacrificing low-level control for
cases when you need it. And it does all of this while maintaining strong
safety guarantees</strong> (unlike say Go, which has the
<a href="https://www.infoq.com/presentations/Null-References-The-Billion-Dollar-Mistake-Tony-Hoare/">billion dollar mistake</a>:
null references).</p>
<p>I had a mental Venn diagram of the properties of programming languages
(gc versus non-gc, static versus dynamic typing, compiled versus interpreted,
etc) and which traits (like execution speed, development time, etc) would
be possible and Rust invalidated large parts of that model!</p>
<p><strong>You often don't need to think about memory management in Rust</strong>: once you
understand the rules the borrow checker enforces, memory is largely something
that exists but is managed for you by the language, just like in garbage
collected languages. Of course there are scenarios where you should
absolutely be thinking about memory and should have a grasp on what Rust
is doing under the hood. But in my experience, most code can be blissfully
ignorant of what is actually happening at the memory level. (However,
awareness of value <em>ownership</em> when programming Rust does add overhead, so
it's not like the cognitive load required for reasoning about memory
disappears completely.)</p>
<p>Rust has both a stack and a heap. But when programming you often don't
need to distinguish these locations. You can do things in Rust like
return a reference to a stack allocated value and pass this reference around
to other functions. This would be a CVE factory in C/C++. But because of
Rust's borrow checker, this is safe (and a common practice) in Rust.
It also predisposes the code towards better performance! Often in C/C++
you will allocate on the heap because you need to return a reference to
memory and returning a reference to a stack allocated value is extremely
dangerous. This heap allocation incurs run-time overhead. So Rust allowing
you to do the fast thing safely is a nice mini win.</p>
<p>In many statically typed languages, I feel like my programming speed
is substantially reduced by having to repeatedly spell out or think
about type names. In C, it feels like I'm always writing type names
so I can perform casting. Newer versions of C++ and Java have improved
matters significantly (e.g. the <code>auto</code> keyword). However, I haven't
programmed them enough recently to know how they compare to Rust on this
front. All I know is that I'm writing type names a lot less frequently
in Rust than I thought I would be and that my programming output isn't
limited by my typing speed as much as it historically was in C/C++.</p>
<p>Despite being compiled down to assembly and exposing extremely
low-level control, Rust often feels like a higher-level language. Equivalent
functionality in Rust is often more concise and/or readable than in C/C++,
while performing similarly, all while having substantially stronger safety
guarantees. <strong>As a professional programmer, the value proposition is
blinding: Rust enables me to do more with less, achieve a lower
defect rate, and not sacrifice on performance.</strong></p>
<h2>Correctness, Quality, Execution Speed, and Development Velocity: Pick 4</h2>
<p>The operation of computers and operating systems is exceptionally complex.</p>
<p>All programming languages justifiably attempt to abstract away aspects of
this complexity to make it easier to deliver value through software. For
example:</p>
<ul>
<li>Assembly is hard: here's a higher level language that compiles down to
  assembly or is implemented in a language that does.</li>
<li>Managing memory manually is hard: use garbage collection.</li>
<li>Concurrency is hard: only allow 1 thread to run at a time (JavaScript, Python,
  etc).</li>
<li>Text encoding is hard: <em>strings</em> are Unicode/UTF-8.</li>
<li>Operating systems have different interfaces: here's a pile of abstractions
  in the standard library for things like I/O, networking, filesystem paths,
  etc.</li>
<li>Strong, static typing isn't very flexible and can impose high change costs:
  use dynamic typing.</li>
<li>And tons more.</li>
</ul>
<p>These abstractions often have undesirable consequences/trade-offs:</p>
<ul>
<li>Garbage collection adds run-time overhead (10% is a number that's commonly
  cited).</li>
<li>Garbage collection adds random slowdowns/pauses, making it difficult to
  achieve consistency in long-tail latency optimization (i.e. ensuring
  consistency in P99.9, P99.99, and beyond percentiles).</li>
<li>Interpreted languages tend to be slower than compiled languages unless you
  invest lots of time into a JIT.</li>
<li>Limiting execution to a single thread limits the ability to harness
  the full power of modern CPUs, which tend to have several cores.</li>
<li>Primitives like environment variables, process arguments, and filenames
  aren't guaranteed to be UTF-8 and coercing them to UTF-8 can be lossy.</li>
<li>Dynamic typing doesn't catch as many bugs at <em>compile time</em> and you have
  to be more diligent about guarding against invariants.</li>
<li>And tons more.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>In other words, there are trade-offs with nearly every decision in programming
language and [standard] library design. There are usually no obviously
correct and undesirable consequence-free decisions.</strong></p>
<p><strong>And we further have to consider the fallibility of people and the inevitability
that mistakes will be made, that bugs and regressions will be introduced and will
need addressing. As an industry, we generally accept that mistakes occur and
bugs are an unavoidable aspect of software development. If new features and
enhancements are value, bugs and defects are anti-value. Like financial debt,
existence of bugs and sub-optimal code can be tolerated to varying extents. But
this is a highly nuanced topic and different people, companies, and projects will
have different perspectives on it. We can all agree that bugs are an inevitable
fact of software.</strong></p>
<p>We also need to confront the reality that as an industry we have
very little empirical data that says much of significance about topics
like <a href="https://danluu.com/empirical-pl/">static versus dynamic typing</a>.
Although we do know some things. As Alex Gaynor informs us in
<a href="https://alexgaynor.net/2020/may/27/science-on-memory-unsafety-and-security/">What science can tell us about C and C++'s security</a>,
the result of ~2/3 of security vulnerabilities being caused by memory
unsafety seems to reproduce against a sufficiently diverse set of
projects and companies. That result and the implications of it are
worth paying attention to!</p>
<p>With that being said, let's dive into my take on the matter.</p>
<p><strong>Of all the programming languages I've used, I feel that Rust has the
strongest disposition towards authoring and maintaining correct, high-quality
software. It does this by offering a myriad of features that are designed
to prevent (or at least minimize) defects. In addition, I believe Rust
shifts the detection of defects to earlier in the software development
lifecycle, greatly reducing the cost to mitigate defects and therefore
develop software.</strong></p>
<p>(As an aside, every time the topic of Rust's safety and correctness comes
up, random people on the Internet rush to their keyboards to say things
along the lines of <em>C/C++ and other languages can be made to be just as
safe as Rust: it's the bad programmers who are using C/C++ wrong.</em> To
those people: please stop. Your belief implies the infallibility of people
and machines and that mistakes won't be made. If things like memory unsafety
bugs in C/C++ could be prevented, industry titans like Apple, Google, and
Microsoft would have found a way. These companies are likely taking many
more measures to prevent security vulnerabilities than you are and
yet the ~2/3 of security vulnerabilities being caused by memory unsafety
(read: humans and machines failing to reason about run-time behavior)
result still occurs. <strong>To the wiser among us, I urge you to call out
perpetrators of this <em>good programmers don't create bugs</em> myth when you see
it</strong>, just like you would/should if you encounter racist, sexist, or other
non-inclusive behaviors. The reason is that belief in this myth can lead to
physical or emotional harm, just like non-inclusive -isms. Security bugs,
for example, can lead to disclosure of private or sensitive data, which can
result in real world harm. Think a stalker or abusive former partner
learning where you now live. Or a memory unsafety error in a medical device
leading to device malfunction, injuring or killing a patient. Because this
is a sensitive topic, I want to be clear that I'm not trying to compare the
relative harms incurred by racism, sexism, other -isms, or the <em>mythical
perfect programmer</em>. Rather, all I'm saying is each of these surpass
the minimum threshold of harm incurred that justifies calling out and
stopping the harmful behavior. I believe that as professionals we have an
ethical and professional obligation to actively squash the <em>mythical
perfect programmer</em> fallacy when we encounter it. Debates on the merits
and limits of tools to prevent/find defects is fine: belief in the <em>perfect
programmer</em> is not. Sorry for the mini rant: I just get upset by people who
think software exists in a vacuum and doesn't have real-world implications
for people's safety.)</p>
<p>In the sections below, I'll outline some of Rust's features and behaviors
that support my assertion that Rust is biased towards correct and higher
quality outcomes and lowers total development cost.</p>
<h3>The Borrow Checker</h3>
<p>To the uninitiated, the borrow checker is perhaps Rust's most novel contribution
to programming. It is a compile time mechanism that enforces various rules about
how Rust code must behave. Think of these as <em>laws</em> that Rust code must obey.
But these are more like societal laws, not scientific laws (which are
irrefutable), as Rust's laws can be broken, often leading to negative
consequences, just like societal laws.</p>
<p>Rust's <a href="https://doc.rust-lang.org/book/ch04-01-what-is-ownership.html">ownership</a>
rules are as follows:</p>
<ul>
<li>Each value in Rust has a variable that's called its owner.</li>
<li>There can only be one owner at a time.</li>
<li>When the owner goes out of scope, the value will be dropped / released.</li>
</ul>
<p>Then there are rules about
<a href="https://doc.rust-lang.org/book/ch04-02-references-and-borrowing.html">references</a>
(think <em>intelligent pointers</em>) to owned values:</p>
<ul>
<li>At any given time, you can have either one mutable reference or any number of
  immutable references.</li>
<li>References must always be valid.</li>
</ul>
<p>Put together, these rules say:</p>
<ul>
<li>There is only a single canonical owner of any given value at any
  given time. The owner automatically releases/frees the value when it is
  no longer needed (just like a garbage collected language does when the
  reference count goes to 0).</li>
<li>If there are references to an owned value, that reference must be valid
  (the owned value hasn't been dropped/released) and you can only have
  either multiple readers or a single writer (not e.g. a reader and a
  writer).</li>
</ul>
<p>The implications of these rules on the behavior of Rust code are significant:</p>
<ul>
<li>Use after free isn't something you have to worry about because references
  can't point to dropped/released values.</li>
<li>Buffer underruns, overflows, and other illegal memory access can't
  exist because references must be valid and point to an owned value /
  memory range.</li>
<li>Memory level data races are prevented because the <em>single writer or multiple
  readers</em> rule prevents concurrent reading and writing. (An assertion here
  is any guards - like locks and mutexes - have appropriate barriers/fences
  in place to ensure correct behavior in multi-threaded contexts. The ones
  in the standard library should.)</li>
</ul>
<p>I used to think that these rules <em>limited</em> the behavior of Rust code. That
statement is true. However, as I've thought about it more, I've refined
my take to be that <strong>ownership and reference rules reinforce properties that
well-behaved software exhibits.</strong></p>
<p>If a C/C++ program had illegal memory access, you would say it is <em>buggy</em> and
the behavior is not <em>correct</em>. If a Java program attempted to mutate a value
on thread A without a lock or other synchronization primitive and thread B
raced to read it, leading to data inconsistency, you would also call that a
<em>bug</em> and <em>incorrect</em> behavior. If a JavaScript/Python/Ruby function were
changed such that it started mutating a value that should be constant, you
would call that a <em>bug</em> and <em>incorrect</em> behavior.</p>
<p><strong>While Rust's ownership and reference rules do limit what software can
do, the functionality they are limiting is often <em>unsafe</em> or <em>buggy</em>, so
losing this functionality is often desirable from a quality and correctness
standpoint. Put another way, Rust's borrow checker eliminates entire
classes of [common] bugs by preventing patterns that lead to incorrect,
buggy behavior.</strong></p>
<p>This. Is. Huge.</p>
<p><strong>Rust's borrow checker catches bugs for which other languages have no
automated mechanism or no low cost, low latency mechanism for detecting.</strong>
There are ways to achieve aspects of what the borrow checker does in other
languages. But they tend to require contorting your coding style to
accomplish and/or employing high cost tools (often running asynchronously
to the compiler) such as {address, memory, thread} sanitizers or fuzzing.
With Rust, you get this bug detection built into the language and compiler:
no additional tools needed. (I'm not saying you shouldn't run additional
tools like sanitizers or fuzz testing against Rust: just that you get a
significant benefit of these tools for a drastically lower cost since they
are built in to the core language.)</p>
<p>Rust's ownership and reference rules help ensure your software is more
well-behaved and bug-free. But, sometimes those rules are too strict.
Fortunately, Rust isn't dogmatic about enforcing them. There are legitimate
cases where you can't work in the confines of these rules.</p>
<p>Say you want to share a cache between multiple threads. Caches need to be
both readable and writable by multiple threads. This violates
the reference rules and maybe the single owner ownership rule, depending on
how things are implemented. Fortunately, there are primitives in the
<a href="https://doc.rust-lang.org/std/sync/index.html">std::sync</a> module like
<a href="https://doc.rust-lang.org/std/sync/struct.RwLock.html">RwLock</a>
and <a href="https://doc.rust-lang.org/std/sync/struct.Arc.html">Arc</a> (atomically
reference counted) you can use here. <code>Arc</code> (and its non-threadsafe <code>Rc</code>
counterpart) give you reference counting, just like a garbage collected
language. Primitives like <code>RwLock</code> allow you to wrap an inner value
and temporarily <em>acquire</em> an appropriate reference to it, mutable or
non-mutable. There's a bit of slight of hand here, but the tricks
employed enable you to satisfy the ownership and reference rules and
use common programming techniques and patterns while still having the
<em>safety</em> and <em>correctness</em> protections the borrow checker enforces.</p>
<h3>Data Races: What Data Races?</h3>
<p>Multi-threaded and concurrent programming is hard. Really hard. Like it
is exceptionally easy to introduce hard-to-diagnose-and-debug bugs hard.</p>
<p>There are many reasons for this. We can all probably relate to the fact
that reasoning about multi-threaded code is just hard: instead of 1 call
stack to reason about there are N. Further complicating matters are that
many of us don't have a firm grasp on how memory works at a very low level.
Do you know all the ins and outs on how CPU caches work on the architecture
you are targeting? Me neither! (But
<a href="https://software.rajivprab.com/2018/04/29/myths-programmers-believe-about-cpu-caches/">this</a>
is a very good place to start excavating a rabbit hole.)</p>
<p>If you are like me, you've spent many years of your professional career
not having to care about multi-threading or concurrent programming because you
spend so much time in languages with single threads, are only implementing code
that runs in single threaded contexts, or you've recognized the reality that
implementing this code safely and correctly is hard and you've intentionally
avoided the space or chosen software architectures (like queue-based message
passing) to minimize risks. Or maybe if you are say a Java programmer you
sprinkle <code>synchronized</code> everywhere out of precaution or in response to race
conditions / bugs once they are found. (Everyone's personal experience is
different, of course.)</p>
<p>Long story short, <strong>the aforementioned ownership and reference rules enforced
by the borrow checker eliminate data races.</strong> This was a major <em>oh wow</em>
moment for me when I learned Rust: I had heard about memory safety but didn't
realize the same forces behind it were also responsible for making concurrency
safe!</p>
<p>This property is referred to as <em>fearless concurrency</em>. I encourage you
to read Aaron Turon's
<a href="https://blog.rust-lang.org/2015/04/10/Fearless-Concurrency.html">Fearless Concurrency</a>
as well as the
<a href="https://doc.rust-lang.org/book/ch16-00-concurrency.html">Fearless Concurrency</a>
chapter in the Rust Book as well.</p>
<h3>Operating Systems Abstractions Ground in Reality</h3>
<p>Rust is the only programming language I've used that attempts to expose
operating system primitives like environment variables, command arguments,
and filesystem paths and doesn't completely mess it up. Truth be told,
this is kind of a niche topic. But as I help maintain a version control
tool which needs to care about preserving content identically across
systems, this topic is near and dear to my heart.</p>
<p>In POSIX land, primitives like environment variables, command arguments,
and filesystem paths are <code>char*</code>, or a bag of null-terminated bytes.</p>
<p>On Windows, these primitives are <code>wchar_t*</code>, or wide bytes.</p>
<p>On both POSIX and Windows, the encoding of the raw bytes can be... complicated.</p>
<p>Nearly every programming language / standard library in existence attempts
to normalize these values to its native string type, which is typically
Unicode or UTF-8. That's doable and correct a lot of the time. Until it
isn't.</p>
<p>Rust, by contrast, has standard library APIs like
<a href="https://doc.rust-lang.org/stable/std/env/fn.vars.html">std::env::vars()</a>
that will coerce operating system values to Rust's UTF-8 backed <code>String</code>
type. But Rust also exposes the
<a href="https://doc.rust-lang.org/stable/std/ffi/struct.OsString.html">OsString</a>
type, which represents operating system native strings. And there are
function variants like
<a href="https://doc.rust-lang.org/stable/std/env/fn.vars_os.html">std::env::vars_os()</a>
to access the raw values instead of the UTF-8 normalized ones.</p>
<p>Rust <a href="https://doc.rust-lang.org/stable/std/path/index.html">paths</a> internally
are stored as <code>OsString</code>, as that as the value passed to the C API
to perform filesystem I/O. However, you can coerce paths to <code>String</code>
easily enough or define paths in terms of <code>String</code> without jumping through
hoops.</p>
<p>The point I'm trying to get across is that Rust's abstractions are ground
in the reality of how computers work. <strong>Given the choice, Rust will rarely
sacrifice the ability to do something correctly.</strong> In cases like operating
system interop, Rust gives you the choice of convenience or correctness,
rather than forcing inconvenience or incorrectness on you, like nearly
every other language.</p>
<h3>Encoding and Enforcing Invariants in the Type System</h3>
<p>Rust <a href="https://doc.rust-lang.org/std/keyword.enum.html">enums</a> are
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Algebraic_data_type">algebraic data types</a>.
Rust enum variants can have values associated with them and Rust enums,
like structs (Rust's main way to define a type), can have
functions/methods hung off of them. Rust enums are effectively
fully-featured, specialized types, where value instances must be a
certain variant of that enum. <strong>This makes Rust enums much more powerful
than in other languages where enums simply map to integer values and/or
can't have associated functions. This power unlocks a lot of possibility
and harnessed the right way can drastically improve correctness of code
and lead to fewer defects.</strong></p>
<p>Programming inevitably needs to deal with invariants, the various
possibilities that can occur. Programmers will reach for control flow
operators to handle these: <em>if x do this</em>, <em>else if y do that</em>, <em>switch</em>
statements, and the like. Handling every possible invariant can be complex,
especially as software evolves over time and the ground beneath you is
constantly shifting.</p>
<p><strong>As you become more familiar with Rust, you'll find yourself encoding
and enforcing invariants in the type system more and more. And enums
are likely the main way you accomplish this.</strong></p>
<p>Let's start with a contrived example. In C/C++, if you had a function
that accepted either an <code>Apple</code> or an <code>Orange</code> value, you might do
something like: <code>void eat(Apple* apple, Orange* orange)</code>. Then you'd
have inline logic like <code>if apple != null</code>. In a dynamically typed
language, you could pass a single argument, but you'd perform inline
type comparison. e.g. with Python you'd write <code>if isinstance(fruit, Apple)</code>.</p>
<p>With Rust, you'd declare and use an enum. e.g.</p>
<div class="pygments_murphy"><pre><span></span><span class="k">struct</span> <span class="nc">Apple</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">{}</span><span class="w"></span>
<span class="k">struct</span> <span class="nc">Orange</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">{}</span><span class="w"></span>

<span class="k">enum</span> <span class="nc">Fruit</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">{</span><span class="w"></span>
<span class="w">    </span><span class="n">Apple</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">Apple</span><span class="p">),</span><span class="w"></span>
<span class="w">    </span><span class="n">Orange</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">Orange</span><span class="p">),</span><span class="w"></span>
<span class="p">}</span><span class="w"></span>

<span class="k">impl</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="n">Fruit</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">{</span><span class="w"></span>
<span class="w">    </span><span class="k">fn</span> <span class="nf">eat</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">&amp;</span><span class="bp">self</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">{</span><span class="w"></span>
<span class="w">        </span><span class="k">match</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="bp">self</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">{</span><span class="w"></span>
<span class="w">            </span><span class="n">Self</span>::<span class="n">Apple</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">apple</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">=&gt;</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">{</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">...</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">},</span><span class="w"></span>
<span class="w">            </span><span class="n">Self</span>::<span class="n">Orange</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">orange</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">=&gt;</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">{</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">...</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">},</span><span class="w"></span>
<span class="w">        </span><span class="p">}</span><span class="w"></span>
<span class="w">    </span><span class="p">}</span><span class="w"></span>
<span class="p">}</span><span class="w"></span>

<span class="kd">let</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="n">apple</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">=</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="n">Fruit</span>::<span class="n">Apple</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">Apple</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">{</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">});</span><span class="w"></span>
<span class="n">apple</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">eat</span><span class="p">();</span><span class="w"></span>
</pre></div>

<p>This (again contrived) example shows how we Rust enum variants can hold
inner values, how we can define methods on Rust enums (so they behave like
regular types), and introduces the <code>match</code> control flow operator.</p>
<p>Quickly, <a href="https://doc.rust-lang.org/book/ch06-02-match.html">match</a> is a
super powerful operator. It will compare its argument against provided
patterns and evaluate the arm that matches. Patterns <strong>must</strong> be comprehensive
or the compiler will error. In the case of enums, if you add a variant - say
<code>Banana</code> for our <code>Fruit</code> example - and fail to add that variant to existing
<code>match</code> expressions, you will get compiler errors!</p>
<p>As you become more proficient with Rust, you'll find yourself moving
lots of (often redundant) control flow expressions and conditional dispatch
(<em>if X do this, if Y do that</em>) into enum variants and encoding the dispatched
actions into that enum/type directly. Conceptually, this is logically
little different from having a base type or interface or by having a single
<em>wrapper</em> class holds various possible values. But the guarantees are stronger
because each distinct possibility is strongly defined as an enum variant.
And when combined with the <code>match</code> control flow operator, you can have
the Rust compiler verify that all variants are accounted for every time
you take conditional action based on the variant.</p>
<p>The 2 most common enums in Rust are <code>Option</code> and <code>Result</code>. The following
sections will explain how they work and further demonstrate how invariants
can be encoded and enforced in Rust's type system.</p>
<h3><code>Option</code>: A Better Way to Handle Nullability</h3>
<p>Many programming languages have the concept of
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nullable_type">nullable types</a>: the ability
for a value to be null or some null-like value. You will often find this
expressed in languages as <code>null</code>, <code>nil</code>, <code>None</code>, or some variant thereof.</p>
<p>When programming in these languages, nullable values <strong>must</strong> be accounted
or it could lead to errors. Languages like C/C++ and Go will attempt to
to resolve the address behind <code>null</code>/<code>nil</code>, leading to at least a program
crash and possibly a security vulnerability. Languages like Java and Python
will raise exceptions (<code>NullPointerException</code> in Java - frequently abbreviated
<code>NPE</code> because it is so common - and likely <code>TypeError</code> in Python).</p>
<p>The prevalence of failure to account for nullable values is a major reason
why null references were coined by their inventor as
<a href="https://www.infoq.com/presentations/Null-References-The-Billion-Dollar-Mistake-Tony-Hoare/">the billion dollar mistake</a>.
(I suspect the real world value is much greater than $1B.)</p>
<p>Having an easy-to-ignore nullable invariant lingering in type systems seems
like a massive foot gun to me. And indeed every programmer with sufficient
experience has likely introduced a bug due to failure to account for null. I
sure have!</p>
<p><strong>Rust doesn't have a null value. Therefore no null references and no
<em>billion dollar mistake</em>. Instead, Rust's standard library has
<a href="https://doc.rust-lang.org/std/option/index.html">Option<T></a>, an enum
representing nullable types / values. And <code>Option</code> is vastly superior to
null values.</strong></p>
<p><code>Option&lt;T&gt;</code> is an enum with 2 variants, <code>Some(T)</code> or <code>None</code>: an instance of some
type or <em>nothing</em>. What makes <code>Option</code> different from languages with null
references is you have to explicitly ask for the inner value: there is no
automatic dereference. <strong>Rust forces you to confront the reality that a
value is nullable and by doing so can drastically reduce a very common bug
class.</strong> I say <em>drastically reduce</em> instead of <em>eliminate</em> because it is
still possible to shoot yourself in the foot. For example, you can call
<a href="https://doc.rust-lang.org/std/option/enum.Option.html#method.unwrap">Option.unwrap()</a>
to obtain the inner value, triggering a panic if the <code>None</code> variant is
present. Despite the potential for programming errors, this solution is
strictly better than null references because <code>Option</code> forces you to confront
the reality of nullability and use of the <em>dangerous</em> access mechanisms is
relatively easy to audit for. (Clippy has some lints to encourage best
practices here.)</p>
<p>The existence of <code>Option&lt;T&gt;</code> means that if you are operating on a non-<code>Option</code>
value, that value is guaranteed to exist and not be null. If you are operating
on <code>Option</code>, the fact it is optional is explicitly encoded in the type and you
know you need to account for it. <strong>If the value passed into a function was once
always defined and a later refactor changed it to be optional (or vice versa), that
semantic change is reflected in the type system and Rust forces you to confront
the implications when that change is made,</strong> not after it was deployed to
production and you started seeing segfaults, NPEs, and the like.</p>
<p><strong>After using Rust's <code>Option&lt;T&gt;</code> to express nullability, you will look at
every other language with null references and bemoan how <em>primitive</em> and
<em>unsafe</em> it feels by comparison. You will yearn for Rust's safer approach
biasing towards correctness and higher quality software.</strong> <code>Option&lt;T&gt;</code> is
massive feature for the professional programmer who cares about these
traits.</p>
<h3><code>Result</code>: A Better Way to Handle Errors</h3>
<p>Different programming languages have different ways of handling errors.
Returning integers or booleans to express success or failure is common.
As is throwing and trapping/catching exceptions.</p>
<p>Like nullability, history has shown us that programmers often fail to
handle error invariants, with bugs of varying severity ensuing. Even Linux
filesystems
<a href="http://research.cs.wisc.edu/wind/Publications/iron-sosp05.pdf">fail</a> to
<a href="http://usenix.org/legacy/event/fast08/tech/full_papers/gunawi/gunawi_html/index.html">handle</a>
errors!</p>
<p><strong>I argue that the traditional programming patterns we use to handle errors bias
towards buggy outcomes, especially with the <em>return an integer/error value</em>
approach.</strong> It is easy to forget to check the return value of a function. In
C/C++, maybe a function once returned nothing (<code>void</code>) and was later refactored
to return an integer error code. You have to know to audit for existing callers
when making these changes or updating dependencies. Furthermore, handling errors
requires effort. That <code>if err != 0</code> or <code>if err != nil</code> pattern gets mighty
annoying to type all of the time! Plus, you have to know what value to compare
against: <em>success</em> can often be 0, -1, or 1 or any other arbitrary value.
<strong>Getting error handling correct 100% of the time is <em>hard</em>. You will fail and
this will lead to bugs.</strong></p>
<p><a href="https://doc.rust-lang.org/std/result/index.html">Result<T, E></a> is Rust's
primary/preferred mechanism for propagating errors and it is different
from traditional approaches.</p>
<p>Like <code>Option&lt;T&gt;</code>, <code>Result&lt;T, E&gt;</code> is an enum with 2 variants: <code>Ok(T)</code> and
<code>Err(E)</code>. That is, a value is either <em>success</em>, wrapping an inner value of
type <code>T</code> or <em>error</em>, wrapping an inner value of type <code>E</code> describing that
error.</p>
<p>Like <code>Option&lt;T&gt;</code>, <code>Result&lt;T, E&gt;</code> forces you to confront the existence of
invariants. Before operating on the value returned by a function, you need
to explicitly access it and that forces you to confront that an error could
have occurred. In addition, the <code>Result</code> type is
<a href="https://doc.rust-lang.org/std/result/index.html#results-must-be-used">annotated</a>
and the compiler will emit a warning when you don't check it. Scenarios like
changing an infallible function returning a type <code>T</code> to fallible returning a
<code>Result&lt;T, E&gt;</code> will fail to compile (due to typing violations) or make compiler
warning noise if there are call sites that fail to account for that change.</p>
<p>In addition to making it more likely that errors are acted upon correctly,
Rust also contains a
<a href="https://doc.rust-lang.org/std/result/index.html#the-question-mark-operator-">? operator</a>
for simplifying handling of errors.</p>
<p>As I said above, typing patterns like <code>if err != 0</code> or <code>if err != nil</code> can become
extremely tedious. Your brain knows what it needs to type to handle errors
but it takes precious seconds to do so, slowing you down. You may have code where
the majority of the lines are the same error handling boilerplate over and over,
increasing verbosity and arguably decreasing readability.</p>
<p>Rust's <code>?</code> operator will <code>return</code> an <code>Err(E)</code> variant or evaluate to the
inner value from the <code>Ok(T)</code> variant. So you can often add an <code>?</code>
operator after a function call returning a <code>Result&lt;T, E&gt;</code> to automatically
propagate an error. Typing a single character is vastly easier and simpler
than writing explicit control flow for error handling!</p>
<p>The benefits of <code>?</code> are blatantly apparent when you have functions calling
into multiple fallible functions. Long functions with multiple <code>if err != 0</code>
blocks followed by the next logical operation often reduce to a 1-liner. e.g.
<code>bar(foo()?)?</code> or <code>foo.do_x()?.do_y()?</code>. When I said earlier that Rust feels
like a higher level language, the <code>?</code> operator is a significant contributor to
that.</p>
<p>There are some downsides to <code>Result&lt;T, E&gt;</code> in terms of programming overhead
and consistency between Rust programs. I'll cover these later in the post.</p>
<p><strong><code>Result&lt;T, E&gt;</code> biases Rust code towards correctness by forcing programmers
to confront the reality that an error could exist and should be handled.
Once you program in Rust, you will look at error handling mechanisms like
returning an error integer or nullable value, realize how brittle and/or
tedious they are, and yearn for something better.</strong></p>
<h3>The <code>unsafe</code> Escape Hatch</h3>
<p>If some of Rust's limitations are too much for you, Rust has an
<em>in case of emergency break glass</em> feature called <code>unsafe</code>. This is kind of
like <em>C mode</em> where you can do things like access and manipulate raw memory
through pointers. You can <em>cast</em> a value to a pointer and back to a new Rust
reference/value, effectively short circuiting the borrow checker for that
particular reference/value.</p>
<p><strong>A common misconception is <code>unsafe</code> disables the borrow checker and/or loosens
type checking. This is incorrect: many of those features are still running
in <code>unsafe</code> code.</strong> However, because Rust can't fully reason about what's
happening (e.g. it doesn't know who owns a raw memory address and when
it will be freed), it can't properly enforce all of its rules that guarantee
safety, leading to, well, <em>unsafety</em>. (See
<a href="https://doc.rust-lang.org/book/ch19-01-unsafe-rust.html">Unsafe Rust</a> for
more on this topic.)</p>
<p><code>unsafe</code> is a necessary evil. In many Rust programs, you won't have to
ever use it. But if you do have to use it, its presence will draw review
scrutiny like moths to light. So unlike say C/C++ where practically every
memory access is a potential security bug and it is effectively impossible
in many scenarios to comprehensively audit for memory safety (if there were
there would be no memory safety bugs), using <code>unsafe</code> safely is often viable
because scrutiny can be concentrated on its relatively few occurrences.
And more experienced Rust programmers know how to encapsulate <code>unsafe</code> into
<em>safe</em> wrappers, limiting how much code needs to be audited when code
around <code>unsafe</code> changes.</p>
<p>What I've personally been enlightened by is the myriad of operations
that Rust considers <em>unsafe</em>. As you learn more and more Rust, you'll
encounter random functions sprinkled across the standard library that
are <code>unsafe</code> and you'll wonder why. The docs usually tell you and that's
how you learn something new (and maybe horrifying) about how computers
actually work.</p>
<h3>Fearless Refactoring</h3>
<p>A significant portion of the software development lifecycle is evolving
existing code. Fixing bugs. Extending existing code with new
functionality. Refactoring code to fix bugs or prepare for new features.
Using code in new, unplanned ways.</p>
<p>In many code bases, the amount of people time spent evolving the code
dwarfs the time for creating actual greenfield code/features.
(Unfortunately, quantifying when you are doing <em>evolution</em> versus
greenfield coding is quite difficult, so both facets often get lumped
together into simply <em>software development time</em>. But in my mind they are
discrete - although highly interdependent - units of work and the evolution
time tends to dwarf the greenfield time on established projects.) <strong>So it
follows that long-term evolution/maintainability of code bases is more
important than initial code creation time.</strong></p>
<p><strong>There is a sufficient body of industry research demonstrating that the
cost to fix defects rises exponentially as you progress through the
software development lifecycle</strong> (do a search for say <em>software development
lifecycle cost of fixing a bug</em>).</p>
<p>Furthermore, human memory functions not unlike multi-tier caches and your
ability to recall information will diminish over time. (You probably know
what you were doing 5 minutes ago, might remember what you were doing at
this time yesterday, and probably have no clue what you were doing on this
date 20 years ago.)</p>
<p><strong>In terms of coding, the best way to address a defect is to not introduce
it in the first place. If you can't do that, your goal is to detect and
correct it as early in the development process as possible, as close as
possible to when the source code creating that defect came into existence.</strong>
Practically, in order of descending desirability:</p>
<ol>
<li>Don't introduce defect (this is impossible because humans are fallible).</li>
<li>Detect and correct defect as soon as the bad key press occurs (within
   reason: you don't want the programmer to lose too much flow) (milliseconds
   later).</li>
<li>At next build / test time (seconds or minutes later).</li>
<li>When code is shared with others (maybe you push a branch and CI tells
   you something is wrong) (minutes to days later).</li>
<li>During code review (minutes to days later).</li>
<li>When code is integrated (e.g. merged) (minutes to days later).</li>
<li>When code is deployed (minutes to days or even months later).</li>
<li>When a bug is reported long after the code has been deployed (weeks
   to years later).</li>
</ol>
<p>The earlier a defect is caught, the better the chances that the author
(or other involved parties) have relevant code <em>paged in</em> and can fix it
with less effort and with lower chances of introducing additional defects.
For me, authoring new code is relatively easy compared to refactoring old
code. That's because I have new code fully paged into my brain and I know
it like the back of my hand. I know where the sharp edges are and how
you'll get cut if you make certain changes. However, if several months
pass without revisiting the code, most of that heightened awareness
evaporates. If I need to change or review that code, my ability to do
that with a high degree of confidence and efficiency is drastically
eroded.</p>
<p>Generally speaking, the earlier a defect is caught, the less damage it can
do. Ideally, a defect is caught and fixed at local development time, before
you burden a reviewer with finding it and certainly before it causes harm or
anti-value after being deployed!</p>
<p>In addition, compressing the software development lifecycle allows you
to ship enhancements sooner, which enables you to deliver value sooner.
This is what we're trying to do as professional programmers after all!</p>
<p><strong>Because the cost to fix a defect rises exponentially as it moves through
the software development lifecycle, it follows that you want defect
detection to occur logarithmically to offset that cost.</strong> That means you
want as many defects as possible to be caught as early as possible.</p>
<p><strong>Compared to other programming languages I've used, Rust is exceptional
at detecting defects earlier in the development lifecycle and as a result
can drastically lower overall development costs.</strong> Here are the main factors
contributing to this belief:</p>
<ul>
<li>The type system is relatively strong and prevents many classes of bugs.</li>
<li>The borrow checker and the rules it enforces prevent <em>safety</em> issues
  at <em>compile</em> time. Some of these violations can be detected by other
  languages' compilers. However, in many cases sufficient auditing
  (like {address, memory, thread} sanitizers) is run much less frequently,
  often only in CI tests, which can be hours or days later.</li>
<li>Confidence that the above 2 function as advertised.</li>
<li>Invariants can be encoded and enforced in the type system through features
  like enums being algebraic data types.</li>
<li>Variables are immutable by default and must be explicitly annotated
  as mutable. This forces you to think about where and how data mutation
  occurs, enabling you to spot issues sooner.</li>
<li><code>Option&lt;T&gt;</code> significantly curtails the <em>billion dollar mistake</em>.</li>
<li><code>Result&lt;T, E&gt;</code> forces you to reckon about handling errors.</li>
</ul>
<p>The Rust compiler is just exceptional at detecting common defects.</p>
<p>Did your code refactor introduce a use-after-free or dangling reference?
Don't worry: the borrow checker will detect that. CVE prevented.</p>
<p>Did you introduce a race condition by performing a mutation somewhere
that was previously immutable? The borrow checker will detect that. You
potentially just saved hours of time debugging a hard-to-reproduce bug.</p>
<p>Did you add an enum variant but forget to add that variant to a
<code>match</code> expression? If you avoided using the <em>match all</em> <code>_</code>
expression, the compiler will tell you match arms aren't exhaustive
and give you an error.</p>
<p>Did a value that was previously always defined become nullable? Changing
the type from <code>T</code> to <code>Option&lt;T&gt;</code> will yield compiler errors due to type
mismatch.</p>
<p>Did an <code>Option&lt;T&gt;</code> that was previously always <code>Some(T)</code> suddenly
become <code>None</code>? Hopefully following Rust best practices mean your code
will just work. In the worst case you get a panic (with a stack trace).
But that's on par with say a Java NPE and is strictly better than a
null dereference that you get with languages like C/C++.</p>
<p>Did you change or add a function returning <code>Result&lt;T, E&gt;</code> but forget
to check if that <code>Result</code> is an <code>Ok(T)</code> or <code>Err(E)</code>, the compiler
will tell you.</p>
<p>I could go on. Rust is full of little examples like these where the
core language and standard library nudge you towards working code and
help detect defects earlier during development, saving vast amounts
of time and money later.</p>
<p><strong>The Rust compiler is so good at rooting out problems that many Rust
programmers have adopted the expression, <em>if it compiles it works</em>. This
statement is obviously falsifiable. But compared to every other programming
language I've used, I'm shocked by how often it is true.</strong></p>
<p>For other programming languages, a working compile is the beginning of your
verification or debugging journey. For Rust, it often feels like the hard
part is over and you are almost done. With other languages, you often
have an indefinite number of iterations to fix <em>language defects</em> (like
null dereferences or dynamic typing errors) beyond the compile step. You
need to address these in addition to any <em>logical/intent defects</em> in your
code. And fixing logical/intent defects could introduce more post-compile
defects. As a programmer, you just don't know when the process will be
done. With Rust, the compiler errors tell you exactly what the <em>language
defects</em> are. So by the time you appease the compiler, you are left with
just your <em>logical/intent</em> defects. I greatly prefer the Rust workflow
which separates these because I'm getting clearer feedback on my progress:
I know that once I've addressed all the <em>language defects</em> the compiler
complains about that is <em>just</em> a matter of fixing <em>logical/intent</em>
defects. I know I'm a giant step closer to victory.</p>
<p><a href="https://hbr.org/2011/05/the-power-of-small-wins">The Progress Principle</a>
is a psychological observation that people tend to prefer a series of
more smaller wins over fewer larger wins. And (unexpected) setbacks can
more than offset the benefits of wins. (The book is an easy read and
I've found its insights applicable to software development workflows.)
Whether Rust's language designers realized it or not, Rust's development
workflow plays into our psychological dispositions as described by <em>The
Progress Principle</em>: defects (setbacks) tend to occur earlier (at compile
time), not at unexpected later times (during code review, CI testing,
deploy, etc) and our progress towards a working solution is composed of
small wins, such as fixing compiler errors and knowing when you transition
from <em>language defects</em> into <em>logical/intent</em> defects. For me, this makes
iterating on Rust more <em>fulfilling</em> and <em>enjoyable</em> than other languages.</p>
<h2>Rust Makes You a Better Overall Programmer</h2>
<p>Whether you realize it or not, every programmer has a personal, generalized
model of how to program, how to reason about code, best practices, and
what not. When we program, we specialize that model to the language
and environment/project we're programming for. The mental model that
each of us has its shaped by our experience: which languages we know,
which concepts we've been exposed, mistakes we've made, people we've
worked with and the practices they've instilled.</p>
<p><strong>If for no other reason, you should learn Rust to expand your generalized
model of how to program so that you can apply Rust's principles outside
of Rust.</strong></p>
<p>Before I learned Rust, I had a mental model of the <em>lifetimes</em> of various
values/variables/memory and how they would be used. If I were coding C, I
would attempt to document these in function comments. e.g. if returning a
pointer, the comment would say how long the memory behind that pointer lives
or who is responsible for freeing it. So when I encountered Rust's ownership
and reference rules when learning Rust, they substantially overlapped with
my personal mental model of how you should reason about memory in order to avoid
bugs. I distinctly remember reading the Rust Book and thinking <em>wow, this
seems to be a formalization of some of the concepts and best practices living
in my head!</em></p>
<p>After using Rust for several months, I realized that my prior mental
model around reasoning about <em>safe</em> program behavior was woefully
incomplete and that Rust's was far superior.</p>
<p><strong>Rust's <em>different</em> ways of doing things will inevitably force you to
think about type design, data access patterns, control flow, etc more
than most other programming languages. In most other languages, it is much
easier to just write runnable code and defer the complexity around
ensuring the code is <em>safe</em>/<em>correct</em> and free from certain classes of
bugs, like memory access violations and race conditions. Rust's ways of
doing things forces you to confront many of these problems up-front,
before anything runs.</strong></p>
<p>Rust's stricter model and way about authoring software eventually percolates
into your personal generalized model of how to program in <em>any programming
language</em>. <strong>As you internalize patterns needed to program Rust proficiently,
you will subconsciously cherry-pick aspects of Rust and apply them when
programming in other languages, making you a better programmer in those
languages.</strong></p>
<p>For example, when you program C/C++, you will realize the minefield of
memory safety issues that linger in those languages. Many of those mines
never explode. But knowing Rust and the patterns needed to appease the
borrow checker and write <em>safe</em> code, you have a better sense of where the
mines are located, the patterns that lead to them exploding, and you can
take preemptive steps or apply extra scrutiny to avoid tripping
them. (If you are like me, you'll reach the conclusion that C/C++ is
intrinsically unsafe and is beyond saving, vowing to avoid it as much as
possible because it is just too dangerous to use safely/responsibly.)</p>
<p>Similarly, when programming in any language, you'll probably think more about
variable mutability and non-mutability, even if those languages don't have
the concept of mutability on variables. You'll be more attune to certain
patterns for mutating data: where mutation occurs, who has a mutable
reference, when there are both mutable and non-mutable references in
existence. Again, your knowledge from Rust will subconsciously raise your
awareness for classes of bugs, making you a better programmer.</p>
<p>The same thing applies to multi-threaded programming and race conditions.
After internalizing Rust's model of how to achieve multi-threading safely,
you will probably not look at multi-threading in other languages the same
way again. If you are like me, you will be horrified by how the lack of
Rust's enforced ownership/reference rules predisposes code to so many
horrible and hard-to-debug bugs. Again, you will probably find yourself
changing your approach to multi-threading to minimize risk.</p>
<p>Fun fact: while at Mozilla I heard multiple anecdotes of [very
intelligent] Firefox developers thinking they had found a bug in Rust's
borrow checker because they thought it was impossible for a flagged error
to occur. However, after sufficient investigation the result was always
(maybe with an exception or two because Mozilla adopted Rust very early)
that the Rust compiler was correct and the developer's assertions about
how code could behave was incorrect. In these cases, the Rust compiler
likely prevented hard-to-debug bugs or even exploitable security
vulnerabilities. I remember one developer exclaiming that if the
bug had shipped, it would have taken <em>weeks</em> to debug and would likely
have gone unfixed for <em>years</em> unless its severity warranted staffing.</p>
<p><strong>I strongly feel that I am a better programmer overall after learning
Rust because I find myself applying the [best] practices that Rust enforces
on me when programming in other languages. For this reason, even if you
don't plan to use Rust in any serious capacity, I encourage people to learn
Rust because exposure to its ideas will likely transform the ways you think
about programming for the better.</strong></p>
<h2>Rust Downsides and Dispelling Some Rust Myths</h2>
<p>This post has been rather positive about Rust so far. Rust, like
everything, is far from perfect and it has its downsides. Professionals
know the limitations of their tools and you should know some of the
issues you'll run into when using Rust.</p>
<p>In addition, Rust is still a relatively young and unpopular programming
language. Since relatively few people know Rust, there are a handful of
myths and inaccuracies circling about the language. I'll also dispel some
of those here.</p>
<h3>Steeper Learning Curve</h3>
<p>A common criticism levied against Rust is it is harder to learn than
other programming languages. I think this is a valid concern. My
experience is Rust took longer to learn and level-up than other
languages I've learned recently, notably Go, Kotlin, and Ruby.</p>
<p>I think the primary reason for this is the borrow checker and the
rules it enforces. Many programmers have never encountered forced
following of ownership and reference rules before and this concept is
completely foreign at first. I liken it to <em>a new way to program</em>.
If you only have experience with dynamically typed languages that
will allow you to compile a ham sandwich, there's a good chance you'll
be frustrated by Rust. Rust will likely challenge your conceptions of
how programming should work and may frustrate you in the process.</p>
<p>In addition to the borrow checker itself, there are a myriad of types
and patterns you'll encounter and eventually need to understand to
<em>appease</em> the borrow checker.</p>
<p>Beyond the borrow checker, Rust's standard library is comprehensive and
offers a lot of types and traits. It will take a while to be exposed
to many of them and know when/how to use each.</p>
<p>You will likely be adding 3rd party crates as dependencies to
your project for common functionality not (yet) in the standard library.
These expand the scope of concepts you need to learn.</p>
<p>I hope I'm not scaring anybody away: you can go pretty far in Rust without
encountering or understanding most of the standard library. That being
said, every new type, trait, concept, and crate you learn unlocks new
possibilities and avenues for delivering value through programming. So
there is an incentive to take the time to learn them sooner than later.</p>
<p>I learned Rust mostly independently for a personal project. While
learning resources such as <a href="https://www.rust-lang.org/learn">Learn Rust</a>,
the <a href="https://cheats.rs/">Rust Language Cheat Sheet</a>, and even Clippy
are fantastic, in hindsight I probably would have become more proficient
sooner had I contributed to an existing Rust project and/or had ongoing
technical collaboration with more experienced Rust developers. This is
probably no different than any other programming language. But because of
Rust's steeper learning curve, I think the benefits of peer exposure are
more significant. That being said, I've heard anecdotes of teams with no
Rust experience learning Rust together with successful results. So there's
no formal recipe for success here.</p>
<p>Finally, despite the steeper learning curve, I'd say the return on
investment pays off pretty quickly. As I've argued elsewhere in this
post, the Rust compiler and type system helps prevent many classes of
bugs. So while it may take longer to initially learn and compose idiomatic
Rust code, it won't take long for Rust to offset the time that you would
have spent chasing bugs, performance optimizations, and the like.</p>
<h3>Rust Moves Too Fast</h3>
<p>Rust releases a new version every 6 weeks. By contrast, many other
programming languages release ~yearly. This faster release cadence has
been a common complaint about Rust.</p>
<p>Quickly, I think people conflate release cadence with churn and hardship
from that release cadence. <strong>Generally speaking, release cadence isn't the
thing you care about: it's how disrupted you are from the releases.</strong> If
your old release continues to work just as well as the new release,
release cadence doesn't really matter (many major websites deploy/release
dozens of times per day and you don't care because you can't tell: you only
care when the UI or behavior changes). <strong>So the thing most of us care about
is how frequently Rust releases cause disruption.</strong> And disruption is often
caused by backwards incompatibility and the introduction of new features,
which when adopted, force upgrades.</p>
<p>A few years ago, I think the concern that <em>Rust moves too fast</em> was
valid: there were significant features in seemingly every release and
crates were eager to jump on the new features, forcing you to upgrade
if you wanted to keep your dependency tree up to date. I feel like I
caught the tail end of this relative chaos in 2018-2019.</p>
<p>But in the last 18-24 months, things seem to have quieted down. Many
of the major language features that people were eager to jump on have
landed. The only ongoing churn I'm aware of in Rust is in the async
ecosystem, and that seems to be stabilizing. New Rust releases are
generally pretty quiet in terms of <em>must use</em> features. The last
<em>milestone</em> release in my mind was 1.45 in July 2020, which stabilized
procedural macros. The community was pretty quick to jump on that
feature/release. My Rust projects have targeted 1.45+ for a while now
with minimal issues.</p>
<p>9 months with no major disruptions is on par with the release cadence
of other programming languages.</p>
<p><strong>In my opinion, the concern that <em>Rust moves too fast</em>, while once valid,
no longer generally applies.</strong> Pockets of truth for segments of users caring
about niche and lesser-used features, yes. But nothing that applies to the
entire Rust ecosystem.</p>
<h3>Compiling Is Too Slow</h3>
<p>A lot of people have commented that Rust builds take too long. It is
true: compiling Rust tends to take longer than C/C++, Go, Java, and
other languages requiring an ahead-of-time compile step.</p>
<p>While a lot has been done to make the Rust compiler faster (it feels
substantially faster than it was a few years ago), it still isn't
as fast as other languages.</p>
<p>Not to dismiss the problem, but in a lot of cases, the speed of Rust
compilation is <em>fast enough</em>. Incremental builds for small libraries
or programs will take a few hundred milliseconds to a second or two.
I suspect most of the people complaining about build times today are
developing very large Rust programs (tens of thousands of lines of
code and/or hundreds of dependencies).</p>
<p>A contributing problem to build times is dependency count. The simplicity
of Cargo makes it very easy to accumulate dependencies in Rust and
each additional crate will slow your build down. PyOxidizer has
~400 dependencies at this point in time, for example (I've been
throwing the kitchen sink at it in terms of features).</p>
<p>There are a few things under your control to mitigate this problem.</p>
<p>First, install <a href="https://github.com/mozilla/sccache">sccache</a>, a
transparent compiler cache. By default it caches to the local
filesystem. But you can also point it at Redis, Memcached, or blob
stores in AWS, Azure, or GCP. Firefox's CI uses an S3 backed cache and
the hit rate (for both Rust and C/C++) is 90-99% on nearly every build.
For PyOxidizer - a medium sized Rust project - sccache reduces full
build times from ~53s wall and ~572s CPU to ~32s wall to 225s CPU on
my 16 core Ryzen 5950X. The wall time savings on a lower CPU core count
machine are even more significant.</p>
<p>Speaking of CPU core counts, the second thing you can do is give
yourself access to more CPU cores. Laptops tend to have at most 4
CPU cores. Consider buying desktops or moving builds to remote
machines, often with dozens of CPU cores. This requires spending
money. But when you factor in people time saved and the cost of
that time and the value of someone's happiness/satisfaction, it
can often be justified.</p>
<p>I'm not trying to dismiss the problems that slow builds can impose,
but if you want to justify their cost, you can argue that the Rust
compiler does more at compilation time than other languages and that
this overhead brings benefits, such as preventing bugs earlier in
the software development lifecycle.
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/There_ain%27t_no_such_thing_as_a_free_lunch">There's no such thing as a free lunch</a>
and Rust's relatively slower builds are a <em>tax</em> you pay for the correctness
the compiler guarantees. To me, that's a justifiable trade-off.</p>
<h3>Rust is Too Young or Isn't Production Ready</h3>
<p>The <em>isn't production ready</em> concern is likely disproven by the
existence of Rust in production in critical roles at a sufficient
number of reputable companies. At this point, there are very few
technical reasons to say Rust isn't production ready. Non-technical reasons
such as lack of organizational knowledge or a limited talent pool for
hiring from, yes. But little on the technical front.</p>
<p>The <em>too young</em> part is ultimately a judgement call for how comfortable
you are with new technologies.</p>
<p>I'm generally pretty conservative/skeptical about adopting new technology.
If you are in this industry long enough you eventually get humbled by your
exuberance.</p>
<p>I was probably in the <em>Rust is too young</em> boat as late as 2017, maybe
2018. While I was cheering on Rust as a Mozillian, I was skeptical it
was going to take off. Birthing successfully languages is hard. The
language still seemed to move too fast and have too many missing
features. Things seemed to stabilize around the 2018 edition. That's
also when you started commonly hearing of companies adopting Rust. Lots
of startups at first. Then big companies started joining in.</p>
<p>Today, companies you have heard of like Amazon, Cloudflare,
Discord, Dropbox, Facebook, Google, and Microsoft are adopting Rust to
varying degrees. There are 58,750 published crates on
<a href="https://crates.io/">crates.io</a>.</p>
<p>I won't drop names, but I've heard of Rust <em>spreading like wildfire</em> at
some companies you've heard of. The stories are pretty similar: random
person or team wants to try Rust. Something small and isolated with a
minimal blast radius in case of disaster is tried first. Rust is an
overwhelming success. As more and more people are exposed to Rust, they
<em>see the light</em>, cries for Rust become louder, and it becomes even more
widely adopted.</p>
<h3>The <em>I'm Writing Fewer Bugs</em> Trap</h3>
<p>When I program in Rust, I strongly feel that my base rate of defect introduction
is substantially less than other programming languages. I have confidence that
the Rust compiler coupled with practices like encoding and enforcing invariants
in the type system leads to fewer defects. In some cases I feel like the surface
area for bugs is limited to <em>logical defects</em>, which are mis-expressions of the
human programmer's intent. And since no automated tool can reliably scan for
<em>human intent</em>, there's no way to prevent <em>logical bugs</em>, and that surface area
is the best we can ever expect from automated scanning.</p>
<p>Knowing what tests to write and how much effort to invest in test writing
is a difficult skill to level up and is full of trade-offs. With Rust, I find
myself writing fewer tests than in other languages because I have confidence
that the compiler will detect issues that would otherwise require explicit
testing.</p>
<p>I <em>feel</em> that my beliefs and practices are rooted in reality and justifiable. Yet I
recognize the danger in placing too much faith in my tools, in Rust.</p>
<p>In theory, Rust alleviates the need for running additional verification
tools, like {address, memory, thread} sanitizers because the safe subset
of Rust prevents the issues these tools detect. Many defects caught by
fuzzing are also similarly prevented by the design of Rust (but not all:
fuzzing is generally a good idea).</p>
<p><strong>What I'm trying to say is that it is really easy to fall into a trap where
you are over-confident about the abilities of Rust to prevent defects and
you find yourself letting your guard down and not maintaining testing and
other verification best practices.</strong></p>
<p>I'm still evolving my beliefs in this area. But my general opinion is that you
should still run things like {address, memory, thread} sanitizers and fuzzing
because <code>unsafe</code> likely exists <em>somewhere</em> in the compiled code, as likely does
C or assembly code. And because a chain is only as strong as its weakest link,
it only takes <em>any</em> bug to undermine the <em>safety</em> of the entire system.
So while these additional verification tools likely won't find as many issues
as they would in <em>unsafe</em> languages, I still think it is a good idea to continue
to run them against Rust, especially for <em>high value</em> code bases.</p>
<h3>Error Handling</h3>
<p><code>Result&lt;T, E&gt;</code> isn't a panacea. Because errors are full on types rather
than simple primitives like integers, you need to spend effort reasoning
and coding about how different error types interact. And often you need
to write a bit of boilerplate code to facilitate that interaction. This
can cancel out a lot of the efficiency benefits of Rust's <code>?</code> operator
for handling errors.</p>
<p>There are a handful of 3rd party Rust crates specializing in error
handling that you'll likely to encounter. These include
<a href="https://crates.io/crates/anyhow">anyhow</a>,
<a href="https://crates.io/crates/error-chain">error-chain</a>,
<a href="https://docs.rs/failure/0.1.8/failure/">failure</a>, and
<a href="https://crates.io/crates/thiserror">thiserror</a>.</p>
<p>Rust's error handling landscape can at times feel fragmented and make
you yearn for something more defined/opinionated in the standard library.
The Rust Community recognizes that this is an area that can be improved
and has <a href="https://blog.rust-lang.org/inside-rust/2020/09/18/error-handling-wg-announcement.html">formed</a>
an error handling project group to improve this space. So hopefully we see
some quality of life improvements to error handling in time.</p>
<h2>Conclusion</h2>
<p>I am irrationally effusive about Rust. When I see this level of excitement
in others, I am extremely skeptical. I was skeptical myself when my former
colleagues at Mozilla were talking up Rust years ago. But having used Rust
for 2.5 years now and authored tens of thousands of lines of Rust code, the
initial relationship euphoria has worn off and I am most definitely in love.</p>
<p><strong>Cynically, Rust has ruined in programming in other languages for me. Less
cynically, Rust has spoiled me.</strong></p>
<p>When I look at other languages without the rules enforced by Rust's borrow
checker, all I see are sharp edges waiting to materialize into bugs.</p>
<p>When I look at other languages with <em>weaker</em> type systems, I think about
all the time I spend having to defend against invariants and how much
cognitive load and programming/review effort I need to incur to maintain
the baseline of quality that I get with Rust.</p>
<p>When I look at programming languages like Python, Ruby, and TypeScript
where you can bolt a type system onto a language that doesn't have it, I
think <em>why would I want to do that when I can use an even better type
system while likely achieving much better performance with Rust?</em> (It's
tempting to reach for a metaphor involving lipstick and pigs.)</p>
<p>When I look at other languages, I generally see the same pile of decades
old ideas packaged in different boxes. Some of these ideas are good and
probably timeless (e.g. functions and variables). Some are demonstrably bad
and should be largely excised from common use (e.g. null references - the
<em>billion dollar mistake</em>).</p>
<p>When I interface with Rust's tooling, I feel like it is respectful of my
time and has my best interests (producing working software) at heart. I
feel the maintainers of the tooling care about me.</p>
<p>When I program in Rust, I feel that I'm producing fewer defects overall.
The compiler is catching defects that would otherwise be caught later
in the software development lifecycle, leading to increased software
development costs.</p>
<p>When I interact with Rust's community of people, respect and empathy
abounds.</p>
<p>Does Rust have its problems and limitations? Of course it does: nothing is
perfect! But in my opinion, its trade-offs are often strictly better than
those found in other programming languages I've used.</p>
<p>At the end of the day, Rust is a programming language and therefore a tool.
Adept professionals know not to get too attached to your tools: ultimately
it is the value you deliver, not how you deliver it. (Of course the choice
of tools can significantly impact the quality and timeline of value
delivery!) Will my thoughts on Rust and preferred languages change over time
as the landscape shifts: of course they will! But for the time being, <strong>Rust
brings so much to the table that its <em>competition</em> lacks that I'm overly
excited about Rust and its ability to advance the state of
software/programming and therefore the industry.</strong></p>
<p>In closing, my current CTO uses the phrase <em>commitment to craft</em> as a desired
mindset for their technical organization. That phrase translates to various
themes: higher quality / lower defect rate, build with the long-term in mind,
implement efficient solutions, etc. <strong>Like an artist reaches for a preferred
paintbrush or a chef for a preferred knife because their preferred tool enables
them to better express their craft, I feel that Rust often enables me to better
express the potential of my professional craft more than other programming languages.
I strongly feel that Rust predisposes software to higher quality outcomes - both
in terms of defect rate and run-time efficiency - while also reducing total
development and execution costs over the entire software development lifecycle.
That makes Rust my first choice language - my go-to tool - for many new
projects at this point in time. If you likewise value <em>commitment to craft</em>, I
urge you to explore Rust so that you too can better harness the potential
of our programming craft.</strong></p>
<p>But don't take my word on it, read what
<a href="https://kerkour.com/blog/rust-in-production-2021/">42 companies using Rust in production</a>
have to say.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <author>
      <name>Gregory Szorc</name>
      <uri>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog</uri>
    </author>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Building Standalone Python Applications with PyOxidizer]]></title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2019/06/24/building-standalone-python-applications-with-pyoxidizer" />
    <id>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2019/06/24/building-standalone-python-applications-with-pyoxidizer</id>
    <updated>2019-06-24T09:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-06-24T09:00:00Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Python" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="PyOxidizer" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Rust" />
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Building Standalone Python Applications with PyOxidizer]]></summary>
    <content type="html" xml:base="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2019/06/24/building-standalone-python-applications-with-pyoxidizer"><![CDATA[<p>Python application distribution is generally considered an unsolved
problem. At their PyCon 2019 keynote talk, Russel Keith-Magee
<a href="https://youtu.be/ftP5BQh1-YM?t=2033">identified code distribution</a> as
a potential <em>black swan</em> - an existential threat for longevity - for
Python. In their words, <em>Python hasn't ever had a consistent story for
how I give my code to someone else, especially if that someone else
isn't a developer and just wants to use my application.</em> I completely
agree. And I want to add my opinion that unless your target user is a
Python developer, they shouldn't need to know anything about Python
packaging, Python itself, or even the existence of Python in order to
use your application. (And you can replace <em>Python</em> in the previous
sentence with any programming language or software technology: most
end-users don't care about the technical implementation, they just
want to get stuff done.)</p>
<p>Today, I'm excited to announce the first release of PyOxidizer
(<a href="https://github.com/indygreg/PyOxidizer">project</a>,
<a href="https://pyoxidizer.readthedocs.io/en/latest/">documentation</a>), an open
source utility that aims to solve the Python application distribution
problem! (The installation instructions are in the docs.)</p>
<h2>Standalone Single File, No Dependencies Executable Python Applications</h2>
<p><strong>PyOxidizer's marquee feature is that it can produce a single file
executable containing a fully-featured Python interpreter, its
extensions, standard library, and your application's modules and
resources.</strong> In other words, you can have a single <code>.exe</code> providing
your application. And unlike other tools in this space which tend to
be operating system specific, PyOxidizer works across platforms
(currently Windows, macOS, and Linux - the most popular platforms for
Python today). Executables built with PyOxidizer have minimal
dependencies on the host environment nor do they do anything
complicated at run-time. I believe PyOxidizer is the only open
source tool to have all these attributes.</p>
<p><strong>On Linux, it is possible to build a fully statically linked executable.</strong>
You can drop this executable into a chroot or container where it is the
only file and it will <em>just work</em>. On macOS and Windows, the only
library dependencies are on always-present or extremely common
libraries. More details are
<a href="https://pyoxidizer.readthedocs.io/en/latest/distributing.html">in the docs</a>.</p>
<p>At execution time, binaries built with PyOxidizer do not do anything
special to run the Python interpreter. (Other tools in this space do
things like create a temporary directory or SquashFS filesystem and
extract Python to it.) <strong>PyOxidizer loads everything from memory and there
is no explicit I/O being performed. When you <code>import</code> a Python module,
the bytecode for that module is being loaded from a memory address in
the executable using zero-copy.</strong> This makes PyOxidizer executables
<a href="https://pyoxidizer.readthedocs.io/en/latest/overview.html#faster-python-programs">faster</a>
to start and <code>import</code> - faster than a <code>python</code> executable itself!</p>
<h2>Current Release and Future Roadmap</h2>
<p>Today's release of PyOxidizer is just the first release milestone in
what I envision is a long and successful project history. While my
over-arching goal with PyOxidizer is to <em>solve</em> vast swaths of the
Python application distribution problem, I want to be clear that this
first release comes nowhere close to doing so. I toiled with what
features <em>must</em> be in the initial release. I ultimately decided that
PyOxidizer's current functionality is extremely valuable to <em>some</em>
audiences and that the project has matured to the point where more
eyeballs and users would substantially help its development. (I could
definitely use some help prioritizing which features to work on and
for that I need users and user feedback.)</p>
<p>In today's release, PyOxidizer is good at producing executables
embedding Python. It doesn't yet venture too far into the <em>distribution</em>
part of the problem (I want it to be trivial to produce MSI installers,
DMG images, deb/rpm packages, etc). But on Linux, this is already a huge
step forward because PyOxidizer makes it easy (hopefully!) to produce
binaries that should <em>just work</em> on other machines. (Anyone who has
attempted to distribute Linux applications will tell you how painful this
problem can be.)</p>
<p>Despite its limitations, I believe today's release of PyOxidizer to
be a viable tool for some applications. And I believe PyOxidizer can
start to replace existing tools in this space. (See the
<a href="https://pyoxidizer.readthedocs.io/en/latest/comparisons.html">Comparisons to Other Tools</a>
document for how PyOxidizer compares to other Python packaging and
distribution tools.)</p>
<p>Using today's release of PyOxidizer, larger user-facing applications
using Python (like Dropbox, <a href="https://kodi.tv/">Kodi</a>,
<a href="https://picard.musicbrainz.org/">MusicBrainz Picard</a>, etc) could use
PyOxidizer to produce self-contained executables. This would likely cut
down on installer size, decrease install/update time (fewer files means
faster operations), and hopefully make packaging simpler for application
maintainers. Maintainers of Python utilities could produce self-contained
executables, making their utilities faster to start and easier to
package and distribute.</p>
<h2>New Possibilities and Reliability for Python</h2>
<p>By enabling support for self-contained, single file Python applications,
PyOxidizer opens exciting new doors for Python. Because Python has
historically required an explicit, separate runtime not part of the
executable, Python was not viable (or was a hinderance) in many domains.
For example, if you wanted to use Python to <em>bootstrap</em> a fresh server
or empty container environment, you had a chicken-and-egg problem because
you needed to install Python before you could use it.</p>
<p>Let's take <a href="https://www.ansible.com/">Ansible</a> for example. One of Ansible's
features is that it remotes into a machine and runs things. The way
it does this is it dynamically generates Python scripts locally, uploads
them to the remote machine, and tells the remote to execute them. Those
Python scripts require the existence of a Python interpreter on the
remote machine. This means you need to install Python on a machine before
you can control it with Ansible. Furthermore, because the remote's Python
isn't under Ansible's control, you can assume very little about its behavior
and capabilities, making interaction a bit brittle.</p>
<p>Using PyOxidizer, projects like Ansible could produce a self-contained
executable containing a Python interpreter. They could transfer that
single binary to the remote machine and execute it, instantly giving the
remote machine access to a fully-featured and modern Python interpreter.
From there, the sky is the limit. In Ansible's case, the executable could
contain the full Ansible runtime, along with any 3rd party Python
packages they wanted to leverage. This would allow execution to occur
(possibly mostly independently) on the remote machine. This architecture
is simpler, scales better, would likely result in faster operations, and
would probably improve the quality of life for everyone involved, from
application developers to its end users.</p>
<p><strong>Self-contained Python applications built with PyOxidizer essentially
solve the <em>Python interpreter bootstrapping and reliability</em> problems.</strong>
By providing a Python interpreter and a known set of Python modules, you
provide a highly deterministic and reliable execution environment for your
application. You don't need to fret about which version of Python
is installed: you <em>know</em> which version of Python you are using.
You don't need to worry about which Python packages are installed:
you control explicitly which packages are available. You don't need to
worry about whether you are running in a virtualenv, what <code>sys.path</code>
is set to, whether <code>.pth</code> files come into play, whether various
<code>PYTHON*</code> environment variables can mess up your application, whether
some Linux distribution packaged Python differently, what to put in your
script's <em>shebang</em>, etc: executables built with PyOxidizer behave as
you have instructed them to because they are <em>compiled</em> that way.</p>
<p>All of the concerns in the previous paragraph contribute to a larger
problem in the eyes of application maintainers that can be summarized as
<em>Python isn't reliable</em>. And because <em>Python isn't reliable</em>, many
people reach the conclusion that <em>Python shouldn't be used</em> (this is the
<em>black swan</em> that was referred to earlier). With PyOxidizer, the Python
environment is isolated and highly deterministic making the
reliability problem largely go away. This makes Python a more viable
technology choice. And it enables application maintainers to aggressively
adopt modern Python versions, utilize third party packages fearlessly,
and spend far less time chasing an extremely long tail of issues related
to Python environment variance. Succinctly, application developers can
focus on building great applications instead of toiling with Python
environment problems.</p>
<h2>Project Status</h2>
<p>PyOxidizer is still in its relative infancy. While it is far from
feature complete, I'm mentally committed to working on the remaining
major functionality. The <a href="https://pyoxidizer.readthedocs.io/en/latest/status.html">Status</a>
document lists major missing functionality, lesser missing functionality,
and potential future value-add functionality.</p>
<p>I want PyOxidizer to provide a Python application packaging and
distribution experience that <em>just works</em> with minimal cognitive effort
from Python application maintainers. I have spent a lot of effort
documenting PyOxidizer. I care passionately about user experience and want
everything about PyOxidizer to be simple and frustration free. I
know things aren't there yet. The problems that PyOxidizer is attempting
to solve are hard (that's a reason nobody has solved them well yet). I
know there's details floating around in my head that haven't been
added to the documentation yet. I know there's missing features and
bugs in PyOxidizer. I know there are
<a href="https://pyoxidizer.readthedocs.io/en/latest/packaging_pitfalls.html">Packaging Pitfalls</a>
yet to be discovered.</p>
<p>This is where you come in.</p>
<p><strong>I need your help to make PyOxidizer great.</strong> I encourage Python
application maintainers reading this to head over to
<a href="https://pyoxidizer.readthedocs.io/en/latest/getting_started.html">Getting Started</a>
and the
<a href="https://pyoxidizer.readthedocs.io/en/latest/packaging.html">Packaging User Guide</a>
and try to package your applications with PyOxidizer. If things don't
work, let me know by <a href="https://github.com/indygreg/PyOxidizer/issues">filing an issue</a>.
If you are confused by lack of or unclear documentation, file an issue.
If something frustrates you, file an issue. If you want to suggest I
work on a certain feature or fix a bug, file an issue! Tweet to
<a href="https://twitter.com/indygreg">@indygreg</a> to engage with me there. Join
the <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/pyoxidizer-users">pyoxidizer-users mailing list</a>.
While I feel PyOxidizer is usable today (that's why I'm announcing it),
<strong>I need your feedback to help guide future prioritization.</strong></p>
<p>Finally, I know PyOxidizer has significant implications for some
companies and projects that use Python. While I'm not looking to
enrich myself or make my livelihood from PyOxidizer, if PyOxidizer is
useful to you and you'd like to send money my way as appreciation, you
can do so <a href="https://www.patreon.com/indygreg">on Patreon</a> or
<a href="https://www.paypal.com/cgi-bin/webscr?cmd=_donations&amp;business=gregory%2eszorc%40gmail%2ecom&amp;lc=US&amp;item_name=PyOxidizer&amp;currency_code=USD&amp;bn=PP%2dDonationsBF%3abtn_donate_LG%2egif%3aNonHosted">PayPal</a>.
If not, that's totally fine: I wouldn't be making PyOxidizer open source
if I didn't want to share it with the world for free! And I am
financially well off as well. I just feel like there should be
more financial contribution to open source because it would improve
the health of the ecosystem and I can help achieve that end by
advocating for it and giving myself.</p>
<h2>Leveraging Rust</h2>
<p>The <em>oxidize</em> part of PyOxidizer comes from Rust (See the
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rust">Wikipedia Rust article</a> - for the
chemical not the programming language - to understand where <em>oxidize</em>
comes from.) The build time packaging and building functionality is
implemented in Rust. And the binary that embeds and controls the
Python interpreter in built applications is Rust code. Rationale for
these decisions is
<a href="https://pyoxidizer.readthedocs.io/en/latest/faq.html#why-rust">explained in the FAQ</a>.</p>
<p>This is my first non-toy project using Rust and I have to say that
Rust is... incredible! I may have to author a dedicated blog post
extolling the virtues of Rust. In short, Rust is now my go-to language
for systems level projects. Unless you need the target platform
versatility, I don't think C or C++ are defensibles choices in 2019 given
their security deficiencies. Languages like Go, Java, and various JVM
or CLR languages are acceptable if you can tolerate having a garbage
collector and/or a larger runtime. But what makes Rust superior in my
mind is the ability for the compiler to prevent large classes of
software bugs (especially those that turn into CVEs) and inefficiencies that
have plagued our industry for decades. <strong>Rust is the first programming
language I've used where I feel like the language itself, the compiler,
the tools around it (cargo, rustfmt, clippy, rustup, etc), and the
community surrounding it all actually care about and assist me with
writing high quality software. Nothing else I've used comes even close.</strong></p>
<p>What I've been most surprised about Rust is how high level it feels
for a systems level language that isn't garbage collected. When you
program lower-level languages like C or C++, compared to a higher level
language like Python, you have to type a lot more and be more explicit
in nearly everything you do. While Rust is certainly not as expressive
or compact as say Python, it is far, far closer to Python than I was
expecting it to be. Yes, you do have to type more and think more about
your code to appease the Rust compiler's constraints. But the return
on that investment is the compiler preventing entire classes of bugs
and C/C++ levels of performance. When I started PyOxidizer, the build
time logic was implemented in Python and only the run-time pieces were
in Rust. <strong>After learning a bit more Rust and realizing the obvious
code quality benefits, I ditched Python and adopted Rust for the build
time logic.</strong> And as the code base has grown and gone through various
refactorings, I am so glad I did so! The Rust compiler has caught
dozens of would-be bugs in Python. Granted, many of these can be
attributed to having strong typing and compile time type checking and
Rust is little different than say Java on this front. But a significant
number of prevented bugs covered invariants in the code because of the
way Rust's type system often intersects with control flow. e.g. <code>match</code>
arms must be exhaustive, so you can't have unhandled values/types and
unchecked <code>Result</code> instances result ina compiler warning. And clippy
has been just fantastic helping to guide me towards writing more
<em>acceptable</em> code following community accepted best practices.</p>
<p><strong>Even though PyOxidizer is implemented in Rust, most end-users shouldn't
have to care</strong> (beyond having to install a Rust compiler and build
PyOxidizer from source). The existence of Rust should be abstracted
away from Python packagers. I did this on purpose because I believe that
users of an application shouldn't have to care about the technical
implementation of that application. It is a bit unfortunate that I
force users to install Rust before using PyOxidizer, but in my defense
the target audience is technically savvy developers, bootstrapping Rust
is easy, and PyOxidizer is young, so I think it is acceptble for now.
If people get hung up on it, I can provide pre-compiled <code>pyoxidizer</code>
executables.</p>
<p>But if you do know Rust, PyOxidizer being implemented in Rust opens
up some exciting possibilities!</p>
<p><strong>One exciting possibility with PyOxidizer is the ability to add Rust
code to your Python application.</strong> PyOxidizer works by generating a
default Rust application (<code>main.rs</code>) that simply instantiates and runs
an embedded Python interpreter then exits. It essentially does what
<code>python</code> or a Python script would do. The key takeaway here is your
<em>Python application</em> is technically a <em>Rust application</em> (in the same
way that <code>python</code> is technically a <em>C application</em>). And being a
Rust application means you can add Rust code to that application. You
can modify the autogenerated <code>main.rs</code> to do things before, during, and
after the embedded Python interpreter runs. It's a regular Rust program
and can do anything that Rust programs can do!</p>
<p>Another possibility - and variant of above - is embedding Python
in existing Rust projects. PyOxidizer's mechanism for embedding a
Python interpreter is implemented as a standalone Rust crate. <strong>One
can add the pyembed crate to an existing Rust project and a little of
build system magic later, your Rust project can now embed and run
a Python interpreter!</strong></p>
<p>There's a lot of potential for hybrid Rust + Python programs. And
I am <strong>very</strong> excited about the possibilities.</p>
<p><strong>If you are a Rust programmer, PyOxidizer allows you to easily embed
Python in your Rust application. If you are a Python programmer,
PyOxidizer allows your to easily leverage Rust in your Python
application.</strong> In short, the package ecosystem of the other becomes
available to you. And if you aren't familiar with Rust, there are some
potentially crazy possibilities. For example,
<a href="https://github.com/jwilm/alacritty">Alacritty</a> is a GPU accelerated
terminal emulator written in Rust and
<a href="https://github.com/servo/servo">Servo</a> is an entire web browser
engine written in Rust. With PyOxidizer, you could integrate a
terminal emulator or browser engine as part of your Python
application if you really wanted to. And, yes, Rust's packaging
tools are so good that stuff like this tends to <em>just work</em>. As
a concrete example, the <code>pyoxidizer</code> CLI tool contains <code>libgit2</code>
for performing in-process interactions with Git repositories. Adding
this required a single line change to a <code>Cargo.toml</code> file and it
<em>just worked</em> on Linux, macOS, and Windows. Stuff like this often
takes hours to days to integrate in C/C++. It is quite ridiculous
how easy it is to add (complex) components to Rust projects!</p>
<p>For years, Python projects have implemented extensions in C to
realize performance wins. If your Python application is a Rust
executable, then implementing this functionality in Rust (rather
than C) seems rationale. So we may see <em>oxidized</em> Python
applications have their performance critical pieces slowly be
rewritten in Rust. (Honestly, the Rust crates to interface between
Rust and the CPython API still leave a bit to be desired, so the
experience of writing this Rust code still isn't great. But things
will certainly improve over time.)</p>
<p>This type of <em>inside-out</em> split language work has been practiced
in Python for years. What PyOxidizer brings to the table is the
ability to more easily port code <em>outside-in</em>. For example, you
could implement performance-criticial, early application logic such
as config file parsing and command line argument parsing in Rust.
You could then have Rust service some application functionality
without Python. Why would you want this? Performance is a valid
reason. Starting a Python interpreter, importing modules, and running
code can consume several dozen or even hundreds of milliseconds. If
you are writing performance sensitive applications, the existence
of <em>any</em> Python can add enough latency that people no longer perceive
the interaction as instananeous. This added latency can make Python
totally inappropriate for some contexts, such as for programs that run
as part of populating your shell's prompt. Writing such code in Rust
instead of Python dramatically increases the probability that the
code is fast and likely delivers stronger correctness guarantees
courtesy of Rust's compile time validation as well!</p>
<p>An extreme practice of <em>outside-in</em> porting of Python to Rust would
be to incrementally rewrite an entire Python application in Rust.
Rust's ergonomics are exceptional and I do think we'll see people
choose Rust where they previously would have chosen Python. I've
done this myself with PyOxidizer and feel it is a very defensible
decision to reach! I feel a bit conflicted releasing a tool which
may undermine Python's popularity by encouraging use of Rust over
Python. But at the end of the day, PyOxidizer increases the utility
of both Python and Rust by giving each more readily accessible
access to the other and PyOxidizer improves the overall utility of
Python by improving the application distribution story. I have no
doubt PyOxidizer is a net benefit for the Python ecosystem, even if
it does help usher in more people choosing Rust over Python. If
I have an ulterior motive in developing PyOxidizer, it is to enable
Mercurial's official distribution to be a Rust executable and
for some functionality (like <code>hg status</code>) to be runnable without
Python (for performance reasons).</p>
<p>Another possible use of PyOxidizer is as a library. All the build time
functionality of PyOxidizer exists in a Rust crate. So, you can add
the <code>pyoxidizer</code> crate to your own Rust project and use its code to
do things like build a library containing Python, compile Python
source modules to bytecode, or walk a directory tree and find Python
resources within. The code is still heavily geared towards PyOxidizer
and there's no promise of API stability. But this potential for library
usage exists and if others want to experiment with building custom
Python binaries not using the <code>pyoxidizer</code> CLI tool, using PyOxidizer
as a library might save you a lot of time.</p>
<h2>Standalone Python Distributions</h2>
<p>One of the most time consuming parts of building PyOxidizer was
figuring out how to build self-contained Python distributions.
Typically, a Python build consists of a library, shared libraries for
various extension modules, shared libraries required by the prior
items, and a hodgepodge of other files, such as .py files implementing
the Python standard library. The
<a href="https://github.com/indygreg/python-build-standalone">python-build-standalone</a>
project was created to automate creating special builds of Python
which are self-contained and distributable. This requires doing
dirty things with build systems. But I don't want to inflict the
details on you here. What I do think is worth mentioning is how
those Python distributions are distributed. The output of the
build is a tarball containing the Python installation, build artifacts
that can be used to link a custom libpython, and a <code>PYTHON.json</code>
file describing the contents of the distribution. PyOxidizer reads
the <code>PYTHON.json</code> file and learns how it should interact with that
distribution. <strong>If you produce a Python distribution conforming to the
format that <code>python-build-standalone</code> defines, you can use that
Python with PyOxidizer.</strong></p>
<p>While I have no urgency to do so at this time, I could see a future
where this Python distribution format is standardized. Then maintainers
of various Python distributions (CPython, PyPy, etc) would independently
produce their own distributable artifacts conforming to this standard,
in turn allowing machine consumers of Python distributions (such as
PyOxidizer) to easily consume different Python distributions and do
interesting things with them. You could even imagine these Python
distribution archives being readily available as packages in your
system's package manager and their locations exposed via the
<code>sysconfig</code> Python module, making it easy for tools (like PyOxidizer)
to find and use them.</p>
<p>Over time, I could see PyOxidizer's functionality rolling up into
official packaging tools like <code>pip</code>, which would know how to consume
the distribution archives and produce an executable containing a
Python interpreter, required Python modules, etc.</p>
<p>Getting PyOxidizer's functionality rolled into official Python
packaging tools is likely years away (if it ever happens). But I think
standardizing a format describing a Python distribution and (optionally)
contains build artifacts that can be used to <em>repackage</em> it is a
prerequisite and would be a good place to start this journey. I would
certainly love for Python distributions (like CPython) to be in charge of
producing official <em>repackagable</em> distributions because this is not
something I want to be in the business of doing long term (I'm
lazy, less equipped to make the correct decisions, and there are
various trust and security concerns). And while I'm here, I am
definitely interested in upstreaming some of the
<code>python-build-standalone</code> functionality into the existing CPython
build system because coercing CPython's build system to produce
distributable binaries is currently a major pain and I'd love to enable
others to do this. I just haven't had time nor do I know if the patches
would be well received. If a CPython maintainer wants to get in
touch, I'd love to have a conversation!</p>
<h2>Conclusion</h2>
<p>I started hacking on PyOxidizer in November 2018. After months
of chipping away at it, I think I finally have a useful utility
for some audiences. There's still a lot of missing features and
some rough edges. But the core functionality is there and I'm
convinced that PyOxidizer or its underlying technology could be
an integral part of solving Python's application distribution
<em>black swan</em> problem. I'm particularly proud of the hacks I
concocted to coerce Python into importing module bytecode from
memory using zero-copy. Those are documented in
<a href="/blog/2018/12/18/distributing-standalone-python-applications/">this blog post</a>
and in the
<a href="https://github.com/indygreg/PyOxidizer/blob/master/pyoxidizer/src/pyembed/lib.rs">pyembed crate docs</a>.</p>
<p>So what are you waiting for? Head on over to the
<a href="https://pyoxidizer.readthedocs.io/en/latest/index.html">documentation</a>,
install PyOxidizer, and let me know how it goes by
<a href="https://github.com/indygreg/PyOxidizer/issues">filing issues</a>!</p>
<p>I hope you enjoy <em>oxidizing</em> your Python applications!</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <author>
      <name>Gregory Szorc</name>
      <uri>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog</uri>
    </author>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[PyOxidizer Support for Windows]]></title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2019/01/06/pyoxidizer-support-for-windows" />
    <id>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2019/01/06/pyoxidizer-support-for-windows</id>
    <updated>2019-01-06T10:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-06T10:00:00Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Python" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="PyOxidizer" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Rust" />
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[PyOxidizer Support for Windows]]></summary>
    <content type="html" xml:base="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2019/01/06/pyoxidizer-support-for-windows"><![CDATA[<p>A few weeks ago I
<a href="/blog/2018/12/18/distributing-standalone-python-applications">introduced PyOxidizer</a>,
a project that aims to make it easier to produce completely self-contained
executables embedding a Python interpreter (using Rust). A few days later I
<a href="/blog/2018/12/28/faster-in-memory-python-module-importing/">observed some PyOxidizer performance benefits</a>.</p>
<p>After a few more hacking sessions, I'm very pleased to report that
PyOxidizer is now working on Windows!</p>
<p>I am able to produce a standalone Windows <code>.exe</code> containing a fully
featured CPython interpreter, all its library dependencies (OpenSSL, SQLite,
liblzma, etc), and a copy of the Python standard library (both source and
bytecode data). The binary weighs in at around 25 MB. (It could be smaller
if we didn't embed <code>.py</code> source files or stripped some dependencies.)
The only DLL dependencies of the exe are <code>vcruntime140.dll</code> and various
system DLLs that are always present on Windows.</p>
<p>Like I did for Linux and macOS, I produced a Python script that performs
~500 <code>import</code> statements for the near entirety of the Python standard library.
I then ran this script with both the official 64-bit Python distribution
and an executable produced with PyOxidizer:</p>
<pre><code># Official CPython 3.7.2 Windows distribution.
$ time python.exe &lt; import_stdlib.py
real    0m0.475s

# PyOxidizer with non-PGO CPython 3.7.2
$ time target/release/pyapp.exe &lt; import_stdlib.py
real    0m0.347s
</code></pre>
<p>Compared to the official CPython distribution, a PyOxidizer executable
can import almost the entirety of the Python standard library ~125ms
faster - or ~73% of original. In terms of the percentage of speedup,
the gains are similar to Linux and macOS. However, there is substantial
new process overhead on Windows compared to POSIX architectures. On the
same machine, a <em>hello world</em> Python process will execute in ~10ms on Linux
and ~40ms on Windows. If we remove the startup overhead, importing
the Python standard library runs at ~70% of its original time, making
the relative speedup on par with that seen on macOS + APFS.</p>
<p>Windows support is a major milestone for PyOxidizer. And it was the
hardest platform to make work. CPython's build system on Windows uses
Visual Studio project files. And coercing the build system to produce
static libraries was a real pain. Lots of CPython's build tooling assumes
Python is built in a very specific manner and multiple changes I made
completely break those assumptions. On top of that, it's very easy to
encounter problems with symbol name mismatch due to the use of
<code>__declspec(dllexport)</code> and <code>__declspec(dllimport)</code>. I spent
several hours going down a rabbit hole learning how Rust generates symbols
on Windows for <code>extern {}</code> items. Unfortunately, we currently have
to use a Rust Nightly feature (the <code>static-nobundle</code> linkage kind)
to get things to work. But I <em>think</em> there are options to remove that
requirement.</p>
<p>Up to this point, my work on PyOxidizer has focused on prototyping the
concept. With Windows out of the way and PyOxidizer working on Linux,
macOS, and Windows, I have achieved confidence that my vision of a
single executable embedding a full-featured Python interpreter is
technically viable on major desktop platforms! (BSD people, I care
about you too. The solution for Linux should be portable to BSD.)
This means I can start focusing on features, usability, and optimization.
In other words, I can start building a tool that others will want to use.</p>
<p>As always, you can follow my work on this blog and by following
the <a href="https://github.com/indygreg/python-build-standalone">python-build-standalone</a>
and <a href="https://github.com/indygreg/PyOxidizer">PyOxidizer</a> projects on
GitHub.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <author>
      <name>Gregory Szorc</name>
      <uri>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog</uri>
    </author>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Faster In-Memory Python Module Importing]]></title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2018/12/28/faster-in-memory-python-module-importing" />
    <id>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2018/12/28/faster-in-memory-python-module-importing</id>
    <updated>2018-12-29T09:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2018-12-28T12:40:00Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Python" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="PyOxidizer" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Rust" />
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Faster In-Memory Python Module Importing]]></summary>
    <content type="html" xml:base="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2018/12/28/faster-in-memory-python-module-importing"><![CDATA[<p>I <a href="/blog/2018/12/18/distributing-standalone-python-applications/">recently blogged about</a>
distributing standalone Python applications. In that post, I announced
<a href="https://github.com/indygreg/PyOxidizer">PyOxidizer</a> - a tool which
leverages Rust to produce standalone executables embedding Python. One of the
features of PyOxidizer is the ability to import Python modules embedded
within the binary using zero-copy.</p>
<p>I also recently blogged about
<a href="/blog/2018/10/29/global-kernel-locks-in-apfs/">global kernel locks in APFS</a>,
which make filesystem operations slower on macOS. This was the latest wrinkle in
a long battle against Python's slow startup times, which I've posted about
on the official python-dev mailing list
<a href="https://mail.python.org/pipermail/python-dev/2014-May/134528.html">over</a>
<a href="https://mail.python.org/pipermail/python-dev/2018-May/153296.html">the</a>
<a href="https://mail.python.org/pipermail/python-dev/2018-October/155466.html">years</a>.</p>
<p>Since I announced PyOxidizer a few days ago, I've had some productive holiday
hacking sessions!</p>
<p>One of the reached milestones is PyOxidizer now supports macOS.</p>
<p>With that milestone reached, I thought it would be interesting to compare
the performance of a PyOxidizer executable versus a standard CPython build.</p>
<p>I produced a <a href="https://gist.github.com/indygreg/be1c229fa41ced5c76d912f7073f9de6">Python script</a>
that imports almost the entirety of the Python standard library - at least the
modules implemented in Python. That's 508 <code>import</code> statements. I then
executed this script using a typical <code>python3.7</code> binary (with the standard
library on the filesystem) and PyOxidizer-produced standalone executables
with a module importer that loads Python modules from memory using zero copy.</p>
<pre><code># Homebrew installed CPython 3.7.2

# Cold disk cache.
$ sudo purge
$ time /usr/local/bin/python3.7 &lt; import_stdlib.py
real   0m0.694s
user   0m0.354s
sys    0m0.121s

# Hot disk cache.
$ time /usr/local/bin/python3.7 &lt; import_stdlib.py
real   0m0.319s
user   0m0.263s
sys    0m0.050s

# PyOxidizer with non-PGO/non-LTO CPython 3.7.2
$ time target/release/pyapp &lt; import_stdlib.py
real   0m0.223s
user   0m0.201s
sys    0m0.017s

# PyOxidizer with PGO/non-LTO CPython 3.7.2
$ time target/release/pyapp &lt; import_stdlib.py
real   0m0.234s
user   0m0.210s
sys    0m0.019

# PyOxidizer with PTO+LTO CPython 3.7.2
$ sudo purge
$ time target/release/pyapp &lt; import_stdlib.py
real   0m0.442s
user   0m0.252s
sys    0m0.059s

$ time target/release/pyall &lt; import_stdlib.py
real   0m0.221s
user   0m0.197s
sys    0m0.020s
</code></pre>
<p>First, the PyOxidizer times are all relatively similar regardless of whether
PGO or LTO is used to build CPython. That's not too surprising, as I'm
exercising a very limited subset of CPython (and I suspect the benefits
of PGO/LTO aren't as pronounced due to the nature of the CPython API).</p>
<p>But the bigger result is the obvious speedup with PyOxidizer and its
in-memory importing: <strong>PyOxidizer can import almost the entirety of the
Python standard library ~100ms faster - or ~70% of original - than a
typical standalone CPython install</strong> with a hot disk cache! This comes
out to ~0.19ms per <code>import</code> statement. If we run <code>purge</code> to clear out
the disk cache, the performance delta increases to 252ms, or ~64% of
original. All these numbers are on a 2018 6-core 2.9 GHz i9 MacBook Pro,
which has a pretty decent SSD.</p>
<p>And on Linux on an i7-6700K running in a Hyper-V VM:</p>
<pre><code># pyenv installed CPython 3.7.2

# Cold disk cache.
$ time ~/.pyenv/versions/3.7.2/bin/python &lt; import_stdlib.py
real   0m0.405s
user   0m0.165s
sys    0m0.065s

# Hot disk cache.
$ time ~/.pyenv/versions/3.7.2/bin/python &lt; import_stdlib.py
real   0m0.193s
user   0m0.161s
sys    0m0.032s

# PyOxidizer with PGO CPython 3.7.2

# Cold disk cache.
$ time target/release/pyapp &lt; import_stdlib.py
real   0m0.227s
user   0m0.145s
sys    0m0.016s

# Hot disk cache.
$ time target/release/pyapp &lt; import_stdlib.py
real   0m0.152s
user   0m0.136s
sys    0m0.016s
</code></pre>
<p>On a hot disk cache, the run-time improvement of PyOxidizer is ~41ms, or
~78% of original. This comes out to ~0.08ms per <code>import</code> statement. When
flushing caches by writing <code>3</code> to <code>/proc/sys/vm/drop_caches</code>, the delta
increases to ~178ms, or ~56% of original.</p>
<p>Using <code>dtruss -c</code> to execute the binaries, the breakdown in system calls
occurring &gt;10 times is clear:</p>
<pre><code># CPython standalone
fstatfs64                                      16
read_nocancel                                  19
ioctl                                          20
getentropy                                     22
pread                                          26
fcntl                                          27
sigaction                                      32
getdirentries64                                34
fcntl_nocancel                                106
mmap                                          114
close_nocancel                                129
open_nocancel                                 130
lseek                                         148
open                                          168
close                                         170
read                                          282
fstat64                                       403
stat64                                        833

# PyOxidizer
lseek                                          10
read                                           12
read_nocancel                                  14
fstat64                                        16
ioctl                                          22
munmap                                         31
stat64                                         33
sysctl                                         33
sigaction                                      36
mmap                                          122
madvise                                       193
getentropy                                    315
</code></pre>
<p>PyOxidizer avoids hundreds of <code>open()</code>, <code>close()</code>, <code>read()</code>,
<code>fstat64()</code>, and <code>stat64()</code> calls. And by avoiding these calls,
PyOxidizer not only avoids the userland-kernel overhead intrinsic to them,
but also any additional overhead that APFS is imposing via its global
lock(s).</p>
<p>(Why the PyOxidizer binary is making hundreds of calls to <code>getentropy()</code>
I'm not sure. It's definitely coming from Python as a side-effect of a
module import and it is something I'd like to fix, if possible.)</p>
<p>With this experiment, we finally have the ability to better isolate the
impact of filesystem overhead on Python module importing and preliminary
results indicate that the overhead is not insignificant - at least on the
tested systems (I'll get data for Windows when PyOxidizer supports it).
While the test is somewhat contrived (I don't think many applications import
the entirety of the Python standard library), some Python applications do
import hundreds of modules. And as I've
<a href="https://mail.python.org/pipermail/python-dev/2018-May/153296.html">written before</a>,
milliseconds matter. This is especially true if you are invoking Python
processes hundreds or thousands of times in a build system, when running
a test suite, for scripting, etc. Cumulatively you can be importing tens
of thousands of modules. So I think shaving even fractions of a
millisecond from module importing is important.</p>
<p>It's worth noting that in addition to the system call overhead, CPython's
path-based importer runs
<a href="https://github.com/python/cpython/blob/804a5d94b6b7f8cb8546112aee2bc3af362f28f5/Lib/importlib/_bootstrap_external.py">substantially more</a>
Python code
<a href="https://github.com/indygreg/PyOxidizer/blob/c50e63338abd08ebac86746a33d750756d622edc/pyrepackager/src/memoryimporter.py">than PyOxidizer</a>
and this likely contributes several milliseconds of overhead as well. Because
PyOxidizer applications are static, the importer can remain simple (finding a
module in PyOxidizer is essentially a Rust <code>HashMap&lt;String, Vec&lt;u8&gt;</code> lookup).
While it might be useful to isolate the filesystem overhead from Python code
overhead, the thing that end-users care about is overall execution time: they
don't care where that overhead is coming from. So I think it is fair to compare
PyOxidizer - with its intrinsically simpler import model - with what Python
typically does (scan <code>sys.path</code> entries and looking for modules on the
filesystem).</p>
<p>Another difference is that PyOxidizer is almost completely statically linked.
By contrast, a typical CPython install has compiled extension modules as
standalone shared libraries and these shared libraries often link against
other shared libraries (such as libssl). From <code>dtruss</code> timing information,
I don't believe this difference contributes to significant overhead, however.</p>
<p>Finally, I haven't yet optimized PyOxidizer. I still have a few tricks up
my sleeve that can likely shave off more overhead from Python startup. But
so far the results are looking <em>very</em> promising. I dare say they are looking
promising enough that Python distributions themselves might want to look
into the area more thoroughly and consider distribution defaults that rely
less on the every-Python-module-is-a-separate-file model.</p>
<p>Stay tuned for more <a href="https://github.com/indygreg/PyOxidizer">PyOxidizer</a>
updates in the near future!</p>
<p><em>(I updated this post a day after initial publication to add measurements
for Linux.)</em></p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <author>
      <name>Gregory Szorc</name>
      <uri>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog</uri>
    </author>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Distributing Standalone Python Applications]]></title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2018/12/18/distributing-standalone-python-applications" />
    <id>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2018/12/18/distributing-standalone-python-applications</id>
    <updated>2018-12-18T15:35:00Z</updated>
    <published>2018-12-18T15:35:00Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Python" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="PyOxidizer" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Rust" />
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Distributing Standalone Python Applications]]></summary>
    <content type="html" xml:base="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2018/12/18/distributing-standalone-python-applications"><![CDATA[<h2>The Problem</h2>
<p>Packaging and application distribution is a hard problem on multiple
dimensions. For Python, large aspects of this problem space are more or
less solved if you are distributing open source Python libraries and your
target audience is developers (<em>use pip and PyPI</em>). But if you are distributing
Python <em>applications</em> - standalone executables that use Python - your
world can be much more complicated.</p>
<p>One of the primary reasons why distributing Python applications is difficult
is because of the complex and often sensitive relationship between a Python
application and the environment it runs in.</p>
<p>For starters we have the Python interpreter itself. If your application doesn't
distribute the Python interpreter, you are at the whims of the Python
interpreter provided by the host machine. You may want to target Python 3.7
only. But because Python 3.5 or 3.6 is the most recent version installed by
many Linux distros, you are forced to support older Python versions and all
their quirks and lack of features.</p>
<p>Going down the rabbit hole, even the presence of a supposedly compatible
version of the Python interpreter isn't a guarantee for success! For example,
the Python interpreter could have a built-in extension that links against
an old version of a library. Just last week I was encountering weird SQlite
bugs in Firefox's automation because Python was using an old version of
SQLite with known bugs. Installing a modern SQLite fixed the problems. Or
the interpreter could have modifications or extra installed packages
interfering with the operation of your application. There are never-ending
corner cases. And I can tell you from my experience with having to support
the Firefox build system (which uses Python heavily) that you will encounter
these corner cases given a broad enough user base.</p>
<p>And even if the Python interpreter on the target machine is fully compatible,
getting your code to run on that interpreter could be difficult! Several
Python applications leverage compiled extensions linking against Python's
C API. Distributing the precompiled form of the extension can be challenging,
especially when your code needs to link against 3rd party libraries, which
may conflict with something on the target system. And, the precompiled
extensions need to be built in a very delicate manner to ensure they can
run on as many target machines as possible. But not distributing pre-built
binaries requires the end-user be able to compile Python extensions. Not
every user has such an environment and forcing this requirement on them is
not user friendly.</p>
<p><strong>From an application developer's point of view, distributing a copy of the
Python interpreter along with your application is the only reliable way of
guaranteeing a more uniform end-user experience.</strong> Yes, you will still
have variability because every machine is different. But you've eliminated
the the Python interpreter from the set of unknowns and that is a huge win.
(Unfortunately, distributing a Python interpreter comes with a host of other
problems such as size bloat, security/patching concerns, poking the OS
packaging bears, etc. But those problems are for another post.)</p>
<h2>Existing Solutions</h2>
<p>There are tons of existing tools for <em>solving</em> the Python application
distribution problem.</p>
<p>The approach that tools like <a href="https://shiv.readthedocs.io/en/latest/">Shiv</a>
and <a href="https://github.com/pantsbuild/pex">PEX</a> take is to leverage Python's
built-in support for <em>running</em> zip files. Essentially, if there is a zip
file containing a <code>__main__.py</code> file and you execute <code>python file.zip</code>
(or have a zip file with a <code>#!/usr/bin/env python</code> shebang), Python
can load modules in that zip file and execute an application within. Pretty
cool!</p>
<p>This approach works great if your execution environment supports shebangs
(Windows doesn't) and the Python interpreter is suitable. But if you need
to support Windows or don't have control over the execution environment
and can't guarantee the Python interpreter is <em>good</em>, this approach isn't
suitable.</p>
<p>As stated above, we want to distribute the Python interpreter with our
application to minimize variability. Let's talk about tools that do that.</p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/facebookincubator/xar/">XAR</a> is a pretty cool offering
from Facebook. XAR files are executables that contain
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SquashFS">SquashFS</a> filesystems. Upon running
the executable, SquashFS filesystems are created. For Python applications,
the XAR contains a copy of the Python interpreter and all your Python modules.
At run-time, these files are <em>extracted</em> to SquashFS filesystems and the
Python interpreter is executed. If you squint hard enough, it is kind of
like a pre-packaged, executable virtualenv which also contains the Python
interpreter.</p>
<p>XARs are pretty cool (and aren't limited to Python). However, because XARs
rely on SquashFS, they have a run-time requirement on the target machine.
This is great if you only need to support Linux and macOS and your target
machines support FUSE and SquashFS. But if you need to support Windows or
a general user population without SquashFS support, XARs won't help you.</p>
<p>Zip files and XARs are great for enterprises that have tightly controlled
environments. But for a general end-user population, we need something
more robust against variance among target machines.</p>
<p>There are a handful of tools for packaging Python applications along with
the Python interpreter in more resilient manners.</p>
<p><a href="http://nuitka.net/pages/overview.html">Nuitka</a> <em>converts</em> Python source
to C code then compiles and links that C code against libpython. You can
perform a static link and compile everything down to a single executable.
If you do the compiling properly, that executable should <em>just work</em> on
pretty much every target machine. That's pretty cool and is exactly the
kind of solution application distributors are looking for: you can't get
much simpler than a self-contained executable! While I'd love to vouch
for Nuitka and recommend using it, I haven't used it so can't. And I'll
be honest, the prospect of compiling Python source to C code kind of
terrifies me. That effectively makes Nuitka a new Python implementation
and I'm not sure I can (yet) place the level of trust in Nuitka that I
have for e.g. CPython and PyPy.</p>
<p>And that leads us to our final category of tools:
<a href="https://docs.python-guide.org/shipping/freezing/">freezing your code</a>. There
are a handful of tools like <a href="https://www.pyinstaller.org/">PyInstaller</a>
which automate the process of building your Python application (often via
standard <code>setup.py</code> mechanisms), assembling all the requisite bits of
the Python interpreter, and producing an artifact that can be distributed
to end users. There are even tools that produce Windows installers, RPMs,
DEBs, etc that you can sign and distribute.</p>
<p>These <em>freezing</em> tools are arguably the state of the art for Python
application distribution to general user populations. On first glance
it seems like all the needed tools are available here. But there are
cracks below the surface.</p>
<h2>Issues with Freezing</h2>
<p>A common problem with freezing is it often relies on the Python interpreter
used to build the frozen application. For example, when building a frozen
application on Linux, it will bundle the system's Python interpreter with
the frozen application. And that interpreter may link against libraries
or libc symbol versions not available on all target machines. So, the
build environment has to be <em>just right</em> in order for the binaries to
run on as many target systems as possible. This isn't an insurmountable
problem. But it adds overhead and complexity to application maintainers.</p>
<p>Another limitation is how these frozen applications handle importing
Python modules.</p>
<p>Multiple tools take the approach of embedding an archive (usually a zip file)
in the executable containing the Python <em>standard library</em> bits not part of
libpython. This includes C extensions (compiled to <code>.so</code> or <code>.pyd</code> files)
and Python source (<code>.py</code>) or bytecode (<code>.pyc</code>) files. There is typically
a step - either at application start time or at module import time - where a
file is extracted to the filesystem such that Python's filesystem-based
importer can load it from there.</p>
<p>For example, PyInstaller <a href="https://pyinstaller.readthedocs.io/en/stable/operating-mode.html#how-the-one-file-program-works">extracts the standard library to a temporary directory
at application start time</a>
(at least when running in single file mode). This can add significant overhead
to the startup time of applications - more than enough to blow through people's
ability to perceive something as <em>instantaneous</em>. This is acceptable for
long-running applications. But for applications (like CLI tools or support
tools for build systems), the overhead can be a non-starter. And, the mere
fact that you are doing filesystem write I/O establishes a requirement that
the application have write access to the filesystem and that write I/O can
perform reasonably well lest application performance suffer. These can be
difficult pills to swallow!</p>
<p>Another limitation is that these tools often assume the executable being
produced is only a Python application. Sometimes Python is <em>part of</em> a
larger application. It would be useful to produce a library that can
easily be embedded within a larger application.</p>
<h2>Improving the State of the Art</h2>
<p>Existing Python application distribution mechanisms don't tick all the
requirements boxes for me. We have tools that are suitable for internal
distribution in well-defined <em>enterprise</em> environments. And we have tools
that target general user populations, albeit with a burden on application
maintainers and often come with a performance hit and/or limited flexibility.</p>
<p>I want something that allows me to produce a standalone, single file executable
containing a Python interpreter, the Python standard library (or a subset of
it), and all the custom code and resources my application needs. That
executable should not require any additional library dependencies beyond what is
already available on most target machines (e.g. libc). That executable should
not require any special filesystem providers (e.g. FUSE/SquashFS) nor should
it require filesystem write access nor perform filesystem write I/O at run-time.
I should be able to embed a Python interpreter within a larger application,
without the overhead of starting the Python interpreter if it isn't needed.</p>
<p>No existing solution ticks all of these boxes.</p>
<p>So I set out to build one.</p>
<p>One problem is producing a Python interpreter that is portable and
fully-featured. You can't punt on this problem because if the core Python
interpreter isn't produced in just the right way, your application will
depend on libraries or symbol versions not available in all environments.</p>
<p>I've created the <a href="https://github.com/indygreg/python-build-standalone">python-build-standalone</a>
project for automating the process of building Python interpreters suitable
for use with standalone, distributable Python applications. The project
produces (and has available for download) binary artifacts including a
pre-compiled Python interpreter and object files used for compiling that
interpreter. The Python interpreter is compiled with PGO/LTO using a modern
Clang, helping to ensure that Python code runs as fast as it can. All of
Python's dependencies are compiled from source with the modern toolchain and
everything is aggressively statically linked to avoid external dependencies.
The toolchain and pre-built distribution are available for downstream
consumers to compile Python extensions with/against.</p>
<p>It's worth noting that use of a modern Clang toolchain is likely sufficiently
different from what you use today. When producing <em>manylinux</em> wheels, it is
recommended to use the <a href="https://github.com/pypa/manylinux">pypa/manylinux</a>
Docker images. These Docker images are based on CentOS 5 (for maximum libc
and other system library compatibility). While they do install a custom
toolchain, Python and any extensions compiled in that environment are compiled
with GCC 4.8.2 (as of this writing). That's a GCC from 2013. A lot has
changed in compilers since 2013 and building Python and extensions with a
compiler released in 2018 should result in various benefits (faster code,
better warnings, etc).</p>
<p>If producing custom CPython builds for standalone distribution interests
you, you should take a look at how I coerced CPython to statically link
all extensions. Spoiler: it involves producing a custom-tailored
<code>Modules/Setup.local</code> file that bypasses <code>setup.py</code>, along with some
<code>Makefile</code> hacks. Because the build environment is deterministic and isolated
in a container, we can get away with some ugly hacks.</p>
<p>A statically linked <code>libpython</code> from which you can produce a standalone
binary embedding Python is only the first layer in the onion. The next layer
is how to handle the Python standard library.</p>
<p><code>libpython</code> only contains the code needed to run the core bits of the Python
interpreter. If we attempt to run a statically linked <code>python</code> executable
without the standard library in the filesystem, things fail pretty fast:</p>
<pre><code>$ rm -rf lib
$ bin/python
Could not find platform independent libraries &lt;prefix&gt;
Could not find platform dependent libraries &lt;exec_prefix&gt;
Consider setting $PYTHONHOME to &lt;prefix&gt;[:&lt;exec_prefix&gt;]
Fatal Python error: initfsencoding: Unable to get the locale encoding
ModuleNotFoundError: No module named 'encodings'

Current thread 0x00007fe9a3432740 (most recent call first):
Aborted (core dumped)
</code></pre>
<p>I'll spare you the details for the moment, but initializing the CPython
interpreter (via <code>Py_Initialize()</code> <em>requires</em> that parts of the Python
standard library be available). This means that in order to fulfill our dream
of a single file executable, we will need custom code that teaches the
embedded Python interpreter to load the standard library from within the
binary... somehow.</p>
<p>As far as I know, efficient embedded standard library handling without run-time
requirements does not exist in the current Python packaging/distribution
ecosystem. So, I had to devise something new.</p>
<p>Enter <a href="https://github.com/indygreg/pyoxidizer">PyOxidizer</a>. PyOxidizer is
a collection of Rust crates that facilitate building an embeddable Python
library, which can easily be added to an executable. We need <em>native</em> code
to interface with the Python C APIs in order to influence Python interpreter
startup. It is 2018 and Rust is a better C/C++, so I chose Rust for this
<em>driver</em> functionality instead of C. Plus, Rust's integrated build system
makes it easier to automate the integration of the custom Python interpreter
files into binaries.</p>
<p>The role of PyOxidizer is to take the pre-built Python interpreter files from
<a href="https://github.com/indygreg/python-build-standalone">python-build-standalone</a>,
combine those files with any other Python files needed to run an application,
and marry them to a Rust crate. This Rust crate can trivially be turned into
a self-contained executable containing a Python application. Or, it can be
combined with another Rust project. Or it can be emitted as a library and
integrated with a non-Rust application. There's a lot of flexibility by design.</p>
<p>The mechanism I used for embedding the Python standard library into a single
file executable without incurring explicit filesystem access at run-time is
(I believe) new, novel, and somewhat crazy. Let me explain how it works.</p>
<p>First, there are no <code>.so</code>/<code>.pyd</code> shared library compiled Python extensions
to worry about. This is because all compiled extensions are statically linked
into the Python interpreter. To the interpreter, they exist as
<a href="https://docs.python.org/3.7/library/importlib.html#importlib.machinery.BuiltinImporter">built-in modules</a>.
Typically, a CPython build will have some modules like <code>_abc</code>, <code>_io</code>, and
<code>sys</code> provided by <em>built-in modules</em>. Modules like <code>_json</code> exist as standalone
shared libraries that are loaded on demand. <code>python-build-standalone</code>'s
modifications to CPython's build system converts all these would-be standalone
shared libraries into <em>built-in modules</em>. (Because we distribute the object
files that compose the eventual <code>libpython</code>, it is possible to filter out
unwanted modules to cut down on binary size if you don't want to ship a
fully-featured Python interpreter.) Because there are no standalone shared
libraries providing Python modules, we don't have the problem of needing to
load a shared library to load a module, which would undermine our goal of
<em>no filesystem access to import modules</em>. And that's a good thing, too,
because <code>dlopen()</code> requires a path: you can't load a shared library from
a memory address. (Fun fact: there are hacks like
<a href="https://sourceware.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=11767">dlopen_with_offset()</a>
that provide an API to load a library from memory, but they require a custom
libc. Google uses this approach for their internal single-file Python
application solution.)</p>
<p>From the <code>python-build-standalone</code> artifacts, PyOxidizer collects all files
belonging to the Python standard library (notably <code>.py</code> and <code>.pyc</code> files).
It also collects other source, bytecode, and resource files needed to run
a custom application.</p>
<p>The relevant files are assembled and serialized into data structures which
contain the names of the resources and their raw content. These data structures
are made available to Rust as <code>&amp;'static [u8]</code> variables (essentially a
<code>static void*</code> if you don't speak Rust).</p>
<p>Using the <a href="https://github.com/dgrunwald/rust-cpython">rust-cpython</a> crate,
PyOxidizer defines a custom Python extension module implemented purely in Rust.
When loaded, the module parses the data structures containing available
Python resource names and data into <code>HashMap&lt;&amp;str, &amp;[u8]&gt;</code> instances. In other
words, it builds a native mapping from resource name to a pointer to its raw
data. The Rust-implemented module exports to Python an API for accessing that
data. From the Python side, you do the equivalent of <code>MODULES.get_code('foo')</code>
to request the bytecode for a named Python module. When called, the Rust code
will perform the lookup and return a <code>memoryview</code> instance pointing to the
raw data. (The use of <code>&amp;[u8]</code> and <code>memoryview</code> means that embedded resource
data is loaded from its static, read-only memory location instead of copied
into a data structure managed by Python. This zero copy approach translates to
less overhead for importing modules. Although, the memory needs to be paged
in by the operating system. So on slow filesystems, reducing I/O and e.g.
compressing module data might be a worthwhile optimization. This can be a
future feature.) </p>
<p>Making data embedded within a binary available to a Python module is relatively
easy. I'm definitely not the first person to come up with this idea. What is
hard - and what I <em>might</em> be the first person to actually do - is how you make
the Python module importing mechanism load <em>all</em> standard library modules via
such a mechanism.</p>
<p>With a custom extension module built-in to the binary exposing module data,
it should <em>just</em> be a matter of registering a custom
<a href="https://docs.python.org/3.7/library/sys.html#sys.meta_path">sys.meta_path</a>
importer that knows how to load modules from that custom location. This
problem turns out to be quite hard!</p>
<p>The initialization of a CPython interpreter is - as I've learned - a bit
complex. A CPython interpreter must be initialized via <code>Py_Initialize()</code>
before any Python code can run. That means in order to modify <code>sys.meta_path</code>,
<code>Py_Initialize()</code> must finish.</p>
<p>A lot of activity occurs under the hood during initialization. Applications
embedding Python have very little control over what happens during
<code>Py_Initialize()</code>. You can change some superficial things like what
filesystem paths to use to bootstrap <code>sys.path</code> and what encodings to use
for stdio descriptors. But you can't really influence the core actions that are
being performed. And there's no mechanism to directly influence
<code>sys.meta_path</code> before an <code>import</code> is performed. (Perhaps there should be?)</p>
<p>During <code>Py_Initialize()</code>, the interpreter needs to configure the encodings
for the filesystem and the stdio descriptors. Encodings are loaded from
Python modules provided by the standard library. So, during the course of
<code>Py_Initialize()</code>, the interpreter needs to import some modules originally
backed by <code>.py</code> files. This creates a dilemma: if <code>Py_Initialize()</code>
needs to <code>import</code> modules in the standard library, the standard library
is backed by memory and isn't available to known importing mechanisms, and
there's no opportunity to configure a custom <code>sys.meta_path</code> importer
before <code>Py_Initialize()</code> runs, how do you teach the interpreter about
your custom module importer and the location of the standard library modules
needed by <code>Py_Initialize()</code>?</p>
<p>This is an extremely gnarly problem and it took me some hours and many false
leads to come up with a solution.</p>
<p>My first attempt involved the esoteric
<a href="https://docs.python.org/3/c-api/import.html#c.PyImport_FrozenModules">frozen modules</a>
feature. (This work predated the use of a custom data structure and module
containing modules data.) The Python interpreter has a
<code>const struct _frozen* PyImport_FrozenModules</code> data structure defining an
array of <em>frozen</em> modules. A <em>frozen</em> module is defined by its module
name and precompiled bytecode data (roughly equivalent to <code>.pyc</code> file
content). Partway through <code>Py_Initialize()</code>, the Python interpreter is able
to import modules. And one of the built-in importers that is automatically
registered knows how to load modules if they are in <code>PyImport_FrozenModules</code>!</p>
<p>I attempted to audit Python interpreter startup and find all modules
that were imported during <code>Py_Initialize()</code>. I then defined a custom
<code>PyImport_FrozenModules</code> containing these modules. In theory, the import
of these modules during <code>Py_Initialize()</code> would be handled by the
<a href="https://docs.python.org/3.7/library/importlib.html#importlib.machinery.FrozenImporter">FrozenImporter</a>
and everything would <em>just work</em>: if I were able to get <code>Py_Initialize()</code> to
complete, I'd be able to register a custom <code>sys.meta_path</code> importer
immediately afterwards and we'd be set.</p>
<p>Things did not go as planned.</p>
<p><code>FrozenImporter</code> doesn't fully conform to the
<a href="https://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-0451/">PEP 451</a> requirements for
setting specific attributes on modules. Without these attributes, the
<code>from . import aliases</code> statement in <code>encodings/__init__.py</code> fails
because the importer is unable to resolve the relative module name. Derp.
One would think CPython's built-in importers would comply with PEP 451
and that all of Python's standard library could be imported as frozen modules.
But this is not the case! I was able to hack around this particular failure
by using an absolute import. But I hit another failure and did not want to
excavate that rabbit hole. Once I realized that <code>FrozenImporter</code> was lacking
mandated module attributes, I concluded that attempting to use <em>frozen modules</em>
as a general import-from-memory mechanism was not viable. Furthermore, the
C code backing <code>FrozenImporter</code> walks the <code>PyImport_FrozenModules</code> array and
does a string compare on the module name to find matches. While I didn't
benchmark, I was concerned that un-indexed scanning at import time would
add considerable overhead when hundreds of modules were in play. (The C code
backing <code>BuiltinImporter</code> uses the same approach and I do worry CPython's
imports of built-in extension modules is causing measurable overhead.)</p>
<p>With <em>frozen modules</em> off the table, I needed to find another way to inject
a custom module importer that was usable during <code>Py_Initialize()</code>. Because
we control the source Python interpreter, modifications to the source code
or even link-time modifications or run-time hacks like trampolines weren't
off the table. But I <strong>really</strong> wanted things to work out of the box because
I don't want to be in the business of maintaining patches to Python
interpreters.</p>
<p>My foray into <em>frozen modules</em> enlightened me to the craziness that is
the bootstrapping of Python's importing mechanism.</p>
<p>I remember hearing that the Python module importing mechanism used to be
written in C and was rewritten in Python. And I knew that the
<a href="https://docs.python.org/3.7/library/importlib.html">importlib</a> package
defined interfaces allowing you to implement your own importers, which
could be registered on
<a href="https://docs.python.org/3.7/library/sys.html#sys.meta_path">sys.meta_path</a>.
But I didn't know how all of this worked at the interpreter level.</p>
<p>The internal <a href="https://github.com/python/cpython/blob/08c2ba0717089662132af69bf5948d82277a8a69/Python/pylifecycle.c#L178">initimport()</a>
C function is responsible for initializing the module importing mechanism. It
does the equivalent of <code>import _frozen_importlib</code>, but using the
<a href="https://docs.python.org/3/c-api/import.html#c.PyImport_ImportFrozenModuleObject">PyImport_ImportFrozenModule()</a>
API. It then manipulates some symbols and calls <code>_frozen_importlib.install()</code>
with references to the <code>sys</code> and <code>imp</code> built-in modules. Later (in
<code>initexternalimport()</code>), a <code>_frozen_importlib_external</code> module is imported
and has code within it executed.</p>
<p>I was initially very confused by this because - while there are references
to <code>_frozen_importlib</code> and <code>_frozen_importlib_external</code> all over the
CPython code base, I couldn't figure out where the code for those modules
actually lived! Some sleuthing of the build directory eventually revealed
that the files <a href="https://github.com/python/cpython/blob/08c2ba0717089662132af69bf5948d82277a8a69/Lib/importlib/_bootstrap.py">Lib/importlib/_bootstrap.py</a>
and <a href="https://github.com/python/cpython/blob/08c2ba0717089662132af69bf5948d82277a8a69/Lib/importlib/_bootstrap_external.py">Lib/importlib/_bootstrap_external.py</a>
were <em>frozen</em> to the module names <code>_frozen_importlib</code> and
<code>_frozen_importlib_external</code>, respectively.</p>
<p>Essentially what is happening is the bulk of Python's import <em>machinery</em> is
implemented in Python (rather than C). But there's a chicken-and-egg
problem where you can't run just any Python code (including any <code>import</code>
statement) until the interpreter is partially or fully initialized.</p>
<p>When building CPython, the Python source code for <code>importlib._bootstrap</code>
and <code>importlib._bootstrap_external</code> are compiled to bytecode. This
bytecode is emitted to <code>.h</code> files, where it is exposed as a
<code>static char *</code>. This bytecode is eventually referenced by the
default <code>PyImport_FrozenModules</code> array, allowing the modules to be
imported via the frozen importer's C API, which bypasses the higher-level
importing mechanism, allowing it to work before the full importing
mechanism is initialized.</p>
<p><code>initimport()</code> and <code>initexternalimport()</code> both call Python functions in
the frozen modules. And we can clearly look at the source of the
corresponding modules and see the Python code do things like
<a href="https://github.com/python/cpython/blob/08c2ba0717089662132af69bf5948d82277a8a69/Lib/importlib/_bootstrap.py#L1158">register the default importers on <code>sys.meta_path</code></a>.</p>
<p>Whew, that was a long journey into the bowels of CPython's internals. How
does all this help with single file Python executables?</p>
<p>Well, the predicament that led us down this rabbit hole was there was no
way to register a custom module importer before <code>Py_Initialize()</code>
completes and before an <code>import</code> is attempted during said <code>Py_Initialize()</code>.</p>
<p>It took me a while, but I finally realized the frozen
<code>importlib._bootstrap_external</code> module provided the window I needed!
<code>importlib._bootstrap_external</code>/<code>_frozen_importlib_external</code> is <em>always</em>
executed during <code>Py_Initialize()</code>. So if you can modify this module's code,
you can run arbitrary code during <code>Py_Initialize()</code> and influence Python
interpreter configuration. And since <code>_frozen_importlib_external</code> is a frozen
module and the <code>PyImport_FrozenModules</code> array is writable and can be modified
before <code>Py_Initialize()</code> is called, all one needs to do is replace the
<code>_frozen_importlib</code> / <code>_frozen_importlib_external</code> bytecode in
<code>PyImport_FrozenModules</code> and you can run arbitrary code during Python
interpreter startup, before <code>Py_Initialize()</code> completes and before any
standard library imports are performed!</p>
<p>My solution to this problem is to concatenate some custom Python code to
<code>importlib/_bootstrap_external.py</code>. This custom code defines a
<code>sys.meta_path</code> importer that knows how to use our Rust-backed built-in
extension module to find and load module data. It redefines the <code>_install()</code>
function so that this custom importer is registered on <code>sys.meta_path</code>
when the function is called during <code>Py_Initialize()</code>. The <em>new</em> Python
source is compiled to bytecode and the <code>PyImport_FrozenModules</code> array is
modified at run-time to point to the modified <code>_frozen_importlib_external</code>
implementation. When <code>Py_Initialize()</code> executes its first standard library
import, module data is provided by the custom <code>sys.meta_path</code> importer,
which grabs it from a Rust extension module, which reads it from a
read-only data structure in the executable binary, which is converted
to a Python <code>memoryview</code> instance and sent back to Python for processing.</p>
<p>There's a bit of <em>magic</em> happening behind the scenes to make all of this
work. PyOxidizer attempts to hide as much of the gory details as possible.
From the perspective of an application maintainer, you just need to define
a minimal config file and it handles most of the low-level details. And there's
even a higher-level Rust API for configuring the embedded Python interpreter,
should you need it.</p>
<p><code>python-build-standalone</code> and <code>PyOxidizer</code> are still in their infancy.
They are very much alpha quality. I consider them technology previews more
than usable software at this point. But I think enough is there to demonstrate
the viability of using Rust as the build system and run-time glue to build
and distribute standalone applications embedding Python.</p>
<p>Time will tell if my utopian vision of zero-copy, no explicit filesystem
I/O for Python module imports will pan out. Others who have ventured into
this space have warned me that lots of Python modules rely on <code>__file__</code>
to derive paths to other resources, which are later <code>stat()</code>d and
<code>open()</code>d. <code>__file__</code> for in-memory modules doesn't exactly make sense
and can't be operated on like normal paths/files. I'm not sure what the
inevitable struggles to support these modules will lead to. Maybe we'll have
to extract things to temporary directories like other standalone Python
applications. Maybe <code>PyOxidizer</code> will take off and people will start using
the <a href="https://docs.python.org/3.7/library/importlib.html#importlib.abc.ResourceReader">ResourceReader</a>
API, which is apparently the proper way to do these things these days.
(Caveat: <code>PyOxidizer</code> doesn't yet implement this API but support is planned.)
Time will tell. I'm not opposed to gross hacks or writing more code as
needed.</p>
<p>Producing highly distributable and performant Python applications has been far
too difficult for far too long. My primary goal for PyOxidizer is to lower these
barriers. By leveraging Rust, I also hope to bring Python and Rust closer
together. I want to enable applications and libraries to effortlessly harness
the powers of both of these fantastic programming languages.</p>
<p>Again, <code>PyOxidizer</code> is still in its infancy. I anticipate a significant amount
of hacking over the holidays and hope to share updates in the weeks ahead. Until
then, please leave comments, watch the <a href="https://github.com/indygreg/PyOxidizer">project on GitHub</a>,
file issues for bugs and feature requests, etc and we'll see where things lead.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
</feed>
