<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"
     xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
     xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
     xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
     xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
     xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
     >
  <channel>
    <title>Gregory Szorc's Digital Home</title>
    <link>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog</link>
    <description>Rambling on</description>
    <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jan 2019 06:07:04 GMT</pubDate>
    <generator>Blogofile</generator>
    <sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
    <sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
    <item>
      <title>One Year at Mozilla</title>
      <link>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2012/07/18/one-year-at-mozilla</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jul 2012 00:00:00 PDT</pubDate>
      <category><![CDATA[Mozilla]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[Firefox]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[Sync]]></category>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2012/07/18/one-year-at-mozilla</guid>
      <description>One Year at Mozilla</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It is hard to believe that my first day as a full-time employee of Mozilla
was one year ago today! But, here I am. And, I'd like to think the past
year is worth reflecting on.</p>
<p>So, what have I been doing for a year? Good question!</p>
<h2>Accomplishments</h2>
<ul>
<li>First patch and commit to Firefox: <a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=673209">bug 673209</a>.
  Yes, my first patch was to configure.in. It scared me too.</li>
<li>Number of non-merge commits: 133</li>
<li>Number of merge commits: 49</li>
<li>Number of reviews: 31</li>
<li>Favorite commit message: <a href="https://hg.mozilla.org/mozilla-central/rev/88d02a07d390">88d02a07d390</a>
  <em>Fix bug 725478 because we run a buggy Python released almost 5 years
  ago; r=tigerblood</em> (it was a bustage follow-up).</li>
<li>Biggest mistake: buildbotcustom change to packaging turned every tree
  red. All of them. Including release. I think I have philor on record
  saying it is the worst burnage he's ever seen. Mission accomplished!</li>
</ul>
<p>Major User-Facing Features:</p>
<ul>
<li>Wrote add-on sync for Firefox (with help from many others, especially
  Dave Townsend and Blair McBride).</li>
<li>Principle reviewer for Apps in the Cloud (apps sync) in Firefox. (Are
  reviewers allowed to take credit?)</li>
</ul>
<p>Honestly, when I see that list, I think <em>that's all?</em> It doesn't feel
like a lot, especially since I work on a major user-facing feature
(Firefox Sync). I do contribute to more. But, if you ask me what the
most significant impact was, I don't think I can call anything else out
as <em>major</em>.</p>
<p>There are certainly a lot of minor things:</p>
<ul>
<li>Actually managed to understand how Firefox Sync works, including the
  crypto model. I even <a href="http://docs.services.mozilla.com/sync/storageformat5.html">documented</a>
  it! I don't think I knew any of that when I started (I basically knew
  that Firefox Sync was using strong client-side encryption. What that
  meant, I had no clue.)</li>
<li>Filed initial bugs (including some patches) to compile mozilla-central
  on Windows 8 and MSVC 2011. By the time people started working on
  Metro development, mozilla-build, configure, and the like already
  supported building.</li>
<li>Configured <a href="https://ci.mozilla.org/job/sync-android/">Android Sync Jenkins Builder</a>.
  I'm told the Android Sync team loves it! You gotta love all the
  built-in dashboards. I really wish we had this for mozilla-central.</li>
<li>Made xpcshell test harness write xUnit files. Machine readable output
  of test results, baby!</li>
<li>Implement <em>send tab to device</em> API in Firefox Sync. Too bad we don't
  have UX to use it :(</li>
<li>Implemented testing-only JavaScript modules. So, instead of the hack
  that is [head] files in tests, you can
  <em>Cu.import("resource://testing-common/foo.js");</em></li>
<li>Made test package generation quieter. This made build logs about 30%
  smaller. This means you can get at build results faster.</li>
<li>Hacked around with JavaScript code coverage using the JS Debugger API.
  Failed in the process. But, I learned a lot about the JS Debugger API,
  so I consider it a win.</li>
<li>Rewrote Firefox Sync's record reconciling algorithm. The old one was
  full of subtle data loss corner cases. The new algorithm is much more
  robust (we think - even with 3 reviewers there was still some head
  scratching).</li>
<li>Emancipated lots of generic JavaScript code from the Sync tree into
  the a <em>services-common</em> package. This anticipated Apps in the Cloud
  and notifications' requirement to use this functionality and allowed
  those projects to get going quicker. At this point, we're effectively
  running a mini Toolkit. We really need to port some of this
  <em>upstream</em>.</li>
<li>Helped design the <a href="http://docs.services.mozilla.com/storage/apis-2.0.html">next version</a>
  of the HTTP service to be used by Sync.</li>
<li>Implemented a standalone JavaScript implementation of the above. The
  production server used by Mozilla runs on Python (running the Python
  server in Mozilla's test environment would be too difficult). The
  server was also implemented using just the spec. This allowed us to
  clarify many parts of the spec. The Python functional tests can also
  be executed against the JS server. This gives us confidence that
  functionality is equivalent and tests hitting the test/JS server will
  behave the same as if they are hitting the production Python server.</li>
<li>Implemented a standalone JavaScript
  <a href="https://hg.mozilla.org/mozilla-central/file/default/services/common/storageservice.js">client</a>  for the above service. Previously, all the logic for this was scattered
  over about a dozen files and was notoriously difficult to audit and
  update. I also think it is a decent example of good code.  Clean.
  Highly documented. No hacks.</li>
<li>Reviewed a skeleton for the notifications service, which will
  eventually power browser notifications in Firefox.</li>
<li>Build system patches to better support Clang. Thankfully, Rafael
  Espíndola has been our Clang champion as of late and is now ensuring
  the bleeding edge of Clang does not break the tree. Thanks, Rafael! (I
  actually think he is in the process of switching our OS X builds to
  use Clang as I type this!)</li>
<li>Worked with security and crypto people to devise the security model
  behind the next version of Firefox Sync. (Brian Warner and Ben Adida
  have been doing most of the crypto work. I'm mostly on the sidelines
  making sure they design a system that can easily interop with Sync.)</li>
<li>Helped devise the <a href="http://docs.services.mozilla.com/sync/storageformat6.html">next version</a>
  of Sync's server-side storage format. This will make the next version
  of Sync faster and able to hold more data at lower server cost.</li>
<li>Gave lots of love to documentation at
  <a href="http://docs.services.mozilla.com/">https://docs.services.mozilla.com/</a>
  (especially the Sync docs). It's almost at the point where others can
  implement Sync clients without having to ask one of the fewer than 10
  people on the planet who actually know.</li>
<li>Contributed many small patches to the build system. Mostly general
  cleanup so far. Although, I have much bigger plans in the works.</li>
<li>Many miscellaneous small things. (I get distracted easily.)</li>
</ul>
<p>Well, that list doesn't seem too shabby. But, a lot of it is smaller
ticket items. I don't think there's anything there worth writing home
about.  Whatever. The future is looking bright for Firefox Sync (Persona
integration will make Sync usable by millions more) and new sync
backends are coming (including search engine sync). So, I'm fine with
not having a longer list of big ticket contributions after only a year.</p>
<h2>On Ramping up at Mozilla</h2>
<p>I will be the first to admit that I had a difficult time getting into
the groove at Mozilla and my first months (dare I say my first half
year) were unproductive by my personal standards.</p>
<p>I can't say I wasn't warned. My manager (Mike Connor) told me
multiple times that it would happen. I was skeptical, insteading
rationalizing that my previous track record of learnly quickly
would hold. He was right. I was wrong. I got fat from the humble pie.</p>
<p>There are a few reasons for this. For starters, I was starting a new
job. It's almost impossible achieve 100% productivity on your first day.
Second, I was working with tools I knew little about, including
JavaScript and especially including the flavor of JavaScript used
inside Firefox. (Short version: the JavaScript within Firefox is awesome
in that it implements bleeding-edge features of the language.
Unfortunately, the JavaScript inside Firefox/Gecko is contaminated
by this blight called XPCOM. It makes things ugly and not very
JavaScript-y. XPCOM also makes the learning curve that much harder
because now you have to learn multiple technologies at the same time.)
It was daunting.</p>
<p>Not helping matters was the fact that Firefox Sync is complicated.
Syncing data is in of itself a difficult problem. Throw in remote
servers, an HTTP protocol, a encryption, and interaction with systems
inside Firefox that are themselves complicated, and you have a <strong>hard</strong>
problem. My first months were literally spent being a thorn in Philipp
von Wieter^H^H^H^H^H^H philikon's side, barraging him with an endless
stream of questions. I am forever in beer debt to him because of this.
When Philipp left the team to work on Boot 2 Gecko and the rest of the
Firefox Sync team was retasked to work on Android Sync shortly
thereafter, I was on my own little island to manage Firefox Sync.
I kind of felt like Tom Hanks' character in <em>Castaway</em>.</p>
<p>If I have one piece of advice for people starting at Mozilla it's this:
be prepared to be humbled by your own ignorance. There is a lot to
learn. It's not easy. Don't feel bad when you struggle. The payoff is
worth it.</p>
<h2>On Life at Mozilla</h2>
<p>Despite the hurdles I initially faced ramping up at Mozilla, life at
Mozilla is great. This mostly stems from the people, of course.</p>
<p>If you are just looking for technical excellence, I think Mozilla has
one of the highest concentrations of any company in the world. Sure,
larger companies will have <em>more</em> amazing individuals. But, the number
per capita at Mozilla is just staggering. I don't know how many times
I've met or talked with someone only to find out later they are
considered to be one of the best in his or her respective field. Reading
Mozilla's phonebook is like looking at a <em>Who's Who</em> list. For someone
like me who loves being a sponge for knowledge, Mozilla is an environment
in which I can thrive. Just thinking back at everything I've learned in
the past year makes my mind asplode.</p>
<p>On the personal front, the personalities of Mozillians are also top
notch. People are generally helpful and supportive. (They need to be for
an open source project to thrive.) People recognize good ideas when they
hear them and there is comparatively few political battles to be won
when enacting change. People themselves are generally interesting and
passionate about the world and the work they do. If you are living
inside the Mozilla bubble, you may not realize how lucky you have it.
I could give specific examples, but I'd be writing all night. Just
take my word for it.</p>
<p>If you need something to whet your appetite, just check out the
zaniness that is <a href="http://mozillamemes.tumblr.com/">Mozilla Memes</a>.
I don't expect you to understand many of the posts unless you are a
Mozillian or follower of Reddit and know what internet memes are. But, if
you are either, it pretty much sums up a large part of the culture for
you. Sometimes I feel like I'm living in one giant, happy meme.</p>
<p>One of the aspects I love most about working at Mozilla is I finally
feel that my career interests are aligned with an organization I
philosophically agree with. Just read the
<a href="https://www.mozilla.org/about/manifesto.html">Mozilla Manifesto</a>. What's
not to like?</p>
<p>This is one of the primary factors that convinced me to join Mozilla.
After Microsoft acquired the startup where I had my first post-college
job (Tellme Networks), I could never hold my head high in Silicon Valley
among my friends in the tech sector. <em>Normal</em> people and those outside
of Silicon Valley were like, "Microsoft, cool!" But, something just
didn't feel right about saying I worked for them. I felt like I was working
for the Empire while I really wanted to be working for the Rebel Alliance.
I felt like I had to atone for my time at Microsoft. I felt like I needed
to cleanse my soul. Mozilla was an obvious answer.</p>
<p>(I don't mean to disparage Microsoft. I actually think the culture has
changed since the days when their behavior earned them the reputation
that Silicon Valley stills holds them accountable for. Still, I would
not work for them in Silicon Valley. Anyway, I'm not here to talk about
the past.)</p>
<p>Mozilla is an organization I'm proud to work for. I exercise that pride
by frequently wearing my awesome Firefox hoodie. Nearly every time I do,
random people come up to me and say how they love Firefox and/or what
Mozilla does for the world. Every time they do, it brings a smile to my
face. This constantly reinforces what I know to be true: that I'm
working for a great organization.</p>
<h2>Future at Mozilla</h2>
<p>I'm already looking forward to the next year at Mozilla. It is already
shaping up to be much, much more productive than my first.</p>
<p>On the roadmap, all of my hacking about with the build system is about
to pay dividends. Ever since my first day at Mozilla I have been
frustrated with the build system and the developer experience one must
go through to contribute to Firefox. After many months of casual (mostly
evenings and weekends) experimentation, my work is about to pay off.</p>
<p>I have successfully formulated a <a href="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2012/06/25/improving-mozilla%27s-build-system/">plan of attack</a>
and helped convince others this is what we need to do. We have since
<a href="http://coop.deadsquid.com/2012/07/reviving-buildfaster-plan-of-attack/">committed</a>
to the fundamental components of that plan and are
<a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=774049">tracking</a> its
progress. (I don't mean to take sole or even primary responsibility for
this as the credit resides with a number of people. But, I would like to
think that the dozens of times I championed aspects of this plan in IRC
and in hallway chats before I was the first person to articulate it in a
post helped lay the groundwork for the eventual acceptance of this
project.) Once we see progress on this project, great things will come
from it. I promise.</p>
<p>My work towards making the build system faster had an unintended
consequence: the creation of a new tool that serves as a frontend to the
build system. One day, I took a step backwards and realized that the
potential for such a tool is much greater than simply interacting with
the build system. So, I extracted that work from my build system
hacking and polished it up a bit. It is now
<a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=751795">one review away</a>
from landing. When it does, thousands of Firefox developers will have a
much better experience when developing Firefox. And, my hope is for
<a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/showdependencytree.cgi?id=774108">many more features</a>
to follow to make it even more awesome, especially for first-time
contributors. I believe this is important to help advance Mozilla's
Mission.</p>
<p>Improving the developer experience of Firefox is exciting and it will
likely make a lot of people really happy. But, it's neither the most
exciting nor most important project I'll contribute to in the upcoming
year. The most exciting and important project for me will be
refactoring Firefox Sync to make it faster, more robust, sync more data,
and, most importantly, usable by more people.</p>
<p>Firefox Sync stands out from similar products in that it keeps your data
safe. Really safe. I
<a href="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2012/04/08/comparing-the-security-and-privacy-of-browser-syncing/">blogged</a>
about this previously. But, I intentionally kept the tone of that post
neutral and factual. The truth is that the security model of Firefox Sync
makes it look like nearly all other products aren't even trying. I take
immense pride in working on a data-sharing feature that makes users'
lives better <strong>without undermining security</strong>. Firefox Sync stands in
rare company in this regard.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, in our zeal for the best security possible, we designed a
product that isn't usable by the majority of people because it is too
complicated to set up and is prone to losing your data. In the end, this
doesn't really serve the overall Firefox user base.</p>
<p>We've been hard at work devising the next version of Firefox Sync which
will retain the optimum security and privacy settings of the existing
product while extending usability at nearly-comparable security and
ofer data recovery to the vast majority of our users. <strong>This is huge.</strong></p>
<p>Yeah, I'm pretty damn excited about my next year at Mozilla.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
