<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed
  xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:thr="http://purl.org/syndication/thread/1.0"
  xml:lang="en"
   >
  <title type="text">Gregory Szorc's Digital Home</title>
  <subtitle type="text">Rambling on</subtitle>

  <updated>2019-01-09T23:13:51Z</updated>
  <generator uri="http://blogofile.com/">Blogofile</generator>

  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" />
  <id>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/feed/atom/</id>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/feed/atom/" />
  <entry>
    <author>
      <name>Gregory Szorc</name>
      <uri>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog</uri>
    </author>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[PyOxidizer Support for Windows]]></title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2019/01/06/pyoxidizer-support-for-windows" />
    <id>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2019/01/06/pyoxidizer-support-for-windows</id>
    <updated>2019-01-06T10:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-06T10:00:00Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Python" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="PyOxidizer" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Rust" />
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[PyOxidizer Support for Windows]]></summary>
    <content type="html" xml:base="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2019/01/06/pyoxidizer-support-for-windows"><![CDATA[<p>A few weeks ago I
<a href="/blog/2018/12/18/distributing-standalone-python-applications">introduced PyOxidizer</a>,
a project that aims to make it easier to produce completely self-contained
executables embedding a Python interpreter (using Rust). A few days later I
<a href="/blog/2018/12/28/faster-in-memory-python-module-importing/">observed some PyOxidizer performance benefits</a>.</p>
<p>After a few more hacking sessions, I'm very pleased to report that
PyOxidizer is now working on Windows!</p>
<p>I am able to produce a standalone Windows <code>.exe</code> containing a fully
featured CPython interpreter, all its library dependencies (OpenSSL, SQLite,
liblzma, etc), and a copy of the Python standard library (both source and
bytecode data). The binary weighs in at around 25 MB. (It could be smaller
if we didn't embed <code>.py</code> source files or stripped some dependencies.)
The only DLL dependencies of the exe are <code>vcruntime140.dll</code> and various
system DLLs that are always present on Windows.</p>
<p>Like I did for Linux and macOS, I produced a Python script that performs
~500 <code>import</code> statements for the near entirety of the Python standard library.
I then ran this script with both the official 64-bit Python distribution
and an executable produced with PyOxidizer:</p>
<pre><code># Official CPython 3.7.2 Windows distribution.
$ time python.exe &lt; import_stdlib.py
real    0m0.475s

# PyOxidizer with non-PGO CPython 3.7.2
$ time target/release/pyapp.exe &lt; import_stdlib.py
real    0m0.347s
</code></pre>
<p>Compared to the official CPython distribution, a PyOxidizer executable
can import almost the entirety of the Python standard library ~125ms
faster - or ~73% of original. In terms of the percentage of speedup,
the gains are similar to Linux and macOS. However, there is substantial
new process overhead on Windows compared to POSIX architectures. On the
same machine, a <em>hello world</em> Python process will execute in ~10ms on Linux
and ~40ms on Windows. If we remove the startup overhead, importing
the Python standard library runs at ~70% of its original time, making
the relative speedup on par with that seen on macOS + APFS.</p>
<p>Windows support is a major milestone for PyOxidizer. And it was the
hardest platform to make work. CPython's build system on Windows uses
Visual Studio project files. And coercing the build system to produce
static libraries was a real pain. Lots of CPython's build tooling assumes
Python is built in a very specific manner and multiple changes I made
completely break those assumptions. On top of that, it's very easy to
encounter problems with symbol name mismatch due to the use of
<code>__declspec(dllexport)</code> and <code>__declspec(dllimport)</code>. I spent
several hours going down a rabbit hole learning how Rust generates symbols
on Windows for <code>extern {}</code> items. Unfortunately, we currently have
to use a Rust Nightly feature (the <code>static-nobundle</code> linkage kind)
to get things to work. But I <em>think</em> there are options to remove that
requirement.</p>
<p>Up to this point, my work on PyOxidizer has focused on prototyping the
concept. With Windows out of the way and PyOxidizer working on Linux,
macOS, and Windows, I have achieved confidence that my vision of a
single executable embedding a full-featured Python interpreter is
technically viable on major desktop platforms! (BSD people, I care
about you too. The solution for Linux should be portable to BSD.)
This means I can start focusing on features, usability, and optimization.
In other words, I can start building a tool that others will want to use.</p>
<p>As always, you can follow my work on this blog and by following
the <a href="https://github.com/indygreg/python-build-standalone">python-build-standalone</a>
and <a href="https://github.com/indygreg/PyOxidizer">PyOxidizer</a> projects on
GitHub.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <author>
      <name>Gregory Szorc</name>
      <uri>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog</uri>
    </author>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Faster In-Memory Python Module Importing]]></title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2018/12/28/faster-in-memory-python-module-importing" />
    <id>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2018/12/28/faster-in-memory-python-module-importing</id>
    <updated>2018-12-29T09:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2018-12-28T12:40:00Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Python" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="PyOxidizer" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Rust" />
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Faster In-Memory Python Module Importing]]></summary>
    <content type="html" xml:base="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2018/12/28/faster-in-memory-python-module-importing"><![CDATA[<p>I <a href="/blog/2018/12/18/distributing-standalone-python-applications/">recently blogged about</a>
distributing standalone Python applications. In that post, I announced
<a href="https://github.com/indygreg/PyOxidizer">PyOxidizer</a> - a tool which
leverages Rust to produce standalone executables embedding Python. One of the
features of PyOxidizer is the ability to import Python modules embedded
within the binary using zero-copy.</p>
<p>I also recently blogged about
<a href="/blog/2018/10/29/global-kernel-locks-in-apfs/">global kernel locks in APFS</a>,
which make filesystem operations slower on macOS. This was the latest wrinkle in
a long battle against Python's slow startup times, which I've posted about
on the official python-dev mailing list
<a href="https://mail.python.org/pipermail/python-dev/2014-May/134528.html">over</a>
<a href="https://mail.python.org/pipermail/python-dev/2018-May/153296.html">the</a>
<a href="https://mail.python.org/pipermail/python-dev/2018-October/155466.html">years</a>.</p>
<p>Since I announced PyOxidizer a few days ago, I've had some productive holiday
hacking sessions!</p>
<p>One of the reached milestones is PyOxidizer now supports macOS.</p>
<p>With that milestone reached, I thought it would be interesting to compare
the performance of a PyOxidizer executable versus a standard CPython build.</p>
<p>I produced a <a href="https://gist.github.com/indygreg/be1c229fa41ced5c76d912f7073f9de6">Python script</a>
that imports almost the entirety of the Python standard library - at least the
modules implemented in Python. That's 508 <code>import</code> statements. I then
executed this script using a typical <code>python3.7</code> binary (with the standard
library on the filesystem) and PyOxidizer-produced standalone executables
with a module importer that loads Python modules from memory using zero copy.</p>
<pre><code># Homebrew installed CPython 3.7.2

# Cold disk cache.
$ sudo purge
$ time /usr/local/bin/python3.7 &lt; import_stdlib.py
real   0m0.694s
user   0m0.354s
sys    0m0.121s

# Hot disk cache.
$ time /usr/local/bin/python3.7 &lt; import_stdlib.py
real   0m0.319s
user   0m0.263s
sys    0m0.050s

# PyOxidizer with non-PGO/non-LTO CPython 3.7.2
$ time target/release/pyapp &lt; import_stdlib.py
real   0m0.223s
user   0m0.201s
sys    0m0.017s

# PyOxidizer with PGO/non-LTO CPython 3.7.2
$ time target/release/pyapp &lt; import_stdlib.py
real   0m0.234s
user   0m0.210s
sys    0m0.019

# PyOxidizer with PTO+LTO CPython 3.7.2
$ sudo purge
$ time target/release/pyapp &lt; import_stdlib.py
real   0m0.442s
user   0m0.252s
sys    0m0.059s

$ time target/release/pyall &lt; import_stdlib.py
real   0m0.221s
user   0m0.197s
sys    0m0.020s
</code></pre>
<p>First, the PyOxidizer times are all relatively similar regardless of whether
PGO or LTO is used to build CPython. That's not too surprising, as I'm
exercising a very limited subset of CPython (and I suspect the benefits
of PGO/LTO aren't as pronounced due to the nature of the CPython API).</p>
<p>But the bigger result is the obvious speedup with PyOxidizer and its
in-memory importing: <strong>PyOxidizer can import almost the entirety of the
Python standard library ~100ms faster - or ~70% of original - than a
typical standalone CPython install</strong> with a hot disk cache! This comes
out to ~0.19ms per <code>import</code> statement. If we run <code>purge</code> to clear out
the disk cache, the performance delta increases to 252ms, or ~64% of
original. All these numbers are on a 2018 6-core 2.9 GHz i9 MacBook Pro,
which has a pretty decent SSD.</p>
<p>And on Linux on an i7-6700K running in a Hyper-V VM:</p>
<pre><code># pyenv installed CPython 3.7.2

# Cold disk cache.
$ time ~/.pyenv/versions/3.7.2/bin/python &lt; import_stdlib.py
real   0m0.405s
user   0m0.165s
sys    0m0.065s

# Hot disk cache.
$ time ~/.pyenv/versions/3.7.2/bin/python &lt; import_stdlib.py
real   0m0.193s
user   0m0.161s
sys    0m0.032s

# PyOxidizer with PGO CPython 3.7.2

# Cold disk cache.
$ time target/release/pyapp &lt; import_stdlib.py
real   0m0.227s
user   0m0.145s
sys    0m0.016s

# Hot disk cache.
$ time target/release/pyapp &lt; import_stdlib.py
real   0m0.152s
user   0m0.136s
sys    0m0.016s
</code></pre>
<p>On a hot disk cache, the run-time improvement of PyOxidizer is ~41ms, or
~78% of original. This comes out to ~0.08ms per <code>import</code> statement. When
flushing caches by writing <code>3</code> to <code>/proc/sys/vm/drop_caches</code>, the delta
increases to ~178ms, or ~56% of original.</p>
<p>Using <code>dtruss -c</code> to execute the binaries, the breakdown in system calls
occurring &gt;10 times is clear:</p>
<pre><code># CPython standalone
fstatfs64                                      16
read_nocancel                                  19
ioctl                                          20
getentropy                                     22
pread                                          26
fcntl                                          27
sigaction                                      32
getdirentries64                                34
fcntl_nocancel                                106
mmap                                          114
close_nocancel                                129
open_nocancel                                 130
lseek                                         148
open                                          168
close                                         170
read                                          282
fstat64                                       403
stat64                                        833

# PyOxidizer
lseek                                          10
read                                           12
read_nocancel                                  14
fstat64                                        16
ioctl                                          22
munmap                                         31
stat64                                         33
sysctl                                         33
sigaction                                      36
mmap                                          122
madvise                                       193
getentropy                                    315
</code></pre>
<p>PyOxidizer avoids hundreds of <code>open()</code>, <code>close()</code>, <code>read()</code>,
<code>fstat64()</code>, and <code>stat64()</code> calls. And by avoiding these calls,
PyOxidizer not only avoids the userland-kernel overhead intrinsic to them,
but also any additional overhead that APFS is imposing via its global
lock(s).</p>
<p>(Why the PyOxidizer binary is making hundreds of calls to <code>getentropy()</code>
I'm not sure. It's definitely coming from Python as a side-effect of a
module import and it is something I'd like to fix, if possible.)</p>
<p>With this experiment, we finally have the ability to better isolate the
impact of filesystem overhead on Python module importing and preliminary
results indicate that the overhead is not insignificant - at least on the
tested systems (I'll get data for Windows when PyOxidizer supports it).
While the test is somewhat contrived (I don't think many applications import
the entirety of the Python standard library), some Python applications do
import hundreds of modules. And as I've
<a href="https://mail.python.org/pipermail/python-dev/2018-May/153296.html">written before</a>,
milliseconds matter. This is especially true if you are invoking Python
processes hundreds or thousands of times in a build system, when running
a test suite, for scripting, etc. Cumulatively you can be importing tens
of thousands of modules. So I think shaving even fractions of a
millisecond from module importing is important.</p>
<p>It's worth noting that in addition to the system call overhead, CPython's
path-based importer runs
<a href="https://github.com/python/cpython/blob/804a5d94b6b7f8cb8546112aee2bc3af362f28f5/Lib/importlib/_bootstrap_external.py">substantially more</a>
Python code
<a href="https://github.com/indygreg/PyOxidizer/blob/c50e63338abd08ebac86746a33d750756d622edc/pyrepackager/src/memoryimporter.py">than PyOxidizer</a>
and this likely contributes several milliseconds of overhead as well. Because
PyOxidizer applications are static, the importer can remain simple (finding a
module in PyOxidizer is essentially a Rust <code>HashMap&lt;String, Vec&lt;u8&gt;</code> lookup).
While it might be useful to isolate the filesystem overhead from Python code
overhead, the thing that end-users care about is overall execution time: they
don't care where that overhead is coming from. So I think it is fair to compare
PyOxidizer - with its intrinsically simpler import model - with what Python
typically does (scan <code>sys.path</code> entries and looking for modules on the
filesystem).</p>
<p>Another difference is that PyOxidizer is almost completely statically linked.
By contrast, a typical CPython install has compiled extension modules as
standalone shared libraries and these shared libraries often link against
other shared libraries (such as libssl). From <code>dtruss</code> timing information,
I don't believe this difference contributes to significant overhead, however.</p>
<p>Finally, I haven't yet optimized PyOxidizer. I still have a few tricks up
my sleeve that can likely shave off more overhead from Python startup. But
so far the results are looking <em>very</em> promising. I dare say they are looking
promising enough that Python distributions themselves might want to look
into the area more thoroughly and consider distribution defaults that rely
less on the every-Python-module-is-a-separate-file model.</p>
<p>Stay tuned for more <a href="https://github.com/indygreg/PyOxidizer">PyOxidizer</a>
updates in the near future!</p>
<p><em>(I updated this post a day after initial publication to add measurements
for Linux.)</em></p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <author>
      <name>Gregory Szorc</name>
      <uri>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog</uri>
    </author>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Distributing Standalone Python Applications]]></title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2018/12/18/distributing-standalone-python-applications" />
    <id>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2018/12/18/distributing-standalone-python-applications</id>
    <updated>2018-12-18T15:35:00Z</updated>
    <published>2018-12-18T15:35:00Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Python" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="PyOxidizer" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Rust" />
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Distributing Standalone Python Applications]]></summary>
    <content type="html" xml:base="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2018/12/18/distributing-standalone-python-applications"><![CDATA[<h2>The Problem</h2>
<p>Packaging and application distribution is a hard problem on multiple
dimensions. For Python, large aspects of this problem space are more or
less solved if you are distributing open source Python libraries and your
target audience is developers (<em>use pip and PyPI</em>). But if you are distributing
Python <em>applications</em> - standalone executables that use Python - your
world can be much more complicated.</p>
<p>One of the primary reasons why distributing Python applications is difficult
is because of the complex and often sensitive relationship between a Python
application and the environment it runs in.</p>
<p>For starters we have the Python interpreter itself. If your application doesn't
distribute the Python interpreter, you are at the whims of the Python
interpreter provided by the host machine. You may want to target Python 3.7
only. But because Python 3.5 or 3.6 is the most recent version installed by
many Linux distros, you are forced to support older Python versions and all
their quirks and lack of features.</p>
<p>Going down the rabbit hole, even the presence of a supposedly compatible
version of the Python interpreter isn't a guarantee for success! For example,
the Python interpreter could have a built-in extension that links against
an old version of a library. Just last week I was encountering weird SQlite
bugs in Firefox's automation because Python was using an old version of
SQLite with known bugs. Installing a modern SQLite fixed the problems. Or
the interpreter could have modifications or extra installed packages
interfering with the operation of your application. There are never-ending
corner cases. And I can tell you from my experience with having to support
the Firefox build system (which uses Python heavily) that you will encounter
these corner cases given a broad enough user base.</p>
<p>And even if the Python interpreter on the target machine is fully compatible,
getting your code to run on that interpreter could be difficult! Several
Python applications leverage compiled extensions linking against Python's
C API. Distributing the precompiled form of the extension can be challenging,
especially when your code needs to link against 3rd party libraries, which
may conflict with something on the target system. And, the precompiled
extensions need to be built in a very delicate manner to ensure they can
run on as many target machines as possible. But not distributing pre-built
binaries requires the end-user be able to compile Python extensions. Not
every user has such an environment and forcing this requirement on them is
not user friendly.</p>
<p><strong>From an application developer's point of view, distributing a copy of the
Python interpreter along with your application is the only reliable way of
guaranteeing a more uniform end-user experience.</strong> Yes, you will still
have variability because every machine is different. But you've eliminated
the the Python interpreter from the set of unknowns and that is a huge win.
(Unfortunately, distributing a Python interpreter comes with a host of other
problems such as size bloat, security/patching concerns, poking the OS
packaging bears, etc. But those problems are for another post.)</p>
<h2>Existing Solutions</h2>
<p>There are tons of existing tools for <em>solving</em> the Python application
distribution problem.</p>
<p>The approach that tools like <a href="https://shiv.readthedocs.io/en/latest/">Shiv</a>
and <a href="https://github.com/pantsbuild/pex">PEX</a> take is to leverage Python's
built-in support for <em>running</em> zip files. Essentially, if there is a zip
file containing a <code>__main__.py</code> file and you execute <code>python file.zip</code>
(or have a zip file with a <code>#!/usr/bin/env python</code> shebang), Python
can load modules in that zip file and execute an application within. Pretty
cool!</p>
<p>This approach works great if your execution environment supports shebangs
(Windows doesn't) and the Python interpreter is suitable. But if you need
to support Windows or don't have control over the execution environment
and can't guarantee the Python interpreter is <em>good</em>, this approach isn't
suitable.</p>
<p>As stated above, we want to distribute the Python interpreter with our
application to minimize variability. Let's talk about tools that do that.</p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/facebookincubator/xar/">XAR</a> is a pretty cool offering
from Facebook. XAR files are executables that contain
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SquashFS">SquashFS</a> filesystems. Upon running
the executable, SquashFS filesystems are created. For Python applications,
the XAR contains a copy of the Python interpreter and all your Python modules.
At run-time, these files are <em>extracted</em> to SquashFS filesystems and the
Python interpreter is executed. If you squint hard enough, it is kind of
like a pre-packaged, executable virtualenv which also contains the Python
interpreter.</p>
<p>XARs are pretty cool (and aren't limited to Python). However, because XARs
rely on SquashFS, they have a run-time requirement on the target machine.
This is great if you only need to support Linux and macOS and your target
machines support FUSE and SquashFS. But if you need to support Windows or
a general user population without SquashFS support, XARs won't help you.</p>
<p>Zip files and XARs are great for enterprises that have tightly controlled
environments. But for a general end-user population, we need something
more robust against variance among target machines.</p>
<p>There are a handful of tools for packaging Python applications along with
the Python interpreter in more resilient manners.</p>
<p><a href="http://nuitka.net/pages/overview.html">Nuitka</a> <em>converts</em> Python source
to C code then compiles and links that C code against libpython. You can
perform a static link and compile everything down to a single executable.
If you do the compiling properly, that executable should <em>just work</em> on
pretty much every target machine. That's pretty cool and is exactly the
kind of solution application distributors are looking for: you can't get
much simpler than a self-contained executable! While I'd love to vouch
for Nuitka and recommend using it, I haven't used it so can't. And I'll
be honest, the prospect of compiling Python source to C code kind of
terrifies me. That effectively makes Nuitka a new Python implementation
and I'm not sure I can (yet) place the level of trust in Nuitka that I
have for e.g. CPython and PyPy.</p>
<p>And that leads us to our final category of tools:
<a href="https://docs.python-guide.org/shipping/freezing/">freezing your code</a>. There
are a handful of tools like <a href="https://www.pyinstaller.org/">PyInstaller</a>
which automate the process of building your Python application (often via
standard <code>setup.py</code> mechanisms), assembling all the requisite bits of
the Python interpreter, and producing an artifact that can be distributed
to end users. There are even tools that produce Windows installers, RPMs,
DEBs, etc that you can sign and distribute.</p>
<p>These <em>freezing</em> tools are arguably the state of the art for Python
application distribution to general user populations. On first glance
it seems like all the needed tools are available here. But there are
cracks below the surface.</p>
<h2>Issues with Freezing</h2>
<p>A common problem with freezing is it often relies on the Python interpreter
used to build the frozen application. For example, when building a frozen
application on Linux, it will bundle the system's Python interpreter with
the frozen application. And that interpreter may link against libraries
or libc symbol versions not available on all target machines. So, the
build environment has to be <em>just right</em> in order for the binaries to
run on as many target systems as possible. This isn't an insurmountable
problem. But it adds overhead and complexity to application maintainers.</p>
<p>Another limitation is how these frozen applications handle importing
Python modules.</p>
<p>Multiple tools take the approach of embedding an archive (usually a zip file)
in the executable containing the Python <em>standard library</em> bits not part of
libpython. This includes C extensions (compiled to <code>.so</code> or <code>.pyd</code> files)
and Python source (<code>.py</code>) or bytecode (<code>.pyc</code>) files. There is typically
a step - either at application start time or at module import time - where a
file is extracted to the filesystem such that Python's filesystem-based
importer can load it from there.</p>
<p>For example, PyInstaller <a href="https://pyinstaller.readthedocs.io/en/stable/operating-mode.html#how-the-one-file-program-works">extracts the standard library to a temporary directory
at application start time</a>
(at least when running in single file mode). This can add significant overhead
to the startup time of applications - more than enough to blow through people's
ability to perceive something as <em>instantaneous</em>. This is acceptable for
long-running applications. But for applications (like CLI tools or support
tools for build systems), the overhead can be a non-starter. And, the mere
fact that you are doing filesystem write I/O establishes a requirement that
the application have write access to the filesystem and that write I/O can
perform reasonably well lest application performance suffer. These can be
difficult pills to swallow!</p>
<p>Another limitation is that these tools often assume the executable being
produced is only a Python application. Sometimes Python is <em>part of</em> a
larger application. It would be useful to produce a library that can
easily be embedded within a larger application.</p>
<h2>Improving the State of the Art</h2>
<p>Existing Python application distribution mechanisms don't tick all the
requirements boxes for me. We have tools that are suitable for internal
distribution in well-defined <em>enterprise</em> environments. And we have tools
that target general user populations, albeit with a burden on application
maintainers and often come with a performance hit and/or limited flexibility.</p>
<p>I want something that allows me to produce a standalone, single file executable
containing a Python interpreter, the Python standard library (or a subset of
it), and all the custom code and resources my application needs. That
executable should not require any additional library dependencies beyond what is
already available on most target machines (e.g. libc). That executable should
not require any special filesystem providers (e.g. FUSE/SquashFS) nor should
it require filesystem write access nor perform filesystem write I/O at run-time.
I should be able to embed a Python interpreter within a larger application,
without the overhead of starting the Python interpreter if it isn't needed.</p>
<p>No existing solution ticks all of these boxes.</p>
<p>So I set out to build one.</p>
<p>One problem is producing a Python interpreter that is portable and
fully-featured. You can't punt on this problem because if the core Python
interpreter isn't produced in just the right way, your application will
depend on libraries or symbol versions not available in all environments.</p>
<p>I've created the <a href="https://github.com/indygreg/python-build-standalone">python-build-standalone</a>
project for automating the process of building Python interpreters suitable
for use with standalone, distributable Python applications. The project
produces (and has available for download) binary artifacts including a
pre-compiled Python interpreter and object files used for compiling that
interpreter. The Python interpreter is compiled with PGO/LTO using a modern
Clang, helping to ensure that Python code runs as fast as it can. All of
Python's dependencies are compiled from source with the modern toolchain and
everything is aggressively statically linked to avoid external dependencies.
The toolchain and pre-built distribution are available for downstream
consumers to compile Python extensions with/against.</p>
<p>It's worth noting that use of a modern Clang toolchain is likely sufficiently
different from what you use today. When producing <em>manylinux</em> wheels, it is
recommended to use the <a href="https://github.com/pypa/manylinux">pypa/manylinux</a>
Docker images. These Docker images are based on CentOS 5 (for maximum libc
and other system library compatibility). While they do install a custom
toolchain, Python and any extensions compiled in that environment are compiled
with GCC 4.8.2 (as of this writing). That's a GCC from 2013. A lot has
changed in compilers since 2013 and building Python and extensions with a
compiler released in 2018 should result in various benefits (faster code,
better warnings, etc).</p>
<p>If producing custom CPython builds for standalone distribution interests
you, you should take a look at how I coerced CPython to statically link
all extensions. Spoiler: it involves producing a custom-tailored
<code>Modules/Setup.local</code> file that bypasses <code>setup.py</code>, along with some
<code>Makefile</code> hacks. Because the build environment is deterministic and isolated
in a container, we can get away with some ugly hacks.</p>
<p>A statically linked <code>libpython</code> from which you can produce a standalone
binary embedding Python is only the first layer in the onion. The next layer
is how to handle the Python standard library.</p>
<p><code>libpython</code> only contains the code needed to run the core bits of the Python
interpreter. If we attempt to run a statically linked <code>python</code> executable
without the standard library in the filesystem, things fail pretty fast:</p>
<pre><code>$ rm -rf lib
$ bin/python
Could not find platform independent libraries &lt;prefix&gt;
Could not find platform dependent libraries &lt;exec_prefix&gt;
Consider setting $PYTHONHOME to &lt;prefix&gt;[:&lt;exec_prefix&gt;]
Fatal Python error: initfsencoding: Unable to get the locale encoding
ModuleNotFoundError: No module named 'encodings'

Current thread 0x00007fe9a3432740 (most recent call first):
Aborted (core dumped)
</code></pre>
<p>I'll spare you the details for the moment, but initializing the CPython
interpreter (via <code>Py_Initialize()</code> <em>requires</em> that parts of the Python
standard library be available). This means that in order to fulfill our dream
of a single file executable, we will need custom code that teaches the
embedded Python interpreter to load the standard library from within the
binary... somehow.</p>
<p>As far as I know, efficient embedded standard library handling without run-time
requirements does not exist in the current Python packaging/distribution
ecosystem. So, I had to devise something new.</p>
<p>Enter <a href="https://github.com/indygreg/pyoxidizer">PyOxidizer</a>. PyOxidizer is
a collection of Rust crates that facilitate building an embeddable Python
library, which can easily be added to an executable. We need <em>native</em> code
to interface with the Python C APIs in order to influence Python interpreter
startup. It is 2018 and Rust is a better C/C++, so I chose Rust for this
<em>driver</em> functionality instead of C. Plus, Rust's integrated build system
makes it easier to automate the integration of the custom Python interpreter
files into binaries.</p>
<p>The role of PyOxidizer is to take the pre-built Python interpreter files from
<a href="https://github.com/indygreg/python-build-standalone">python-build-standalone</a>,
combine those files with any other Python files needed to run an application,
and marry them to a Rust crate. This Rust crate can trivially be turned into
a self-contained executable containing a Python application. Or, it can be
combined with another Rust project. Or it can be emitted as a library and
integrated with a non-Rust application. There's a lot of flexibility by design.</p>
<p>The mechanism I used for embedding the Python standard library into a single
file executable without incurring explicit filesystem access at run-time is
(I believe) new, novel, and somewhat crazy. Let me explain how it works.</p>
<p>First, there are no <code>.so</code>/<code>.pyd</code> shared library compiled Python extensions
to worry about. This is because all compiled extensions are statically linked
into the Python interpreter. To the interpreter, they exist as
<a href="https://docs.python.org/3.7/library/importlib.html#importlib.machinery.BuiltinImporter">built-in modules</a>.
Typically, a CPython build will have some modules like <code>_abc</code>, <code>_io</code>, and
<code>sys</code> provided by <em>built-in modules</em>. Modules like <code>_json</code> exist as standalone
shared libraries that are loaded on demand. <code>python-build-standalone</code>'s
modifications to CPython's build system converts all these would-be standalone
shared libraries into <em>built-in modules</em>. (Because we distribute the object
files that compose the eventual <code>libpython</code>, it is possible to filter out
unwanted modules to cut down on binary size if you don't want to ship a
fully-featured Python interpreter.) Because there are no standalone shared
libraries providing Python modules, we don't have the problem of needing to
load a shared library to load a module, which would undermine our goal of
<em>no filesystem access to import modules</em>. And that's a good thing, too,
because <code>dlopen()</code> requires a path: you can't load a shared library from
a memory address. (Fun fact: there are hacks like
<a href="https://sourceware.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=11767">dlopen_with_offset()</a>
that provide an API to load a library from memory, but they require a custom
libc. Google uses this approach for their internal single-file Python
application solution.)</p>
<p>From the <code>python-build-standalone</code> artifacts, PyOxidizer collects all files
belonging to the Python standard library (notably <code>.py</code> and <code>.pyc</code> files).
It also collects other source, bytecode, and resource files needed to run
a custom application.</p>
<p>The relevant files are assembled and serialized into data structures which
contain the names of the resources and their raw content. These data structures
are made available to Rust as <code>&amp;'static [u8]</code> variables (essentially a
<code>static void*</code> if you don't speak Rust).</p>
<p>Using the <a href="https://github.com/dgrunwald/rust-cpython">rust-cpython</a> crate,
PyOxidizer defines a custom Python extension module implemented purely in Rust.
When loaded, the module parses the data structures containing available
Python resource names and data into <code>HashMap&lt;&amp;str, &amp;[u8]&gt;</code> instances. In other
words, it builds a native mapping from resource name to a pointer to its raw
data. The Rust-implemented module exports to Python an API for accessing that
data. From the Python side, you do the equivalent of <code>MODULES.get_code('foo')</code>
to request the bytecode for a named Python module. When called, the Rust code
will perform the lookup and return a <code>memoryview</code> instance pointing to the
raw data. (The use of <code>&amp;[u8]</code> and <code>memoryview</code> means that embedded resource
data is loaded from its static, read-only memory location instead of copied
into a data structure managed by Python. This zero copy approach translates to
less overhead for importing modules. Although, the memory needs to be paged
in by the operating system. So on slow filesystems, reducing I/O and e.g.
compressing module data might be a worthwhile optimization. This can be a
future feature.) </p>
<p>Making data embedded within a binary available to a Python module is relatively
easy. I'm definitely not the first person to come up with this idea. What is
hard - and what I <em>might</em> be the first person to actually do - is how you make
the Python module importing mechanism load <em>all</em> standard library modules via
such a mechanism.</p>
<p>With a custom extension module built-in to the binary exposing module data,
it should <em>just</em> be a matter of registering a custom
<a href="https://docs.python.org/3.7/library/sys.html#sys.meta_path">sys.meta_path</a>
importer that knows how to load modules from that custom location. This
problem turns out to be quite hard!</p>
<p>The initialization of a CPython interpreter is - as I've learned - a bit
complex. A CPython interpreter must be initialized via <code>Py_Initialize()</code>
before any Python code can run. That means in order to modify <code>sys.meta_path</code>,
<code>Py_Initialize()</code> must finish.</p>
<p>A lot of activity occurs under the hood during initialization. Applications
embedding Python have very little control over what happens during
<code>Py_Initialize()</code>. You can change some superficial things like what
filesystem paths to use to bootstrap <code>sys.path</code> and what encodings to use
for stdio descriptors. But you can't really influence the core actions that are
being performed. And there's no mechanism to directly influence
<code>sys.meta_path</code> before an <code>import</code> is performed. (Perhaps there should be?)</p>
<p>During <code>Py_Initialize()</code>, the interpreter needs to configure the encodings
for the filesystem and the stdio descriptors. Encodings are loaded from
Python modules provided by the standard library. So, during the course of
<code>Py_Initialize()</code>, the interpreter needs to import some modules originally
backed by <code>.py</code> files. This creates a dilemma: if <code>Py_Initialize()</code>
needs to <code>import</code> modules in the standard library, the standard library
is backed by memory and isn't available to known importing mechanisms, and
there's no opportunity to configure a custom <code>sys.meta_path</code> importer
before <code>Py_Initialize()</code> runs, how do you teach the interpreter about
your custom module importer and the location of the standard library modules
needed by <code>Py_Initialize()</code>?</p>
<p>This is an extremely gnarly problem and it took me some hours and many false
leads to come up with a solution.</p>
<p>My first attempt involved the esoteric
<a href="https://docs.python.org/3/c-api/import.html#c.PyImport_FrozenModules">frozen modules</a>
feature. (This work predated the use of a custom data structure and module
containing modules data.) The Python interpreter has a
<code>const struct _frozen* PyImport_FrozenModules</code> data structure defining an
array of <em>frozen</em> modules. A <em>frozen</em> module is defined by its module
name and precompiled bytecode data (roughly equivalent to <code>.pyc</code> file
content). Partway through <code>Py_Initialize()</code>, the Python interpreter is able
to import modules. And one of the built-in importers that is automatically
registered knows how to load modules if they are in <code>PyImport_FrozenModules</code>!</p>
<p>I attempted to audit Python interpreter startup and find all modules
that were imported during <code>Py_Initialize()</code>. I then defined a custom
<code>PyImport_FrozenModules</code> containing these modules. In theory, the import
of these modules during <code>Py_Initialize()</code> would be handled by the
<a href="https://docs.python.org/3.7/library/importlib.html#importlib.machinery.FrozenImporter">FrozenImporter</a>
and everything would <em>just work</em>: if I were able to get <code>Py_Initialize()</code> to
complete, I'd be able to register a custom <code>sys.meta_path</code> importer
immediately afterwards and we'd be set.</p>
<p>Things did not go as planned.</p>
<p><code>FrozenImporter</code> doesn't fully conform to the
<a href="https://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-0451/">PEP 451</a> requirements for
setting specific attributes on modules. Without these attributes, the
<code>from . import aliases</code> statement in <code>encodings/__init__.py</code> fails
because the importer is unable to resolve the relative module name. Derp.
One would think CPython's built-in importers would comply with PEP 451
and that all of Python's standard library could be imported as frozen modules.
But this is not the case! I was able to hack around this particular failure
by using an absolute import. But I hit another failure and did not want to
excavate that rabbit hole. Once I realized that <code>FrozenImporter</code> was lacking
mandated module attributes, I concluded that attempting to use <em>frozen modules</em>
as a general import-from-memory mechanism was not viable. Furthermore, the
C code backing <code>FrozenImporter</code> walks the <code>PyImport_FrozenModules</code> array and
does a string compare on the module name to find matches. While I didn't
benchmark, I was concerned that un-indexed scanning at import time would
add considerable overhead when hundreds of modules were in play. (The C code
backing <code>BuiltinImporter</code> uses the same approach and I do worry CPython's
imports of built-in extension modules is causing measurable overhead.)</p>
<p>With <em>frozen modules</em> off the table, I needed to find another way to inject
a custom module importer that was usable during <code>Py_Initialize()</code>. Because
we control the source Python interpreter, modifications to the source code
or even link-time modifications or run-time hacks like trampolines weren't
off the table. But I <strong>really</strong> wanted things to work out of the box because
I don't want to be in the business of maintaining patches to Python
interpreters.</p>
<p>My foray into <em>frozen modules</em> enlightened me to the craziness that is
the bootstrapping of Python's importing mechanism.</p>
<p>I remember hearing that the Python module importing mechanism used to be
written in C and was rewritten in Python. And I knew that the
<a href="https://docs.python.org/3.7/library/importlib.html">importlib</a> package
defined interfaces allowing you to implement your own importers, which
could be registered on
<a href="https://docs.python.org/3.7/library/sys.html#sys.meta_path">sys.meta_path</a>.
But I didn't know how all of this worked at the interpreter level.</p>
<p>The internal <a href="https://github.com/python/cpython/blob/08c2ba0717089662132af69bf5948d82277a8a69/Python/pylifecycle.c#L178">initimport()</a>
C function is responsible for initializing the module importing mechanism. It
does the equivalent of <code>import _frozen_importlib</code>, but using the
<a href="https://docs.python.org/3/c-api/import.html#c.PyImport_ImportFrozenModuleObject">PyImport_ImportFrozenModule()</a>
API. It then manipulates some symbols and calls <code>_frozen_importlib.install()</code>
with references to the <code>sys</code> and <code>imp</code> built-in modules. Later (in
<code>initexternalimport()</code>), a <code>_frozen_importlib_external</code> module is imported
and has code within it executed.</p>
<p>I was initially very confused by this because - while there are references
to <code>_frozen_importlib</code> and <code>_frozen_importlib_external</code> all over the
CPython code base, I couldn't figure out where the code for those modules
actually lived! Some sleuthing of the build directory eventually revealed
that the files <a href="https://github.com/python/cpython/blob/08c2ba0717089662132af69bf5948d82277a8a69/Lib/importlib/_bootstrap.py">Lib/importlib/_bootstrap.py</a>
and <a href="https://github.com/python/cpython/blob/08c2ba0717089662132af69bf5948d82277a8a69/Lib/importlib/_bootstrap_external.py">Lib/importlib/_bootstrap_external.py</a>
were <em>frozen</em> to the module names <code>_frozen_importlib</code> and
<code>_frozen_importlib_external</code>, respectively.</p>
<p>Essentially what is happening is the bulk of Python's import <em>machinery</em> is
implemented in Python (rather than C). But there's a chicken-and-egg
problem where you can't run just any Python code (including any <code>import</code>
statement) until the interpreter is partially or fully initialized.</p>
<p>When building CPython, the Python source code for <code>importlib._bootstrap</code>
and <code>importlib._bootstrap_external</code> are compiled to bytecode. This
bytecode is emitted to <code>.h</code> files, where it is exposed as a
<code>static char *</code>. This bytecode is eventually referenced by the
default <code>PyImport_FrozenModules</code> array, allowing the modules to be
imported via the frozen importer's C API, which bypasses the higher-level
importing mechanism, allowing it to work before the full importing
mechanism is initialized.</p>
<p><code>initimport()</code> and <code>initexternalimport()</code> both call Python functions in
the frozen modules. And we can clearly look at the source of the
corresponding modules and see the Python code do things like
<a href="https://github.com/python/cpython/blob/08c2ba0717089662132af69bf5948d82277a8a69/Lib/importlib/_bootstrap.py#L1158">register the default importers on <code>sys.meta_path</code></a>.</p>
<p>Whew, that was a long journey into the bowels of CPython's internals. How
does all this help with single file Python executables?</p>
<p>Well, the predicament that led us down this rabbit hole was there was no
way to register a custom module importer before <code>Py_Initialize()</code>
completes and before an <code>import</code> is attempted during said <code>Py_Initialize()</code>.</p>
<p>It took me a while, but I finally realized the frozen
<code>importlib._bootstrap_external</code> module provided the window I needed!
<code>importlib._bootstrap_external</code>/<code>_frozen_importlib_external</code> is <em>always</em>
executed during <code>Py_Initialize()</code>. So if you can modify this module's code,
you can run arbitrary code during <code>Py_Initialize()</code> and influence Python
interpreter configuration. And since <code>_frozen_importlib_external</code> is a frozen
module and the <code>PyImport_FrozenModules</code> array is writable and can be modified
before <code>Py_Initialize()</code> is called, all one needs to do is replace the
<code>_frozen_importlib</code> / <code>_frozen_importlib_external</code> bytecode in
<code>PyImport_FrozenModules</code> and you can run arbitrary code during Python
interpreter startup, before <code>Py_Initialize()</code> completes and before any
standard library imports are performed!</p>
<p>My solution to this problem is to concatenate some custom Python code to
<code>importlib/_bootstrap_external.py</code>. This custom code defines a
<code>sys.meta_path</code> importer that knows how to use our Rust-backed built-in
extension module to find and load module data. It redefines the <code>_install()</code>
function so that this custom importer is registered on <code>sys.meta_path</code>
when the function is called during <code>Py_Initialize()</code>. The <em>new</em> Python
source is compiled to bytecode and the <code>PyImport_FrozenModules</code> array is
modified at run-time to point to the modified <code>_frozen_importlib_external</code>
implementation. When <code>Py_Initialize()</code> executes its first standard library
import, module data is provided by the custom <code>sys.meta_path</code> importer,
which grabs it from a Rust extension module, which reads it from a
read-only data structure in the executable binary, which is converted
to a Python <code>memoryview</code> instance and sent back to Python for processing.</p>
<p>There's a bit of <em>magic</em> happening behind the scenes to make all of this
work. PyOxidizer attempts to hide as much of the gory details as possible.
From the perspective of an application maintainer, you just need to define
a minimal config file and it handles most of the low-level details. And there's
even a higher-level Rust API for configuring the embedded Python interpreter,
should you need it.</p>
<p><code>python-build-standalone</code> and <code>PyOxidizer</code> are still in their infancy.
They are very much alpha quality. I consider them technology previews more
than usable software at this point. But I think enough is there to demonstrate
the viability of using Rust as the build system and run-time glue to build
and distribute standalone applications embedding Python.</p>
<p>Time will tell if my utopian vision of zero-copy, no explicit filesystem
I/O for Python module imports will pan out. Others who have ventured into
this space have warned me that lots of Python modules rely on <code>__file__</code>
to derive paths to other resources, which are later <code>stat()</code>d and
<code>open()</code>d. <code>__file__</code> for in-memory modules doesn't exactly make sense
and can't be operated on like normal paths/files. I'm not sure what the
inevitable struggles to support these modules will lead to. Maybe we'll have
to extract things to temporary directories like other standalone Python
applications. Maybe <code>PyOxidizer</code> will take off and people will start using
the <a href="https://docs.python.org/3.7/library/importlib.html#importlib.abc.ResourceReader">ResourceReader</a>
API, which is apparently the proper way to do these things these days.
(Caveat: <code>PyOxidizer</code> doesn't yet implement this API but support is planned.)
Time will tell. I'm not opposed to gross hacks or writing more code as
needed.</p>
<p>Producing highly distributable and performant Python applications has been far
too difficult for far too long. My primary goal for PyOxidizer is to lower these
barriers. By leveraging Rust, I also hope to bring Python and Rust closer
together. I want to enable applications and libraries to effortlessly harness
the powers of both of these fantastic programming languages.</p>
<p>Again, <code>PyOxidizer</code> is still in its infancy. I anticipate a significant amount
of hacking over the holidays and hope to share updates in the weeks ahead. Until
then, please leave comments, watch the <a href="https://github.com/indygreg/PyOxidizer">project on GitHub</a>,
file issues for bugs and feature requests, etc and we'll see where things lead.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <author>
      <name>Gregory Szorc</name>
      <uri>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog</uri>
    </author>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Global Kernel Locks in APFS]]></title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2018/10/29/global-kernel-locks-in-apfs" />
    <id>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2018/10/29/global-kernel-locks-in-apfs</id>
    <updated>2018-10-29T14:20:00Z</updated>
    <published>2018-10-29T14:20:00Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Python" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Mercurial" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Apple" />
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Global Kernel Locks in APFS]]></summary>
    <content type="html" xml:base="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2018/10/29/global-kernel-locks-in-apfs"><![CDATA[<p>Over the past several months, a handful of people had been complaining
that Mercurial's test harness was executing much slower on Macs. But
this slowdown seemingly wasn't occurring on Linux or Windows. And not
every Mac user experienced the slowness!</p>
<p>Before jetting off to the Mercurial 4.8 developer meetup in Stockholm
a few weeks ago, I sat down with a relatively fresh 6+6 core MacBook Pro
and experienced the problem firsthand: on my 4+4 core i7-6700K running
Linux, the Mercurial test harness completes in ~12 minutes, but on this
MacBook Pro, it was executing in ~38 minutes! On paper, this result
doesn't make any sense because there's no way that the MacBook Pro should
be ~3x slower than that desktop machine.</p>
<p>Looking at Activity Monitor when running the test harness with 12 tests
in parallel revealed something odd: the system was spending ~75% of overall
CPU time inside the kernel! When reducing the number of tests that ran in
parallel, the percentage of CPU time spent in the kernel decreased and
the overall test harness execution time also decreased. This kind of
behavior is usually a sign of something very inefficient in kernel land.</p>
<p>I sample profiled all processes on the system when running the Mercurial
test harness. Aggregate thread stacks revealed a common pattern:
<code>readdir()</code> being in the stack.</p>
<p>Upon closer examination of the stacks, <code>readdir()</code> calls into
<code>apfs_vnop_readdir()</code>, which calls into some functions with <code>bt</code> or
<code>btree</code> in their name, which call into <code>lck_mtx_lock()</code>,
<code>lck_mtx_lock_grab_mutex()</code> and various other functions with
<code>lck_mtx</code> in their name. And the caller of most <code>readdir()</code> appeared
to be Python 2.7's module importing mechanism (notably
<code>import.c:case_ok()</code>).</p>
<p>APFS refers to the
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apple_File_System">Apple File System</a>,
which is a filesystem that Apple introduced in 2017 and is the
default filesystem for new versions of macOS and iOS. If upgrading an
old Mac to a new macOS, its HFS+ filesystems would be automatically
converted to APFS.</p>
<p>While the source code for APFS is not available for me to confirm, the
profiling results showing excessive time spent in
<code>lck_mtx_lock_grab_mutex()</code> combined with the fact that execution time
decreases when the parallel process count decreases leads me to the
conclusion that <strong>APFS obtains a global kernel lock during read-only
operations such as <code>readdir()</code></strong>. In other words, APFS slows down when
attempting to perform parallel read-only I/O.</p>
<p>This isn't the first time I've encountered such behavior in a
filesystem: last year I
<a href="/blog/2017/12/08/good-riddance-to-aufs/">blogged about very similar behavior in AUFS</a>,
which was making Firefox CI significantly slower.</p>
<p>Because Python 2.7's module importing mechanism was triggering the
slowness by calling <code>readdir()</code>, I
<a href="https://mail.python.org/pipermail/python-dev/2018-October/155466.html">posted to python-dev</a>
about the problem, as I thought it was important to notify the larger
Python community. After all, this is a generic problem that affects
the performance of starting <em>any</em> Python process when running on APFS.
i.e. if your build system invokes many Python processes in parallel,
you could be impacted by this. As part of obtaining data for that post, I
discovered that Python 3.7 does not call <code>readdir()</code> as part of
module importing and therefore doesn't exhibit a severe slowdown. (Python's
module importing code was rewritten significantly in Python 3 and the <em>fix</em>
was likely introduced well before Python 3.7.)</p>
<p>I've <a href="https://gist.github.com/indygreg/a50e187f5372807cdcab5ac12bc2feea">produced a gist that can reproduce the problem</a>.
The script essentially performs a recursive directory walk. It exercises
the <code>opendir()</code>, <code>readdir()</code>, <code>closedir()</code>, and <code>lstat()</code> functions
heavily and is essentially a benchmark of the filesystem and filesystem
cache's ability to return file metadata.</p>
<p>When you tell it to walk a very large directory tree - say a Firefox
version control checkout (which has over 250,000 files) - the excessive
time spent in the kernel is very apparent on macOS 10.13 High Sierra:</p>
<pre><code>$ time ./slow-readdir.py -l 12 ~/src/firefox
ran 12 walks across 12 processes in 172.209s

real    2m52.470s
user    1m54.053s
sys    23m42.808s

$ time ./slow-readdir.py -l 12 -j 1 ~/src/firefox
ran 12 walks across 1 processes in 523.440s

real    8m43.740s
user    1m13.397s
sys     3m50.687s

$ time ./slow-readdir.py -l 18 -j 18 ~/src/firefox
ran 18 walks across 18 processes in 210.487s

real    3m30.731s
user    2m40.216s
sys    33m34.406s
</code></pre>
<p>On the same machine upgraded to macOS 10.14 Mojave, we see a bit of a
speedup!:</p>
<pre><code>$ time ./slow-readdir.py -l 12 ~/src/firefox
ran 12 walks across 12 processes in 97.833s

real    1m37.981s
user    1m40.272s
sys    10m49.091s

$ time ./slow-readdir.py -l 12 -j 1 ~/src/firefox
ran 12 walks across 1 processes in 461.415s

real    7m41.657s
user    1m05.830s
sys     3m47.041s

$ time ./slow-readdir.py -l 18 -j 18 ~/src/firefox
ran 18 walks across 18 processes in 140.474s

real    2m20.727s
user    3m01.048s
sys    17m56.228s
</code></pre>
<p>Contrast with my i7-6700K Linux machine backed by EXT4:</p>
<pre><code>$ time ./slow-readdir.py -l 8 ~/src/firefox
ran 8 walks across 8 processes in 6.018s

real    0m6.191s
user    0m29.670s
sys     0m17.838s

$ time ./slow-readdir.py -l 8 -j 1 ~/src/firefox
ran 8 walks across 1 processes in 33.958s

real    0m34.164s
user    0m17.136s
sys     0m13.369s

$ time ./slow-readdir.py -l 12 -j 12 ~/src/firefox
ran 12 walks across 12 processes in 25.465s

real    0m25.640s
user    1m4.801s
sys     1m20.488s
</code></pre>
<p>It is apparent that macOS 10.14 Mojave has received performance work
relative to macOS 10.13! Overall kernel CPU time when performing parallel
directory walks has decreased substantially - to ~50% of original on some
invocations! Stacks seem to reveal new code for lock acquisition, so this
might indicate generic improvements to the kernel's locking mechanism
rather than APFS specific changes. Changes to file metadata caching could
also be responsible for performance changes. Although it is difficult to tell
without access to the APFS source code. Despite those improvements, APFS
is still spending a lot of CPU time in the kernel. And the kernel CPU time
is still comparatively very high compared to Linux/EXT4, even for single
process operation.</p>
<p>At this time, I haven't conducted a comprehensive analysis of APFS to
determine what other filesystem operations seem to acquire global kernel
locks: all I know is <code>readdir()</code> does. A casual analysis of profiled
stacks when running Mercurial's test harness against Python 3.7 seems
to show <code>apfs_*</code> functions still on the stack a lot and that seemingly
indicates more APFS slowness under parallel I/O load. But HFS+ exhibited
similar problems (it appeared HFS+ used a single I/O thread inside the
kernel for many operations, making I/O on macOS pretty bad), so I'm
not sure if these could be considered <em>regressions</em> the way <code>readdir()</code>'s
new behavior is.</p>
<p>I've reported this issue to Apple at
<a href="https://bugreport.apple.com/web/?problemID=45648013">https://bugreport.apple.com/web/?problemID=45648013</a>
and on OpenRadar at <a href="https://openradar.appspot.com/radar?id=5025294012383232">https://openradar.appspot.com/radar?id=5025294012383232</a>.
I'm told that issues get more attention from Apple when there are many
duplicates of the same issue. So please reference this issue if you file your
own report.</p>
<p>Now that I've elaborated on the technical details, I'd like to add some
personal commentary. While this post is about APFS, this issue of global
kernel locks during common I/O operations is not unique to APFS. I
<a href="/blog/2017/12/08/good-riddance-to-aufs/">already referenced</a> similar
issues in AUFS. And I've encountered similar behaviors with Btrfs (although
I can't recall exactly which operations). And NTFS has its own
<a href="https://github.com/Microsoft/WSL/issues/873#issuecomment-425272829">bag of problems</a>.</p>
<p>This seeming pattern of global kernel locks for common filesystem operations
and slow filesystems is really rubbing me the wrong way. Modern NVMe SSDs
are capable of reading and writing well over 2 gigabytes per second and
performing hundreds of thousands of I/O operations per second. We even have
Intel soon producing
<a href="https://newsroom.intel.com/editorials/re-architecting-data-center-memory-storage-hierarchy/">persistent solid state storage that plugs into DIMM slots</a>
because it is that friggin fast.</p>
<p>Today's storage hardware is capable of ludicrous performance. It is fast enough
that you will likely saturate multiple CPU cores processing the read or written
data coming from and going to storage - especially if you are using higher-level,
non-JITed (read: slower) programming languages (like Python). There has also been
a trend that systems are growing more CPU cores faster than they are instructions
per second per core. And SSDs only achieve these ridiculous IOPS numbers if many
I/O operations are <em>queued</em> and can be more efficiently dispatched within the
storage device. What this all means is that it probably makes sense to use
parallel I/O across multiple threads in order to extract all potential
performance from your persistent storage layer.</p>
<p>It's also worth noting that we now have solid state storage that outperforms (in
some dimensions) what DRAM from ~20 years ago was capable of. Put another way I/O
APIs and even some filesystems were designed in an era when its RAM was slower than
what today's persistent storage is capable of! While I'm no filesystems or kernel
expert, it does seem a bit silly to be using APIs and filesystems designed for an
era when storage was multiple orders of magnitude slower and systems only had a
single CPU core.</p>
<p>My takeaway is I can't help but feel that systems-level software (including the
kernel) is severely limiting the performance potential of modern storage
devices. If we have e.g. global kernel locks when performing common I/O operations,
there's no chance we'll come close to harnessing the full potential of today's
storage hardware. Furthermore, the behavior of filesystems is woefully under
documented and software developers have little solid advice for how to achieve
optimal I/O performance. As someone who cares about performance, I want to
squeeze every iota of potential out of hardware. But the lack of documentation
telling me which operations acquire locks, which strategies are best for say
reading or writing 10,000 files using N threads, etc makes this extremely
difficult. And even if this documentation existed, because of differences in
behavior across filesystems and operating systems and the difficulty in
programmatically determining the characteristics of filesystems at run time,
it is practically impossible to design a <em>one size fits all</em> approach to
high performance I/O.</p>
<p>The filesystem is a powerful concept. I want to agree and use the <em>everything is a
file</em> philosophy. Unfortunately, filesystems don't appear to be scaling very well
to support the potential of modern day storage technology. We're probably at the
point where commodity priced solid state storage is far more capable than today's
software for the majority of applications. Storage hardware manufacturers will
keep producing faster and faster storage and their marketing teams will keep
convincing us that we need to buy it. But until software catches up, chances are
most of us won't come close to realizing the true potential of modern storage
hardware. And that's even true for specialized applications that do employ tricks
taking hundreds or thousands of person hours to implement in order to eek out every
iota of performance potential. The average software developer and application
using filesystems as they were designed to be used has little to no chance of
coming close to utilizing the performance potential of modern storage devices.
That's really a shame. </p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <author>
      <name>Gregory Szorc</name>
      <uri>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog</uri>
    </author>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Release of python-zstandard 0.9]]></title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2018/04/09/release-of-python-zstandard-0.9" />
    <id>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2018/04/09/release-of-python-zstandard-0.9</id>
    <updated>2018-05-16T09:45:00Z</updated>
    <published>2018-04-09T09:30:00Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Python" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Mozilla" />
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Release of python-zstandard 0.9]]></summary>
    <content type="html" xml:base="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2018/04/09/release-of-python-zstandard-0.9"><![CDATA[<p>I have just released
<a href="https://pypi.python.org/pypi/zstandard/0.9.0">python-zstandard 0.9.0</a>. You can
install the latest release by running <code>pip install zstandard==0.9.0</code>.</p>
<p><a href="http://facebook.github.io/zstd/">Zstandard</a> is a highly tunable and therefore
flexible compression algorithm with support for modern features such as
multi-threaded compression and <em>dictionaries</em>. Its performance is remarkable
and if you use it as a drop-in replacement for zlib, bzip2, or other common
algorithms, you'll frequently see more than a doubling in performance.</p>
<p>python-zstandard provides rich bindings to the zstandard C library without
sacrificing performance, safety, features, or a Pythonic feel. The bindings
run on Python 2.7, 3.4, 3.5, 3.6, 3.7 using either a C extension or CFFI
bindings, so it works with CPython and PyPy.</p>
<p>I can make a compelling argument that python-zstandard is one of the
richest compression packages available to Python programmers. Using it, you
will be able to leverage compression in ways you couldn't with other packages
(especially those in the standard library) all while achieving ridiculous
performance. Due to my focus on performance, python-zstandard is able to
outperform Python bindings to other compression libraries that <em>should</em> be
faster. This is because python-zstandard is very diligent about minimizing
memory allocations and copying, minimizing Python object creation, reusing
state, etc.</p>
<p>While python-zstandard is formally marked as a beta-level project and hasn't
yet reached a 1.0 release, it is suitable for production usage.
python-zstandard 0.8 shipped with Mercurial and is in active production
use there. I'm also aware of other consumers using it in production, including
at Facebook and Mozilla.</p>
<p>The sections below document some of the new features of python-zstandard 0.9.</p>
<h2>File Object Interface for Reading</h2>
<p>The 0.9 release contains a <code>stream_reader()</code> API on the compressor and
decompressor objects that allows you to treat those objects as readable file
objects. This means that you can pass a <code>ZstdCompressor</code> or <code>ZstdDecompressor</code>
around to things that accept file objects and things generally <em>just work</em>.
e.g.:</p>
<div class="pygments_murphy"><pre><span></span>   <span class="k">with</span> <span class="nb">open</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">compressed_file</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s1">&#39;rb&#39;</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="k">as</span> <span class="n">ifh</span><span class="p">:</span>
       <span class="n">cctx</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">zstd</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">ZstdDecompressor</span><span class="p">()</span>
       <span class="k">with</span> <span class="n">cctx</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">stream_reader</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">ifh</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="k">as</span> <span class="n">reader</span><span class="p">:</span>
           <span class="k">while</span> <span class="bp">True</span><span class="p">:</span>
               <span class="n">chunk</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">reader</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">read</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">32768</span><span class="p">)</span>
               <span class="k">if</span> <span class="ow">not</span> <span class="n">chunk</span><span class="p">:</span>
                   <span class="k">break</span>
</pre></div>

<p>This is probably the most requested python-zstandard feature.</p>
<p>While the feature is usable, it isn't complete. Support for <code>readline()</code>,
<code>readinto()</code>, and a few other APIs is not yet implemented. In addition,
you can't use these <em>reader</em> objects for opening zstandard compressed
tarball files because Python's <code>tarfile</code> package insists on doing
backward seeks when reading. The current implementation doesn't support
backwards seeking because that requires buffering decompressed output and that
is not trivial to implement. I recognize that all these features are useful
and I will try to work them into a subsequent release of 0.9.</p>
<h2>Negative Compression Levels</h2>
<p>The 1.3.4 release of zstandard (which python-zstandard 0.9 bundles) supports
negative compression levels. I won't go into details, but negative compression
levels disable extra compression features and allow you to trade compression
ratio for more speed.</p>
<p>When compressing a 6,472,921,921 byte uncompressed bundle of the Firefox
Mercurial repository, the previous fastest we could go with level 1 was
~510 MB/s (measured on the input side) yielding a 1,675,227,803 file (25.88%
of original).</p>
<p>With level <code>-1</code>, we compress to 1,934,253,955 (29.88% of original) at
~590 MB/s. With level <code>-5</code>, we compress to 2,339,110,873 bytes (36.14% of
original) at ~720 MB/s.</p>
<p>On the decompress side, level 1 decompresses at ~1,150 MB/s (measured at
the output side), -1 at ~1,320 MB/s, and -5 at ~1,350 MB/s (generally speaking,
zstandard's decompression speeds are relatively similar - and fast - across
compression levels).</p>
<p>And that's just with a single thread. zstandard supports using multiple
threads to compress a single input and python-zstandard makes this feature
easy to use. Using 8 threads on my 4+4 core i7-6700K, level 1 compresses
at ~2,000 MB/s (3.9x speedup), -1 at ~2,300 MB/s (3.9x speedup), and -5
at ~2,700 MB/s (3.75x speedup).</p>
<p>That's with a large input. What about small inputs?</p>
<p>If we take 456,599 Mercurial commit objects spanning 298,609,254 bytes from
the Firefox repository and compress them individually, at level 1 we yield
a total of 133,457,198 bytes (44.7% of original) at ~112 MB/s. At level -1,
we compress to 161,241,797 bytes (54.0% of original) at ~215 MB/s. And at
level -5, we compress to 185,885,545 bytes (62.3% of original) at ~395 MB/s.</p>
<p>On the decompression side, level 1 decompresses at ~260 MB/s, -1 at
~1,000 MB/s, and -5 at ~1,150 MB/s.</p>
<p>Again, that's 456,599 operations on a single thread with Python.</p>
<p>python-zstandard has an <em>experimental</em> API where you can pass in a collection
of inputs and it batch compresses or decompresses them in a single operation.
It releases and GIL and uses multiple threads. It puts the results in shared
buffers in order to minimize the overhead of memory allocations and Python
object creation and garbage collection. Using this mode with 8 threads on
my 4+4 core i7-6700K, level 1 compresses at ~525 MB/s, -1 at ~1,070 MB/s,
and -5 at ~1,930 MB/s. On the decompression side, level 1 is ~1,320 MB/s,
-1 at ~3,800 MB/s, and -5 at ~4,430 MB/s.</p>
<p>So, my consumer grade desktop i7-6700K is capable of emitting decompressed
data at over 4 GB/s with Python. That's pretty good if you ask me. (Full
disclosure: the timings were taken just around the compression operation
itself: overhead of loading data into memory was not taken into account. See
the <code>bench.py</code> script in the
<a href="https://github.com/indygreg/python-zstandard">source repository</a> for more.</p>
<h2>Long Distance Matching Mode</h2>
<p>Negative compression levels take zstandard into performance territory that
has historically been reserved for compression formats like lz4 that are
optimized for that domain. <em>Long distance matching</em> takes zstandard in the
other direction, towards compression formats that aim to achieve optimal
compression ratios at the expense of time and memory usage.</p>
<p>python-zstandard 0.9 supports long distance matching and all the configurable
parameters exposed by the zstandard API.</p>
<p>I'm not going to capture many performance numbers here because python-zstandard
performs about the same as the C implementation because <em>LDM</em> mode spends
most of its time in zstandard C code. If you are interested in numbers, I
recommend reading the zstandard
<a href="https://github.com/facebook/zstd/releases/tag/v1.3.2">1.3.2</a>
and <a href="https://github.com/facebook/zstd/releases/tag/v1.3.4">1.3.4</a> release notes.</p>
<p>I will, however, underscore that zstandard can achieve close to lzma's
compression ratios (what the <code>xz</code> utility uses) while completely smoking
lzma on decompression speed. For a bundle of the Firefox Mercurial repository,
zstandard level 19 with a long distance window size of 512 MB using 8 threads
compresses to 1,033,633,309 bytes (16.0%) in ~260s wall, 1,730s CPU.
<code>xz -T8 -8</code> compresses to 1,009,233,160 (15.6%) in ~367s wall, ~2,790s CPU.</p>
<p>On the decompression side, zstandard takes ~4.8s and runs at ~1,350 MB/s as
measured on the output side while <code>xz</code> takes ~54s and runs at ~114 MB/s.
Zstandard, however, does use a lot more memory than <code>xz</code> for decompression,
so that performance comes with a cost (512 MB versus 32 MB for this
configuration).</p>
<h2>Other Notable Changes</h2>
<p>python-zstandard now uses the <em>advanced</em> compression and decompression APIs
everywhere. All tunable compression and decompression parameters are available
to python-zstandard. This includes support for disabling magic headers in frames
(saves 4 bytes per frame - this can matter for very small inputs, especially when
using dictionary compression).</p>
<p>The full dictionary training API is exposed. Dictionary training can now use
multiple threads.</p>
<p>There are a handful of utility functions for inspecting zstandard frames,
querying the state of compressors, etc.</p>
<p>Lots of work has gone into shoring up the code base. We now build with warnings
as errors in CI. I performed a number of focused auditing passes to fix
various classes of deficiencies in the C code. This includes use of the
<em>buffer protocol</em>: python-zstandard is now able to accept <em>any</em> Python
object that provides a view into its underlying raw data.</p>
<p>Decompression contexts can now be constructed with a max memory threshold
so attempts to decompress something that would require more memory will
result in error.</p>
<p>See the
<a href="https://github.com/indygreg/python-zstandard/releases/tag/0.9.0">full release notes</a>
for more.</p>
<h2>Conclusion</h2>
<p>Since I last released a major version of python-zstandard, a lot has changed in
the zstandard world. As I
<a href="/blog/2017/03/07/better-compression-with-zstandard/">blogged last year</a>,
zstandard circa early 2017 was a very compelling compression format: it already
outperformed popular compression formats like zlib and bzip2 across the board.
As a <em>general purpose</em> compression format, it made a compelling case for itself.
In my mind, <em>brotli</em> was its only real challenger.</p>
<p>As I wrote then, zstandard isn't perfect. (Nothing is.) But a year later, it
is refreshing to see advancements.</p>
<p>A criticism one year ago was zstandard was pretty good as a general purpose
compression format but it wasn't great if you live at the fringes. If you were
a speed freak, you'd probably use lz4. If you cared about compression ratios,
you'd probably use lzma. But recent releases of zstandard have made huge strides
into the territory of these niche formats. Negative compression levels allow
zstandard to flirt with lz4's performance. Long distance matching allows
zstandard to achieve close to lzma's compression ratios. <strong>This is a big friggin
deal because it makes it much, much harder to justify a domain-specific compression
format over zstandard.</strong> I think lzma still has a significant edge for ultra
compression ratios when memory utilization is a concern. But for many consumers,
memory is readily available and it is easy to justify trading potentially hundreds
of megabytes of memory to achieve a 10x speedup for decompression. Even if you
aren't willing to sacrifice more memory, the ability to tweak compression
parameters is huge. You can do things like store multiple versions of a
compressed document and conditionally serve the one most appropriate for the
client, all while running the same zstandard-only code on the client. That's
huge.</p>
<p>A year later, zstandard continues to impress me for its set of features and its
versatility. The library is continuing to evolve - all while maintaining
backwards compatibility on the decoding side. (That's a sign of a good
format design if you ask me.) I was honestly shocked to see that zstandard
was able to change its compression settings in a way that allowed it to compete
with lz4 and lzma without requiring a format change.</p>
<p>The more I use zstandard, the more I think that <em>everyone should use this</em> and
that popular compression formats just aren't cut out for modern computing any
more. Every time I download a zlib/gz or bzip2 compressed archive, I'm thinking
<em>if only they used zstandard this archive would be smaller, it would have
decompressed already, and I wouldn't be thinking about how annoying it is
to wait for compression operations to complete</em>. In my mind, zstandard is such
an obvious advancement over the status quo and is such a versatile format -
now covering the gamut of super fast compression to ultra ratios - that it is
bordering on negligent to not use zstandard. With the removal of the controversial
patent rights grant license clause in zstandard 1.3.1, that justifiable
resistance to widespread adoption of zstandard has been eliminated. Zstandard
is objectively superior for many workloads and I heavily encourage its use. I
believe python-zstandard provides a high-quality interface to zstandard and
I encourage you to give it and zstandard a try the next time you compress data.</p>
<p>If you run into any problems or want to get involved with development,
python-zstandard lives at
<a href="https://github.com/indygreg/python-zstandard">indygreg/python-zstandard</a> on
GitHub.</p>
<p>*(I updated the post on 2018-05-16 to remove a paragraph about zstandard
competition. In the original post, I unfairly compared zstandard to Snappy
instead of Brotli and made some inaccurate statements around that comparison.)</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <author>
      <name>Gregory Szorc</name>
      <uri>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog</uri>
    </author>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[from __past__ import bytes_literals]]></title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2017/03/13/from-__past__-import-bytes_literals" />
    <id>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2017/03/13/from-__past__-import-bytes_literals</id>
    <updated>2017-03-13T09:55:00Z</updated>
    <published>2017-03-13T09:55:00Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Python" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Mercurial" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Mozilla" />
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[from __past__ import bytes_literals]]></summary>
    <content type="html" xml:base="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2017/03/13/from-__past__-import-bytes_literals"><![CDATA[<p>Last year, I simultaneously committed one of the ugliest and
impressive hacks of my programming <em>career</em>. I haven't had time
to write about it. Until now.</p>
<p>In summary, the hack is a
<a href="https://www.mercurial-scm.org/repo/hg/rev/1c22400db72d">source-transforming module loader</a>
for Python. It can be used by Python 3 to import a Python 2 source
file while translating certain primitives to their Python 3 equivalents.
It is kind of like <a href="https://docs.python.org/3.6/library/2to3.html">2to3</a>
except it executes at run-time during <code>import</code>. The main goal of the
hack was to facilitate porting Mercurial to Python 3 while deferring
having to make the most invasive - and therefore most annoying -
elements of the port in the canonical source code representation.</p>
<p>For the technically curious, it works as follows.</p>
<p>The <code>hg</code> Python executable registers a custom
<a href="https://docs.python.org/3.6/library/sys.html#sys.meta_path">meta path finder</a>
instance. This entity is invoked during <code>import</code> statements to try
to find the module being imported. It tells a later phase of the
import mechanism how to <em>load</em> that module from wherever it is
(usually a <code>.py</code> or <code>.pyc</code> file on disk) to a Python module object.
The custom finder only responds to requests for modules known
to be managed by the Mercurial project. For these modules, it tells
the next stage of the import mechanism to invoke a custom
<a href="https://docs.python.org/3.6/library/importlib.html#importlib.abc.SourceLoader">SourceLoader</a>
instance. Here's where the real magic is: when the custom <em>loader</em>
is invoked, it tokenizes the Python source code using the
<a href="https://docs.python.org/3.6/library/tokenize.html">tokenize</a> module,
iterates over the token stream, finds specific patterns, and
rewrites them to something <em>more appropriate</em>. It then <em>untokenizes</em>
back to Python source code then falls back to the built-in loader
which does the heavy lifting of compiling the source to Python code
objects. So, we have Python 2 source files on disk that magically get
transformed to be Python compatible when they are loaded by Python 3.
Oh, and there is no performance penalty for the token transformation
on subsequence loads because the transformed bytecode is cached in
the <code>.pyc</code> file (using a custom header so we know it was transformed
and can be invalidated when the transformation logic changes).</p>
<p>At the time I wrote it, the token stream manipulation converted most
string literals (<code>''</code>) to bytes literals (<code>b''</code>). In other words, it
restored the Python 2 behavior of string literals being <code>bytes</code> and
not <code>unicode</code>. We jokingly call it
<code>from __past__ import bytes_literals</code> (a play on Python 2's
<code>from __future__ import unicode_literals</code> special syntax which
changes string literals from Python 2's <code>str</code>/<code>bytes</code> type to
<code>unicode</code> to match Python 3's behavior).</p>
<p>Since I implemented the first version, others have implemented:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.mercurial-scm.org/repo/hg/rev/178c89e8519a">Automatically inserting</a>
  a <code>from mercurial.pycompat import ...</code> statement to the top of the
  source. This statement is the Mercurial equivalent of importing
  common wrapper types similar to what
  <a href="https://pythonhosted.org/six/">six</a> provides.</li>
<li>More robust
  <a href="https://www.mercurial-scm.org/repo/hg/rev/423377290a3a">function argument parsing support</a>.
  (Because going from a token stream to a higher-level primitive like a
  function call is difficult.)</li>
<li><a href="https://www.mercurial-scm.org/repo/hg/rev/eaaedad68011">Automatically rewriting</a>
  <code>.iteritems()</code> to <code>.items()</code>.</li>
</ul>
<p>As one can expect, when I tweeted a link to this commit, many Python
developers (including a few CPython core developers) expressed a mix
of intrigue and horror. But mostly horror.</p>
<p>I fully concede that what I did here is a gross hack. And, it is the
intention of the Mercurial project to undo this hack and perform a
proper port once Python 3 support in Mercurial is more mature. But, I
want to lay out my defense on why I did this and why the Mercurial
project is tolerant of this ugly hack.</p>
<p>Individuals within the Mercurial project have wanted to port to Python
3 for years. Until recently, it hasn't been a project priority
because a port was too much work for too little end-user gain. And, on
the technical front, a port was just not practical until Python 3.5.
(Two main blockers were no <code>u''</code> literals - restored in Python 3.3 -
and no <code>%</code> formatting for <code>b''</code> literals - restored in 3.5. And as I
understand it, senior members of the Mercurial project had to lobby
Python maintainers pretty hard to get features like <code>%</code> formatting of
<code>b''</code> literals restored to Python 3.)</p>
<p>Anyway, after a number of failed attempts to initiate the Python 3
port over the years, the Mercurial project started making some
positive steps towards Python 3 compatibility, such as switching
to <a href="https://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-0328/">absolute imports</a> and
addressing syntax issues that allowed modules to be parsed into
an AST and even compiled and loadable. These may seem like small
steps, but for a larger project, it was a lot of work.</p>
<p>The porting effort hit a large wall when it came time to actually
make the AST-valid Python code run on Python 3. Specifically, we had
a strings problem.</p>
<p>When you write software that exchanges data between machines -
sometimes machines running different operating systems or having
different encodings - and there is an expectation that things work
the same and data roundtrips accordingly, trying to force text
encodings is essentially impossible and inevitably breaks something or
someone. It is much easier for Mercurial to operate <em>bytes first</em> and
only take text encoding into consideration when absolutely necessary
(such as when emitting bytes to the terminal in the wanted encoding
or when emitting JSON). That's not to say Mercurial ignores the
existence of encodings. Far from it: Mercurial does attempt to
normalize some data to Unicode. But it often does so with a special
Python type that internally stores the raw byte sequence of the
source so that a consumer can choose to operate at the bytes or
Unicode level. </p>
<p>Anyway, this means that practically every string variable in Mercurial
is a <code>bytes</code> type (or something that acts like a <code>bytes</code> type). And
since string literals in Python 3 are the <code>str</code> type (which represents
Unicode), that would mean having to prefix almost every <code>''</code> string
literal in Mercurial with <code>b''</code> in order to placate Python 3. Having
to update every occurrence of simple primitives that could be statically
transformed automatically felt like busy work. <strong>We wanted to spend time
on the meaningful parts of the Python 3 port so we could find
interesting problems and challenges, not toil with mechanical
conversions that add little to no short-term value while simultaneously
increasing cognitive dissonance and quite possibly increasing the odds
of introducing a bug in Python 2.</strong> In other words, why should humans
do the work that machines can do for us? Thus, the source-transforming
module importer was born.</p>
<p>While I concede what Mercurial did is a giant hack, I maintain it was
the correct thing to do. It has allowed the Python 3 port to move
forward without being blocked on the more tedious and invasive
transformations that could introduce subtle bugs (including performance
regressions) in Python 2. Perfect is the enemy of good. People time is
valuable. The source-transforming module importer allowed us to unblock
an important project without sinking a lot of people time into it. I'd
make that trade-off again.</p>
<p>While I won't encourage others to take this approach to porting to
Python 3, if you want to, Mercurial's source is available under a GPL
license and the custom module importer could be adapted to any project
with minimal modifications. If someone does extract it as reusable code,
please leave a comment and I'll update the post to link to it.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <author>
      <name>Gregory Szorc</name>
      <uri>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog</uri>
    </author>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Better Compression with Zstandard]]></title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2017/03/07/better-compression-with-zstandard" />
    <id>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2017/03/07/better-compression-with-zstandard</id>
    <updated>2017-03-08T10:08:00Z</updated>
    <published>2017-03-07T09:55:00Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Python" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Mercurial" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Mozilla" />
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Better Compression with Zstandard]]></summary>
    <content type="html" xml:base="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2017/03/07/better-compression-with-zstandard"><![CDATA[<p>I think I first heard about the <a href="http://facebook.github.io/zstd/">Zstandard</a>
compression algorithm at a Mercurial developer sprint in 2015.
At one end of a large table a few people were uttering expletives out
of sheer excitement. At developer gatherings, that's the universal signal
for <em>something is awesome</em>. Long story short, a Facebook engineer shared
a link to the
<a href="http://fastcompression.blogspot.com/">RealTime Data Compression blog</a>
operated by Yann Collet (then known as the author of LZ4 - a compression
algorithm known for its insane speeds) and people were completely
nerding out over the excellent articles and the data within showing the
beginnings of a new general purpose lossless compression algorithm named
Zstandard. It promised better-than-deflate/zlib compression ratios <strong>and</strong>
performance on both compression and decompression. This being a Mercurial
meeting, many of us were intrigued because zlib is used by Mercurial
for various functionality (including on-disk storage and compression over
the wire protocol) and zlib operations frequently appear as performance hot
spots.</p>
<p>Before I continue, if you are interested in low-level performance and
software optimization, I highly recommend perusing the
<a href="http://fastcompression.blogspot.com/">RealTime Data Compression blog</a>.
There are some absolute nuggets of info in there.</p>
<p>Anyway, over the months, the news about Zstandard (zstd) kept getting
better and more promising. As the 1.0 release neared, the Facebook
engineers I interact with (Yann Collet - Zstandard's author - is now
employed by Facebook) were absolutely ecstatic about Zstandard and its
potential. I was toying around with pre-release versions and was
absolutely blown away by the performance and features. I believed
the hype.</p>
<p>Zstandard 1.0 was
<a href="https://code.facebook.com/posts/1658392934479273/smaller-and-faster-data-compression-with-zstandard">released on August 31, 2016</a>.
A few days later, I started the
<a href="https://github.com/indygreg/python-zstandard">python-zstandard</a> project to
provide a fully-featured and Pythonic interface to the underlying zstd C
API while not sacrificing safety or performance. The ulterior motive was
to leverage those bindings in Mercurial so Zstandard could be a first class
citizen in Mercurial, possibly replacing zlib as the default compression
algorithm for all operations.</p>
<p>Fast forward six months and I've achieved many of those goals.
python-zstandard has a nearly complete interface to the zstd C API.
It even exposes some primitives not in the C API, such as batch
compression operations that leverage multiple threads and use minimal
memory allocations to facilitate insanely fast execution. (Expect a
dedicated post on python-zstandard from me soon.)</p>
<p>Mercurial 4.1 ships with the python-zstandard bindings. Two Mercurial
4.1 peers talking to each other will exchange Zstandard compressed
data instead of zlib. For a Firefox repository clone, transfer size is
reduced from ~1184 MB (zlib level 6) to ~1052 MB (zstd level 3) in the
default Mercurial configuration while using ~60% of the CPU that zlib
required on the compressor end. When cloning from hg.mozilla.org, the
pre-generated zstd <em>clone bundle</em> hosted on a CDN using maximum
compression is ~707 MB - ~60% the size of zlib! And, work is ongoing
for Mercurial to support Zstandard for on-disk storage, which should
bring considerable performance wins over zlib for local operations.</p>
<p>I've learned a lot working on python-zstandard and integrating Zstandard
into Mercurial. My primary takeaway is <strong>Zstandard is awesome</strong>.</p>
<p>In this post, I'm going to extol the virtues of Zstandard and provide
reasons why I think you should use it.</p>
<h2>Why Zstandard</h2>
<p>The main objective of lossless compression is to spend one resource
(CPU) so that you may reduce another (I/O). This trade-off is usually
made because data - either at rest in storage or in motion over a
network or even through a machine via software and memory - is a
limiting factor for performance. So if compression is needed for your
use case to mitigate I/O being the limiting resource and you can swap
in a different compression algorithm that magically reduces both CPU
and I/O requirements, that's pretty exciting. At scale, better
and more efficient compression can translate to substantial cost
savings in infrastructure. It can also lead to improved application
performance, translating to better end-user engagement, sales,
productivity, etc. This is why companies like Facebook (Zstandard),
Google (brotli, snappy, zopfli), and
<a href="https://www.crunchbase.com/organization/pied-piper">Pied Piper</a>
(middle-out) invest in compression.</p>
<p>Today, the most widely used compression algorithm in the world is
likely <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DEFLATE">DEFLATE</a>. And, software
most often interacts with DEFLATE via what is likely the most widely
used software library in the world, <a href="http://www.zlib.net/">zlib</a>.</p>
<p>Being at least 27 years old, DEFLATE is getting a bit long in the
tooth. Computers are completely different today than they were in 1990.
The Pentium microprocessor debuted in 1993. If memory serves (pun
intended), it used PC66 DRAM, which had a transfer rate of 533 MB/s.
For comparison, a modern NVMe M.2 SSD (like the Samsung 960 PRO)
can read at 3000+ MB/s and write at 2000+ MB/s. In other words,
persistent storage today is faster than the RAM from the era when
DEFLATE was invented. And of course CPU and network speeds have
increased as well. We also have completely different instruction
sets on CPUs for well-designed algorithms and software to take
advantage of. What I'm trying to say is the market is ripe for
DEFLATE and zlib to be dethroned by algorithms and software that
take into account the realities of modern computers.</p>
<p>(For the remainder of this post I'll use <em>zlib</em> as a stand-in for
<em>DEFLATE</em> because it is simpler.)</p>
<p>Zstandard initially piqued my attention by promising better-than-zlib
compression and performance in both the compression and decompression
directions. That's impressive. But it isn't unique. Brotli achieves
the same, for example. But what kept my attention was Zstandard's rich
feature set, tuning abilities, and therefore versatility.</p>
<p>In the sections below, I'll describe some of the benefits of Zstandard
in more detail.</p>
<p>Before I do, I need to throw in an obligatory disclaimer about data
and numbers that I use. Benchmarking is hard. Benchmarks should not
be trusted. There are so many variables that can influence performance
and benchmarks. (A recent example that surprised me is the
<a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1323106">CPU frequency/power ramping properties of Xeon versus non-Xeon Intel CPUs</a>.
tl;dr a Xeon won't hit max CPU frequency if only a core or two
is busy, meaning that any single or low-threaded benchmark is
likely misleading on Xeons unless you change power settings to
mitigate its conservative power ramping defaults. And if you change
power settings, does that reflect real-life usage?)</p>
<p>Reporting useful and accurate performance numbers for compression is
hard because there are so many variables to care about. For example:</p>
<ul>
<li>Every corpus is different. Text, JSON, C++, photos, numerical data,
  etc all exhibit different properties when fed into compression and
  could cause compression ratios or speeds to vary significantly.</li>
<li>Few large inputs versus many smaller inputs (some algorithms work
  better on large inputs; some libraries have high per-operation
  overhead).</li>
<li>Memory allocation and use strategy. Performance can vary
  significantly depending on how a compression library allocates,
  manages, and uses memory. This can be an implementation specific
  detail as opposed to a core property of the compression algorithm.</li>
</ul>
<p>Since Mercurial is the driver for my work in Zstandard, the data and
numbers I report in this post are mostly Mercurial data. Specifically,
I'll be referring to data in the
<a href="https://hg.mozilla.org/mozilla-unified">mozilla-unified Firefox repository</a>.
This repository contains over 300,000 commits spanning almost 10 years.
The data within is a good mix of text (mostly C++, JavaScript, Python,
HTML, and CSS source code and other free-form text) and binary (like
PNGs). The Mercurial layer adds some binary structures to e.g. represent
metadata for deltas, diffs, and patching. There are two Mercurial-specific
pieces of data I will use. One is a Mercurial <em>bundle</em>. This is essentially
a representation of all data in a repository. It stores a mix of raw,
fulltext data and deltas on that data. For the mozilla-unified repo, an
uncompressed bundle (produced via <code>hg bundle -t none-v2 -a</code>) is ~4457 MB.
The other piece of data is <em>revlog chunks</em>. This is a mix of fulltext
and delta data for a specific item tracked in version control. I
frequently use the <em>changelog</em> corpus, which is the fulltext data
describing changesets or commits to Firefox. The numbers quoted and
used for charts in this post
<a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1PHhGxsQR3zDE-2Eeu5Hn2t-UKw4oGV-7LQTMGEdBh9U/edit?usp=sharing">are available in a Google Sheet</a>.</p>
<p>All performance data was obtained on an i7-6700K running Ubuntu 16.10
(Linux 4.8.0) with a mostly stock config. Benchmarks were performed in
memory to mitigate storage I/O or filesystem interference. Memory used
is DDR4-2133 with a cycle time of 35 clocks.</p>
<p>While I'm pretty positive about Zstandard, it isn't perfect. There are
corpora for which Zstandard performs worse than other algorithms, even
ones I compare it directly to in this post. So, your mileage may vary.
Please enlighten me with your counterexamples by leaving a comment.</p>
<p>With that (rather large) disclaimer out of the way, let's talk about
what makes Zstandard awesome.</p>
<h2>Flexibility for Speed Versus Size Trade-offs</h2>
<p>Compression algorithms typically contain parameters to control how
much work to do. You can choose to spend more CPU to (hopefully)
achieve better compression or you can spend less CPU to sacrifice
compression. (OK, fine, there are other factors like memory usage at
play too. I'm simplifying.) This is commonly exposed to
end-users as a compression <em>level</em>. (In reality there are often
multiple parameters that can be tuned. But I'll just use <em>level</em>
as a stand-in to represent the concept.)</p>
<p>But even with adjustable compression levels, the performance of many
compression algorithms and libraries tend to fall within a relatively
narrow window. In other words, many compression algorithms focus on
niche markets. For example, LZ4 is super fast but doesn't yield great
compression ratios. LZMA yields terrific compression ratios but is
extremely slow.</p>
<p>This can be visualized in the following chart showing results when
compressing a mozilla-unified Mercurial bundle:</p>
<p><img alt="bundle compression with common algorithms" src="/images/compression-bundle-common.png" /></p>
<p>This chart plots the logarithmic compression speed in megabytes per
second against achieved compression ratio. The further right a data
point is, the better the compression and the smaller the output.
The higher up a point is, the faster compression is.</p>
<p>The ideal compression algorithm lives in the top right, which means
it compresses well and is fast. But the powers of mathematics push
compression algorithms away from the top right.</p>
<p>On to the observations.</p>
<p>LZ4 is highly vertical, which means its compression ratios are
limited in variance but it is extremely flexible in speed. So for
this data, you might as well stick to a lower compression level
because higher values don't buy you much.</p>
<p>Bzip2 is the opposite: a horizontal line. That means it is consistently
the same speed while yielding different compression ratios. In other
words, you might as well crank bzip2 up to maximum compression because
it doesn't have a significant adverse impact on speed.</p>
<p>LZMA and zlib are more interesting because they exhibit more variance
in both the compression ratio and speed dimensions. But let's be frank,
they are still pretty narrow. LZMA looks pretty good from a shape
perspective, but its top speed is just too slow - only ~26 MB/s!</p>
<p>This small window of flexibility means that you often have to choose
a compression algorithm based on the speed versus size trade-off you are
willing to make at that time. That choice often gets baked into
software. And as time passes and your software or data gains popularity,
changing the software to swap in or support a new compression algorithm
becomes harder because of the cost and disruption it will cause. That's
technical debt.</p>
<p>What we really want is a single compression algorithm that occupies
lots of <em>space</em> in both dimensions of our chart - a curve that has
high variance in both compression speed and ratio. Such an algorithm
would allow you to make an easy decision choosing a compression
algorithm without locking you into a narrow behavior profile. It would
allow you make a completely different size versus speed trade-off in
the future by only adjusting a config knob or two in your application -
no swapping of compression algorithms needed!</p>
<p>As you can guess, Zstandard fulfills this role. This can clearly be seen
in the following chart (which also adds brotli for comparison).</p>
<p><img alt="bundle compression with modern algorithms" src="/images/compression-bundle-modern.png" /></p>
<p>The advantages of Zstandard (and brotli) are obvious. Zstandard's
compression speeds go from ~338 MB/s at level 1 to ~2.6 MB/s at
level 22 while covering compression ratios from 3.72 to 6.05. On one
end, <strong>zstd level 1 is ~3.4x faster than zlib level 1 while achieving
better compression than zlib level 9!</strong> That fastest speed is only 2x
slower than LZ4 level 1. On the other end of the spectrum, zstd
level 22 runs ~1 MB/s slower than LZMA at level 9 and produces a
file that is only 2.3% larger.</p>
<p>It's worth noting that zstd's C API exposes several knobs for tweaking
the compression algorithm. Each compression level maps to a pre-defined
set of values for these knobs. It is possible to set these values beyond
the ranges exposed by the default compression levels 1 through 22. I've
done some basic experimentation with this and have made compression even
faster (while sacrificing ratio, of course). This covers the gap between
Zstandard and brotli on this end of the tuning curve.</p>
<p>The wide span of compression speeds and ratios is a game changer
for compression. Unless you have special requirements such as
lightning fast operations (which LZ4 can provide) or special
corpora that Zstandard can't handle well, Zstandard is a very safe and
flexible choice for general purpose compression.</p>
<h2>Multi-threaded Compression</h2>
<p>Zstd 1.1.3 contains a multi-threaded compression API that allows a
compression operation to leverage multiple threads. The output from
this API is compatible with the Zstandard frame format and doesn't require
any special handling on the decompression side. <strong>In other words, a
compressor can switch to the multi-threaded API and decompressors won't
care.</strong></p>
<p>This is a big deal for a few reasons. First, today's advancements in
computer processors tend to yield more capacity from more cores not
from faster clocks and better cycle efficiency (although many cases
do benefit greatly from modern instruction sets like AVX and therefore
better cycle efficiency). Second, so many compression libraries are
only single-threaded and require consumers to invent their own framing
formats or storage models to facilitate multi-threading. (See
<a href="http://blosc.org/">Blosc</a> for such a library.) Lack of a
multi-threaded API in the compression library means trusting another
piece of software or writing your own multi-threaded code.</p>
<p>The following chart adds a plot of Zstandard multi-threaded compression
with 4 threads.</p>
<p><img alt="multi-threaded compression" src="/images/compression-bundle-multithreaded.png" /></p>
<p>The existing curve for Zstandard basically shifted straight up. Nice!</p>
<p>The ~338 MB/s speed for single-threaded compression on zstd level 1
increases to ~1,376 MB/s with 4 threads. That's ~4.06x faster. And,
it is ~2.26x faster than the previous fastest entry, LZ4 at level 1!
The output size only increased by ~4 MB or ~0.3% over single-threaded
compression.</p>
<p>The scaling properties for multi-threaded compression on this input
are terrific: all 4 cores are saturated and the output size barely
changed.</p>
<p>Because Zstandard's multi-threaded compression API produces data compatible
with any Zstandard decompressor, it can logically be considered an extension
of <em>compression levels</em>. This means that the already extremely flexible
speed vs ratio curve becomes even wider in the speed axis. Zstandard
was already a justifiable choice with its extreme versatility. But when
you throw in native multi-threaded compression API support, the
flexibility for tuning compression performance is just absurd. With
enough cores, you are likely to run into I/O limits long before you
exhaust the CPU, at which point you can crank up the compression
level and sacrifice as much CPU as you are willing to burn. That's
a good position to be in.</p>
<h2>Decompression Speed</h2>
<p>Compression speed and ratios only tell half the story about a compression
algorithm. Except for archiving scenarios where you write once and
read rarely, you probably care about decompression performance.</p>
<p>Popular compression algorithms like zlib and bzip2 have less than stellar
decompression speeds. On my i7-6700K, zlib decompression can deliver many
decompressed data sets at the output end at 200+ MB/s. However, on the
input/compressed end, it frequently fails to reach 100 MB/s or even
80 MB/s. This is significant because if your application is reading data
over a 1 Gbps network or from a local disk (modern SSDs can read at several
hundred MB/s or more), then your application has a CPU bottleneck at
decoding the data - and that's before you actually do anything useful
with the data in the application layer! (Remember: the idea behind
compression is to spend CPU to mitigate an I/O bottleneck. So if
compression makes you CPU bound, you've undermined the point of
compression!) And if my Skylake CPU running at 4.0 GHz is CPU -
not I/O - bound, A Xeon in a data center will be even slower and
even more CPU bound (Xeons tend to run at much lower clock speeds -
the laws of thermodynamics require that in order to run more cores in
the package). In short, <strong>if you are using zlib for high throughput
scenarios, there's a good chance it is a bottleneck and slowing down
your application</strong>.</p>
<p>We again measure the speed of algorithms using a Firefox Mercurial
bundle. The following charts plot decompression speed versus ratio
for this file. The first chart measures decompression speed on the
input end of the decompressor. The second measures speed at the
output end.</p>
<p><img alt="decompression input" src="/images/decompression-bundle-input.png" /></p>
<p><img alt="decompression output" src="/images/decompression-bundle-output.png" /></p>
<p>Zstandard matches its great compression speed with great decompression
speed. Zstandard can deliver decompressed output at 1000+ MB/s while
consuming input at 200-275MB/s. Furthermore, decompression speed is
mostly independent of the compression level. (Although higher
compression levels require more memory in the decompressor.) So, <strong>if
you want to throw more CPU at re-compression later so data at rest takes
less space, you can do that without sacrificing read performance.</strong>
I haven't done the math, but there is probably a break-even point
where having dedicated machines re-compress terabytes or petabytes
of data at rest offsets the costs of those machine through reduced
storage costs.</p>
<p>While Zstandard is not as fast decompressing as LZ4 (which can consume
compressed input at 500+ MB/s), its performance is often ~4x faster
than zlib. On many CPUs, this puts it well above 1 Gbps, which is
often desirable to avoid a bottleneck at the network layer.</p>
<p>It's also worth noting that while Zstandard and brotli were comparable
on the compression half of this data, Zstandard has a clear advantage
doing decompression.</p>
<p>Finally, you don't appear to pay a price for multi-threaded Zstandard
compression on the decompression side (<code>zstdmt</code> in the chart).</p>
<h2>Dictionary Support</h2>
<p>The examples so far in this post have used a single 4,457 MB piece of
input data to measure behavior. Large data can behave completely
differently from small data. This is because so much of what
compression algorithms do is find patterns that came before so incoming
data can be <em>referenced</em> to old data instead of uniquely stored. And if
data is small, there isn't much of it that came before to reference!</p>
<p>This is often why many small, independent chunks of input compress
poorly compared to a single large chunk. This can be demonstrated by
comparing the widely-used <em>zip</em> and <em>tar</em> archive formats. On the
surface, both do the same thing: they are a container of files. But
they employ compression at different phases. A <em>zip</em> file will zlib
compress each entry independently. However, a <em>tar</em> file doesn't use
compression internally. Instead, the tar file itself is fed into a
compression algorithm and compressed as a whole.</p>
<p>We can observe the difference on real world data. Firefox
ships with a file named <code>omni.ja</code>. Despite the weird extension, this
is a <em>zip</em> file. The file contains most of the assets for non-compiled
code used by Firefox. This includes the JavaScript, HTML, CSS, and
images that power many parts of the Firefox frontend. The file weighs
in at 9,783,749 bytes for the 64-bit Windows Firefox Nightly from
2017-03-06. (Or 9,965,793 bytes when using <code>zip -9</code> - the code for
generating <code>omni.ja</code> is smarter than <code>zip</code> and creates smaller
files.) But a zlib level 9 compressed <code>tar.gz</code> file of that directory
is 8,627,155 bytes. That 1,156KB / 13% size difference is significant
when you are talking about delivering bits to end users! (In this
case, the content within the archive needs to be individually
addressable to facilitate fast access to any item without having
to decompress the entire archive: this matters for performance.)</p>
<p>A more extreme example of the differences between <em>zip</em> and <em>tar</em>
is the files in the Firefox source checkout. On revision
a08ec245fa24 of the Firefox Mercurial repository, a <em>zip</em> file of
all files in version control is 430,446,549 bytes versus
322,916,403 bytes for a <em>tar.gz</em> file (1,177,430,383 bytes uncompressed
spanning 180,912 files). Using Zstandard, compressing each file
discretely at compression level 3 yields 391,387,299 bytes of
compressed data versus 294,926,418 as a single stream (without the
<em>tar</em> container). Same compression algorithm. Different application
method. Drastically different results. That's the impact of input
size on compression performance.</p>
<p>While the compression ratio and speed of a single large stream is
often better than multiple smaller chunks, there are still
use cases that either don't have enough data or prefer independent
access to each piece of input (like Firefox's <code>omni.ja</code> file). So
a robust compression algorithm should handle small inputs as well
as it does large inputs.</p>
<p>Zstandard helps offset the inherent inefficiencies of small inputs
by supporting <em>dictionary compression</em>. A <em>dictionary</em> is
essentially data used to seed the compressor's state. If the
compressor sees data that exists in the dictionary, it references
the dictionary instead of storing new data in the compressed output
stream. This results in smaller output sizes and better compression
ratios. One drawback to this is the dictionary has to be used to
decompress data, which means you need to figure out how to
distribute the dictionary and ensure it remains in sync with all
data producers and consumers. This isn't always trivial.</p>
<p>Dictionary compression only works if there is enough repeated data
and patterns in the inputs that can be extracted to yield a
useful dictionary. Examples of this include markup languages, source
code, or pieces of similar data (such as JSON payloads from HTTP API
requests or telemetry data), which often have many repeated keywords
and patterns.</p>
<p>Dictionaries are typically produced by <em>training</em> them on existing
data. Essentially, you feed a bunch of samples into an algorithm
that spits out a meaningful and useful dictionary. The more coherency
in the data that will be compressed, the better the dictionary and
the better the compression ratios.</p>
<p>Dictionaries can have a significant effect on compression ratios and
speed.</p>
<p>Let's go back to Firefox's <code>omni.ja</code> file. Compressing each file
discretely at zstd level 12 yields 9,177,410 bytes of data. But if
we produce a 131,072 byte dictionary by training it on all files
within <code>omni.ja</code>, the total size of each file compressed discretely
is 7,942,886 bytes. Including the dictionary, the total size is
8,073,958 bytes, 1,103,452 bytes smaller than non-dictionary
compression! (The zlib-based <code>omni.ja</code> is 9,783,749 bytes.) So
Zstandard plus dictionary compression would likely yield a
meaningful ~1.5 MB size reduction to the <code>omni.ja</code> file. This would
make the Firefox distribution smaller and <em>may</em> improve startup
time (since many files inside <code>omni.ja</code> are accessed at
startup), which would make a number of people very happy. (Of
course, Firefox doesn't yet contain the zstd C library. And adding
it just for this use case may not make sense. But Firefox does ship
with the brotli library and brotli supports dictionary compression
and has similar performance characteristics as Zstandard, so, uh,
someone may want to look into transitioning <code>omni.jar</code> to
<em>not zlib</em>.)</p>
<p>But the benefits of dictionary compression don't end at compression
ratios: operations with dictionaries can be faster as well!</p>
<p>The following chart shows performance when compressing Mercurial
<em>changeset</em> data (describes a Mercurial commit) for the Firefox
repository. There are 382,530 discrete inputs spanning 221,429,458
bytes (mean: 579 bytes, median: 306 bytes). (Note: measurements were
conducted in Python and therefore may introduce some overhead.)</p>
<p><img alt="dictionary compression performance" src="/images/decompression-dictionary-changeset.png" /></p>
<p>Aside from zstd level 3 dictionary compression, Zstandard is faster
than zlib level 6 across the board (I suspect this one-off is an
oddity with the zstd compression parameters at this level and this
corpus because zstd level 4 is faster than level 3, which is weird).</p>
<p>It's also worth noting that non-dictionary zstandard compression
has similar compression ratios to zlib. Again, this demonstrates
the intrinsic difficulties of compressing small inputs.</p>
<p>But the real takeaway from this data are the speed differences with
dictionary compression enabled. Dictionary decompression is
2.2-2.4x <em>faster</em> than non-dictionary decompression. Already
respectable ~240 MB/s decompression speed (measured at the output
end) becomes ~530 MB/s. Zlib level 6 was ~140 MB/s, so swapping
in dictionary compression makes things ~3.8x faster. It takes ~1.5s
of CPU time to zlib decompress this corpus. So if Mercurial can
be taught to use Zstandard dictionary compression for changelog data,
certain operations on this corpus will complete ~1.1s faster. That's
significant.</p>
<p>It's worth stating that Zstandard isn't the only compression algorithm
or library to support dictionary compression. Brotli and zlib do as
well, for example. But, Zstandard's support for dictionary compression
seems to be more polished than other libraries I've seen. It has multiple
APIs for training dictionaries from sample data. (Brotli has none nor
does brotli's documentation say how to generate dictionaries as far as
I can tell.)</p>
<p>Dictionary compression is definitely an advanced feature, applicable
only to certain use cases (lots of small, similar data). But there's
no denying that if you can take advantage of dictionary compression,
you may be rewarded with significant performance wins.</p>
<h2>A Versatile C API</h2>
<p>I spend a lot of my time these days in higher-level programming
languages like Python and JavaScript. By the time you interact with
compression in high-level languages, the low-level compression APIs
provided by the compression library are most likely hidden from you
and bundled in a nice, friendly abstraction, suitable for a
higher-level language. And more often than not, many features of
that low-level API are not exposed for you to call. So, you don't
get an appreciation for how good (or bad) or feature rich (or
lacking) the low-level API is.</p>
<p>As part of writing
<a href="https://github.com/indygreg/python-zstandard">python-zstandard</a>, I've
spent a lot of time interfacing with the zstd C API. And, as part
of evaluating other compression libraries for use in Mercurial, I've
been looking at C APIs for other libraries and the Python bindings to
them. A takeaway from this is an appreciation for the quality of
zstd's C API.</p>
<p>Many compression library APIs are either too simple or too complex.
Zstandard's is in the Goldilocks zone. Aside from a few minor missing
features, its C API was more than adequate in its 1.0 release.</p>
<p>What I really appreciate about the zstd C API is that it provides
high, medium, and low-level APIs. From the highest level, you throw
it pointers to input and output buffers and it does an operation.
From the medium level, you use a reusable <em>context</em> holding state
and other parameters and it does an operation. From the low-level,
you are calling multiple functions and shuffling bytes around,
maintaining your own state and potentially bypassing the Zstandard
<em>framing</em> format in the process. The different levels give you
almost total control over everything. This is critical for performance
optimization and when writing bindings for higher-level languages that
may have different expectations on the behavior of software. The
performance I've achieved in python-zstandard just isn't (easily)
possible with other compression libraries because of their lacking
API design.</p>
<p>Oftentimes when interacting with a C library I think <em>if only there
were a function to let me do X my life would be much easier</em>. I
rarely have this experience with Zstandard. The C API is well thought out,
has almost all the features I want/need, and is pretty easy to use.
While most won't notice this difference, it should be a significant
advantage for Zstandard in the long run, as more bindings are
written and more people have a high-quality experience with it
because the C API allows them to.</p>
<h2>Zstandard Isn't Perfect</h2>
<p>I've been pretty positive about Zstandard so far in this post.
In fear of sounding like a fanboy who is so blinded by admiration
that he can't see faults and because nothing is perfect, I need to
point out some negatives about Zstandard. (Aside: put little faith
in the words uttered by someone who can't find a fault in something
they praise.)</p>
<p>First, the <a href="https://github.com/facebook/zstd/blob/3bee41a70eaf343fbcae3637b3f6edbe52f35ed8/doc/zstd_compression_format.md#zstandard-frames">framing format</a>
is a bit heavyweight in some scenarios. The frame header is at <em>least</em>
6 bytes. For input of 256-65791 bytes, recording the original source
size and its checksum will result in a 12 byte frame. Zlib, by contrast,
is only 6 bytes for this scenario. When storing tens of thousands of
compressed records (this is a use case in Mercurial), the frame overhead
can matter and this can make it difficult for compressed Zstandard
data to be as small as zlib for very small inputs. (It's worth noting
that zlib doesn't store the decompressed size in its header. There are
pros and cons to this, which I'll discuss in my eventual post about
python-zstandard and how it achieves optimal performance.) If the frame
overhead matters to you, the zstd C API does expose a <em>block</em> API that
operates at a level below the framing format, allowing you to roll your
own framing protocol. I also
<a href="https://github.com/facebook/zstd/issues/591">filed a GitHub issue</a> to
make the 4 byte magic number optional, which would go a long way to
cutting down on frame overhead.</p>
<p>Second, the C API is not yet fully stabilized. There are a number of
functions marked as <em>experimental</em> that aren't exported from the shared
library and are only available via static linking. There's a ton of
useful functionality in there, including low-level compression parameter
adjustment, digested dictionaries (for reusing computed dictionaries
across multiple <em>contexts</em>), and the multi-threaded compression API.
python-zstandard makes heavy use of these <em>experimental</em> APIs. This
requires bundling zstd with python-zstandard and statically linking
with this known version because functionality could change at any time.
This is a bit annoying, especially for distro packagers.</p>
<p>Third, the low-level compression parameters are under-documented. I
think I understand what a lot of them do. But it isn't obvious when
I should consider adjusting what. The default compression levels
seem to work pretty well and map to reasonable compression parameters.
But a few times I've noticed that tweaking things slightly can result
in desirable improvements. I wish there were a guide of sorts to
help you tune these parameters.</p>
<p>Fourth, dictionary compression is still a bit too complicated and
hand-wavy for my liking. I can measure obvious benefits when using it
largely out of the box with some corpora. But it isn't always a win
and the cost for training dictionaries is too high to justify using
it outside of scenarios where you are pretty sure it will be beneficial.
When I do use it, I'm not sure which compression levels it works best
with, how many samples need to be fed into the dictionary trainer,
which training algorithm to use, etc. If that isn't enough, there is
also the concept of <em>content-only dictionaries</em> where you use a
fulltext as the dictionary. This can be useful for delta-encoding
schemes (where compression effectively acts like a diff/delta
generator instead of using something like Myers diff). If this topic
interests you, there is a
<a href="https://www.mercurial-scm.org/pipermail/mercurial-devel/2017-January/092186.html">thread on the Mercurial developers list</a>
where Yann Collet and I discuss this.</p>
<p>Fifth, the patent rights grant. There is some
<a href="https://github.com/facebook/zstd/blob/4ded9e591cbed57c54fc8f7a50412af5980e23a7/PATENTS#L14">wording in the PATENTS file</a>
in the Zstandard project that may... concern lawyers. While Zstandard
is covered by the standard BSD 3-Clause license, that supplemental
<code>PATENTS</code> file may scare some lawyers enough that you won't be able
to use Zstandard. You may want to talk to a lawyer before using
Zstandard, especially if you or your company likes initiating patent
lawsuits against companies (or wishes to reserve that right - as many
companies do), as that is the condition upon which the license
terminates. Note that there is a long history between Facebook and
consumers of its open source software regarding this language in the
<code>PATENTS</code> file. Do a search for <code>React patent grant</code> to read more.</p>
<p>Sixth and finally, Zstandard is still relatively new. I can totally
relate to holding off until something new and shiny proves itself.
That being said, the Zstandard framing protocol has some escape
hatches for future needs. And, the project proved during its pre-1.0
days that it knows how to handle backwards and future compatibility
issues. And considering Facebook and others are using Zstandard in
production, I wouldn't be too worried. I think the biggest risk is
to people (like me) who are writing code against the <em>experimental</em>
C APIs. But even then, the changes to the experimental APIs in the
past several months have been minor. I'm not losing sleep over it.</p>
<p>That may seem like a long and concerning list. Most of the issues are
relatively minor. The language in the <code>PATENTS</code> file may be a
showstopper to some. From my perspective, the biggest thing Zstandard has
going against it is its youth. But that will only improve with age.
While I'm usually pretty conservative about adopting new technology
(I've gotten burned enough times that I prefer the neophytes do the
field testing for me), the upside to using Zstandard is potentially
drastic performance and efficiency gains. And that can translate to
success versus failure or millions of dollars in saved infrastructure
costs and productivity gains. I'm willing to take my chances.</p>
<h2>Conclusion</h2>
<p>For the corpora I've thrown at it, Zstandard handily outperforms zlib
in almost every dimension. And, it even manages to best other <em>modern</em>
compression algorithms like brotli in many tests.</p>
<p>The underlying algorithm and techniques used by Zstandard are highly
parameterized, lending themselves to a variety of use cases from embedded
hardware to massive data crunching machines with hundreds of gigabytes
of memory and dozens of CPU cores.</p>
<p>The C API is well-designed and facilitates high performance and
adaptability to numerous use cases. It is <em>batteries included</em>,
providing functions to train dictionaries and perform multi-threaded
compression.</p>
<p>Zstandard is backed by Facebook and seems to have a healthy open source
culture <a href="https://github.com/facebook/zstd">on Github</a>. My interactions
with Yann Collet have been positive and he seems to be a great
project maintainer.</p>
<p>Zstandard is an exciting advancement for data compression and therefore
for the entire computing field. As someone who has lived in the world
of zlib for years, was a casual user of compression, and thought zlib
was <em>good enough</em> for most use cases, I can attest that Zstandard is
game changing. After being enlightened to all the advantages of
Zstandard, I'll never casually use zlib again: it's just too slow and
inflexible for the needs of modern computing. If you use compression,
I highly recommend investigating Zstandard.</p>
<p><em>(I updated the post on 2017-03-08 to include a paragraph about the
supplemental license in the <code>PATENTS</code> file.)</em></p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <author>
      <name>Gregory Szorc</name>
      <uri>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog</uri>
    </author>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Automatic Python Static Analysis on MozReview]]></title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2015/01/24/automatic-python-static-analysis-on-mozreview" />
    <id>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2015/01/24/automatic-python-static-analysis-on-mozreview</id>
    <updated>2015-01-24T23:30:00Z</updated>
    <published>2015-01-24T23:30:00Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Python" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="MozReview" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Mozilla" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="code review" />
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Automatic Python Static Analysis on MozReview]]></summary>
    <content type="html" xml:base="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2015/01/24/automatic-python-static-analysis-on-mozreview"><![CDATA[<p>A bunch of us were in Toronto last week hacking on MozReview.</p>
<p>One of the cool things we did was deploy a bot for performing Python
static analysis. If you submit some .py files to MozReview, the bot
should leave a review. If it finds violations (it uses
<a href="https://flake8.readthedocs.org/">flake8</a> internally), it will open
an issue for each violation. It also leaves a comment that should
hopefully give enough detail on how to fix the problem.</p>
<p>While we haven't done much in the way of performance optimizations,
the bot typically submits results less than 10 seconds after the review
is posted! So, a human should never be reviewing Python that the bot
hasn't seen. This means you can stop thinking about style nits and start
thinking about what the code does.</p>
<p>This bot should be considered an alpha feature. The code for the bot
isn't even checked in yet. We're running the bot against production
to get a feel for how it behaves. If things don't go well, we'll turn
it off until the problems are fixed.</p>
<p>We'd like to eventually deploy C++, JavaScript, etc bots. Python won out
because it was the easiest to integrate (it has sane and efficient
tooling that is compatible with Mozilla's code bases - most existing
JavaScript tools won't work with Gecko-flavored JavaScript, sadly).</p>
<p>I'd also like to eventually make it easier to locally run the same
static analysis we run in MozReview. Addressing problems locally before
pushing is a no-brainer since it avoids needless context switching from
other people and is thus better for productivity. This will come in
time.</p>
<p>Report issues in #mozreview or in the Developer Services :: MozReview
Bugzilla component.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <author>
      <name>Gregory Szorc</name>
      <uri>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog</uri>
    </author>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Python Packaging Do's and Don'ts]]></title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2014/07/15/python-packaging-do's-and-don'ts" />
    <id>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2014/07/15/python-packaging-do's-and-don'ts</id>
    <updated>2014-07-15T17:20:00Z</updated>
    <published>2014-07-15T17:20:00Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Python" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Mozilla" />
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Python Packaging Do's and Don'ts]]></summary>
    <content type="html" xml:base="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2014/07/15/python-packaging-do's-and-don'ts"><![CDATA[<p>Are you someone who casually interacts with Python but don't know the
inner workings of Python? Then this post is for you. Read on to learn
why some things are the way they are and how to avoid making some
common mistakes.</p>
<h2>Always use Virtualenvs</h2>
<p>It is an easy trap to view <a href="https://virtualenv.pypa.io/en/latest/virtualenv.html">virtualenvs</a>
as an obstacle, a distraction towards accomplishing something. People
see me adding virtualenvs to build instructions and they say <em>I don't
use virtualenvs, they aren't necessary, why are you doing that?</em></p>
<p>A virtualenv is effectively an overlay on top of your system Python
install. Creating a virtualenv can be thought of as copying your system
Python environment into a local location. When you modify virtualenvs,
you are modifying an isolated container. Modifying virtualenvs has no
impact on your system Python.</p>
<p>A goal of a virtualenv is to isolate your system/global Python install
from unwanted changes. When you accidentally make a change to a
virtualenv, you can just delete the virtualenv and start over from
scratch. When you accidentally make a change to your system Python, it
can be much, much harder to recover from that.</p>
<p>Another goal of virtualenvs is to allow different versions of packages
to exist. Say you are working on two different projects and each
requires a specific version of Django. With virtualenvs, you install one
version in one virtualenv and a different version in another virtualenv.
Things happily coexist because the virtualenvs are independent.
Contrast with trying to manage both versions of Django in your system
Python installation. Trust me, it's not fun.</p>
<p>Casual Python users may not encounter scenarios where virtualenvs make
their lives better... until they do, at which point they realize their
system Python install is beyond saving. People who eat, breath, and die
Python run into these scenarios all the time. We've learned how bad life
without virtualenvs can be and so we use them everywhere.</p>
<p>Use of virtualenvs is a best practice. Not using virtualenvs will result
in something unexpected happening. It's only a matter of time.</p>
<p>Please use virtualenvs.</p>
<h2>Never use sudo</h2>
<p>Do you use sudo to install a Python package? You are doing it wrong.</p>
<p>If you need to use sudo to install a Python package, that almost
certainly means you are installing a Python package to your
system/global Python install. And this means you are modifying your
system Python instead of isolating it and keeping it pristine.</p>
<p>Instead of using sudo to install packages, create a virtualenv and
install things into the virtualenv. There should never be permissions
issues with virtualenvs - the user that creates a virtualenv has full
realm over it.</p>
<h2>Never modify the system Python environment</h2>
<p>On some systems, such as OS X with Homebrew, you don't need sudo to
install Python packages because the user has write access to the Python
directory (<em>/usr/local</em> in Homebrew).</p>
<p>For the reasons given above, don't muck around with the system Python
environment. Instead, use a virtualenv.</p>
<h2>Beware of the package manager</h2>
<p>Your system's package manager (apt, yum, etc) is likely using root and/or
installing Python packages into the system Python.</p>
<p>For the reasons given above, this is bad. Try to use a virtualenv, if
possible. Try to not use the system package manager for installing
Python packages.</p>
<h2>Use pip for installing packages</h2>
<p>Python packaging has historically been a mess. There are a handful of
tools and APIs for installing Python packages. As a casual Python user,
you only need to know of one of them:
<a href="https://pip.pypa.io/en/latest/">pip</a>.</p>
<p>If someone says <em>install a package</em>, you should be thinking <em>create a
virtualenv, activate a virtualenv, <code>pip install &lt;package&gt;</code></em>. <strong>You
should never run <code>pip install</code> outside of a virtualenv.</strong> (The exception
is to install virtualenv and pip itself, which you almost certainly want
in your system/global Python.)</p>
<p>Running <em>pip install <package></em> will install packages from
<a href="https://pypi.python.org/pypi">PyPI</a>, the Python Packaging Index by
default. It's Python's official package repository.</p>
<p>There are a lot of old and outdated tutorials online about Python
packaging. Beware of bad content. For example, if you see documentation
that says <em>use easy_install</em>, you should be thinking, <em>easy_install is
a legacy package installer that has largely been replaced by pip, I
should use pip instead</em>. When in doubt, consult the
<a href="https://python-packaging-user-guide.readthedocs.org/en/latest/index.html">Python packaging user guide</a>
and do what it recommends.</p>
<h2>Don't trust the Python in your package manager</h2>
<p>The more Python programming you do, the more you learn to not trust the
Python package provided by your system / package manager.</p>
<p>Linux distributions such as Ubuntu that sit on the forward edge of
versions are better than others. But I've run into enough problems with
the OS or package manager maintained Python (especially on OS X), that
I've learned to distrust them.</p>
<p>I use <a href="https://github.com/yyuu/pyenv">pyenv</a> for installing and managing
Python distributions from source. pyenv also installs virtualenv and
pip for me, packages that I believe should be in all Python installs
by default. As a more experienced Python programmer, I find pyenv 
<em>just works</em>.</p>
<p>If you are just a beginner with Python, it is probably safe to ignore
this section. Just know that as soon as something weird happens, start
suspecting your default Python install, especially if you are on OS X.
If you suspect trouble, use something like pyenv to enforce a buffer so
the system can have its Python and you can have yours.</p>
<h2>Recovering from the past</h2>
<p>Now that you know the preferred way to interact with Python, you are
probably thinking <em>oh crap, I've been wrong all these years - how do I
fix it?</em></p>
<p>The goal is to get a Python install <em>somewhere</em> that is as pristine as
possible. You have two approaches here: cleaning your existing Python or
creating a new Python install.</p>
<p>To clean your existing Python, you'll want to purge it of pretty much
all packages not installed by the core Python distribution. The
exception is virtualenv, pip, and setuptools - you almost certainly want
those installed globally. On Homebrew, you can uninstall everything related to
Python and blow away your Python directory, typically
/usr/local/lib/python*. Then, <em>brew install python</em>. On Linux distros,
this is a bit harder, especially since most Linux distros rely on Python
for OS features and thus they may have installed extra packages. You
could try a similar approach on Linux, but I don't think it's worth it.</p>
<p>Cleaning your system Python and attempting to keep it pure are ongoing
tasks that are very difficult to keep up with. All it takes is one
dependency to get pulled in that trashes your system Python. Therefore,
I shy away from this approach.</p>
<p>Instead, I install and run Python from my user directory. I use
<a href="https://github.com/yyuu/pyenv">pyenv</a>. I've also heard great things
about <a href="http://conda.pydata.org/miniconda.html">Miniconda</a>. With either
solution, you get a Python in your home directory that starts clean and
pure. Even better, it is completely independent from your system Python.
So if your package manager does something funky, there is a buffer. And,
if things go wrong with your userland Python install, you can always
nuke it without fear of breaking something in system land. This seems to
be the best of both worlds.</p>
<p>Please note that installing packages in the system Python shouldn't be
evil. When you create virtualenvs, you can - and should - tell
virtualenv to not use the system site-packages (i.e. <em>don't use
non-core packages from the system installation</em>). This is the default
behavior in virtualenv. It should provide an adequate buffer. But from
my experience, things still manage to bleed through. My userland Python
install is extra safety. If something wrong happens, I can only blame
myself.</p>
<h2>Conclusion</h2>
<p>Python's long and complicated history of package management makes it
very easy for you to shoot yourself in the foot. The long list of
outdated tutorials on The Internet make this a near certainty for casual
Python users. Using the guidelines in this post, you can adhere to best
practices that will cut down on surprises and rage and keep your Python
running smoothly.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <author>
      <name>Gregory Szorc</name>
      <uri>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog</uri>
    </author>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Aggregating Version Control Info at Mozilla]]></title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2014/01/21/aggregating-version-control-info-at-mozilla" />
    <id>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2014/01/21/aggregating-version-control-info-at-mozilla</id>
    <updated>2014-01-21T10:50:00Z</updated>
    <published>2014-01-21T10:50:00Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Git" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Mercurial" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Mozilla" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Python" />
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Aggregating Version Control Info at Mozilla]]></summary>
    <content type="html" xml:base="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2014/01/21/aggregating-version-control-info-at-mozilla"><![CDATA[<p>Over the winter break, I set out on an ambitious project to create
a service to help developers and others manage the flury
of patches going into Firefox. While the project is far from complete,
I'm ready to unleash the first part of the project upon the world.</p>
<p>If you point your browsers to
<a href="http://moztree.gregoryszorc.com/">moztree.gregoryszorc.com</a>, you'll
hopefully see some documentation about what I've built.
<a href="https://bitbucket.org/indygreg/moz-tree-utopia">Source code</a> is
available and free, of course. Patches very welcome.</p>
<p>Essentially, I built a centralized indexing service for version
control repositories with Mozilla's extra metadata thrown in.
I tell it what repositories to mirror, and it clones everything,
fetches data such as the pushlog and Git SHA-1 mappings, and
stores everything in a central database. It then exposes this
aggregated data through world-readable web services.</p>
<p>Currently, I have the service indexing the popular project branches
for Firefox (central, aurora, beta, release, esr, b2g, inbound, fx-team,
try, etc). You can view the
<a href="http://moztree.gregoryszorc.com/api/repos">full list</a> via the web
service. As a bonus, I'm also serving these repositories via
<a href="http://hg.gregoryszorc.com/">hg.gregoryszorc.com</a>. My server appears
to be significantly faster than
<a href="https://hg.mozilla.org">hg.mozilla.org</a>. If you want to use it for
your daily needs, go for it. I make no SLA guarantees, however.</p>
<p>I'm also using this service as an opportunity to experiment with
alternate forms of Mercurial hosting. I have mirrors of mozilla-central
and the try repository with generaldelta and lz4 compression enabled.
I may blog about what those are eventually. The teaser is that they can
make Mercurial perform a lot faster under some conditions. I'm also
using ZFS under the hood to manage repositories. Each repository is a
ZFS filesystem. This means I can create repository copies on the server
(user repositories anyone?) at a nearly free cost. Contrast this to the
traditional method of full clones, which take lots of time, memory, CPU,
and storage.</p>
<p>Anyway, some things you can do with the existing web service:</p>
<ul>
<li>Obtain metadata about Mercurial changesets.
  <a href="http://moztree.gregoryszorc.com/api/changeset/940b2974f35b">Example</a>.</li>
<li>Look up metadata about Git commits.
  <a href="http://moztree.gregoryszorc.com/api/git-sha1/40438af67c321">Example</a>.</li>
<li>Obtain a <a href="http://moztree.gregoryszorc.com/api/spore">SPORE descriptor</a>
  describing the web service endpoints. This allows you to auto-generate
  clients from descriptors. Yay!</li>
</ul>
<p>Obviously, that's not a lot. But adding new endpoints is relatively
straightforward. See the <a href="https://bitbucket.org/indygreg/moz-tree-utopia/src/tip/repodata/web/app.py">source</a>.
It's literally as easy as defining a URL mapping and writing a
database query.</p>
<p>The performance is also not the best. I just haven't put in the effort
to tune things yet. All of the querying hits the database, not
Mercurial. So, making things faster should merely be a matter of
database and hosting optimization. Patches welcome!</p>
<p>Some ideas that I haven't had time to implement yet:</p>
<ul>
<li>Return changests in a specific repository</li>
<li>Return recently pushed changesets</li>
<li>Return pushes for a given user</li>
<li>Return commits for a given author</li>
<li>Return commits referencing a given bug</li>
<li>Obtain TBPL URLs for pushes with changeset</li>
<li>Integrate bugzilla metadata</li>
</ul>
<p>Once those are in place, I foresee this service powering a number of
dashboards. Patches welcome.</p>
<p>Again, this service is only the tip of what's possible. There's a lot
that could be built on this service. I have ideas. Others have ideas.</p>
<p>The project includes a Vagrant file and Puppet
manifests for provisioning the server. It's a one-liner to get a
development environment up and running. It should be really easy to
contribute to this project. Patches welcome.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
</feed>
