<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed
  xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:thr="http://purl.org/syndication/thread/1.0"
  xml:lang="en"
   >
  <title type="text">Gregory Szorc's Digital Home</title>
  <subtitle type="text">Rambling on</subtitle>

  <updated>2015-01-16T18:50:18Z</updated>
  <generator uri="http://blogofile.com/">Blogofile</generator>

  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" />
  <id>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/feed/atom/</id>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/feed/atom/" />
  <entry>
    <author>
      <name>Gregory Szorc</name>
      <uri>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog</uri>
    </author>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Code First and the Rise of the DVCS and GitHub]]></title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2015/01/10/code-first-and-the-rise-of-the-dvcs-and-github" />
    <id>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2015/01/10/code-first-and-the-rise-of-the-dvcs-and-github</id>
    <updated>2015-01-10T12:35:00Z</updated>
    <published>2015-01-10T12:35:00Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Git" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Mozilla" />
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Code First and the Rise of the DVCS and GitHub]]></summary>
    <content type="html" xml:base="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2015/01/10/code-first-and-the-rise-of-the-dvcs-and-github"><![CDATA[<p>The ascendancy of GitHub has very little to do with its namesake tool,
Git.</p>
<p>What GitHub did that was so radical for its time and the strategy that
GitHub continues to execute so well on today is the approach of
putting <em>code first</em> and enabling change to be a frictionless process.</p>
<p>In case you weren't around for the pre-GitHub days or don't remember,
they were not pleasant. Tools around code management were a far cry
from where they are today (I still argue the tools are pretty bad, but
that's for another post). Centralized version control systems were
prevalent (CVS and Subversion in open source, Perforce, ClearCase,
Team Foundation Server, and others in the corporate world). Tools for
looking at and querying code had horrible, ugly interfaces and came out
of a previous era of web design and browser capabilities. It felt like
a chore to do anything, including committing code. Yes, the world
had awesome services like <a href="https://sourceforge.net/">SourceForge</a>,
but they weren't the same as GitHub is today.</p>
<p>Before I get to my central thesis, I want to highlight some supporting
reasons for GitHub's success. There were two developments in the second
half of the 2000s the contributed to the success of GitHub: the rises
of the distributed version control system (DVCS) and the modern web.</p>
<p>While distributed version control systems like Sun WorkShop TeamWare and
BitKeeper existed earlier, it wasn't until the second half of the 2000s
that DVCS systems took off. You can argue part of the reason for this
was open source: my recollection is there wasn't a well-known DVCS
available as free software before 2005. Speaking of 2005, it was a big
year for DVCS projects: Git, Mercurial, and Bazaar all had initial
releases. Suddenly, there were old-but-new ideas on how to do source
control being exposed to new and willing-to-experiment audiences. DVCS
were a critical leap from traditional version control because they
(theoretically) impose less process and workflow limitations on users.
With traditional version control, you needed to be online to commit,
meaning you were managing patches, not commits, in your local
development workflow. There were some forms of branching and merging,
but they were a far cry from what is available today and were often too
complex for mere mortals to use. As more and more people were exposed to
<em>distributed</em> version control, they welcomed its less-restrictive and
more powerful workflows. They realized that source control tools don't
have to be so limiting. <em>Distributed</em> version control also promised all
kinds of revamped workflows that could be harnessed. There were
potential wins all around.</p>
<p>Around the same time that open source DVCS systems were emerging, web
browsers were evolving from an application to render static pages to a
platform for running web <em>applications</em>. Web sites using JavaScript
to dynamically manipulate web page content (DHTML as it was known back
then) were starting to hit their stride. I believe it was GMail that
turned the most heads as to the full power of the <em>modern web</em>
experience, with its novel-for-its-time extreme reliance on
XMLHttpRequest for dynamically changing page content. People were
realizing that powerful, desktop-like applications could be built for
the web and could run everywhere.</p>
<p>GitHub launched in April 2008 standing on the shoulders of both the
emerging interest in the Git content tracking tool and the capabilities
of modern browsers.</p>
<p>I wasn't an early user of GitHub. My recollection is that GitHub was
mostly a Rubyist's playground back then. I wasn't a Ruby programmer, so
I had little reason to use GitHub in the early stages. But people did
start using GitHub. And in the spirit of Ruby (on Rails), GitHub moved
fast, or at least was projecting the notion that they were. While other
services built on top of DVCS tools - like Bitbucket - did exist back then,
GitHub seemed to have momentum associated with it. (Look at the archives
for <a href="https://github.com/blog">GitHub's</a> and
<a href="https://blog.bitbucket.org/">Bitbucket's</a> respective blogs. GitHub has
hundreds of blog entries; Bitbucket numbers in the dozens.) Developers
everywhere up until this point had all been dealing with sub-optimal tools
and workflows. Some of us realized it. Others hadn't. Many of those who
did saw GitHub as a beacon of hope: we have all these new ideas and new
potentials with distributed version control and here is a service under
active development trying to figure out how to exploit that. Oh, and
it's free for open source. Sign me up!</p>
<p>GitHub did capitalize on a market opportunity. They also capitalized on
the value of marketing and the perception that they were moving fast and
providing features that people - especially in open source - wanted.
This captured the early adopters market. But I think what really set
GitHub apart and led to the success they are enjoying today is their
<em>code first</em> approach and their desire to make contribution easy, and
even fun and sociable.</p>
<p>As developers, our job is to solve problems. We often do that by writing
and changing code. And this often involves working as part of a team, or
collaborating. To collaborate, we need tools. You eventually need some
processes. And as I
<a href="/blog/2015/01/09/firefox-contribution-process-debt/">recently blogged</a>,
this can lead to <em>process debt</em> and inefficiencies associated with them.</p>
<p>Before GitHub, the <em>process debt</em> for contributing to other projects was
high. You often had to subscribe to mailing lists in order to submit
patches as emails. Or, you had to create an account on someone's bug
tracker or code review tool before you could send patches. Then you had
to figure out how to use these tools and any organization or
project-specific extensions and workflows attached to them. It was quite
involved and a lot could go wrong. Many projects and organizations (like
Mozilla) still practice this traditional methology. Furthermore (and as
I've
<a href="/blog/2014/10/27/implications-of-using-bugzilla-for-firefox-patch-development/">written before</a>),
these traditional, single patch/commit-based tools often aren't
effective at ensuring the desired output of high quality software.</p>
<p>Before GitHub solved <em>process debt</em> via commoditization of knowledge via
market dominance, they took another approach: emphasizing <em>code first</em>
development.</p>
<p>GitHub is all about the <strong>code</strong>. You load a project page and you see
<strong>code</strong>. You may think a README with basic project information would be
the first thing on a <em>project</em> page. But it isn't. <em>Code</em>, like data,
is king.</p>
<p>Collaboration and contribution on GitHub revolve around the <em>pull
request</em>. It's a way of saying, <em>hey, I made a change, will you take
it?</em> There's nothing too novel in the concept of the <em>pull request</em>:
it's fundamentally no different than sending emails with patches to a
mailing list. But what is so special is GitHub's execution. Gone are
the days of configuring and using one-off tools and processes. Instead,
we have the friendly confines of a clean, friendly, and modern web
experience. While GitHub is built upon the Git tool, you don't even
need to use Git (a tool
<a href="http://git-man-page-generator.lokaltog.net/">lampooned</a>
for its
<a href="http://stevelosh.com/blog/2013/04/git-koans/">horrible usability and approachability</a>)
to contribute on GitHub! Instead, you can
<a href="https://help.github.com/articles/github-flow-in-the-browser/">do everything from your browser</a>.
That warrants repeating: <strong>you don't need to leave your browser to
contribute on GitHub</strong>. GitHub has essentially reduced <em>process debt</em>
to <em>edit a text document</em> territory, and pretty much anybody who has
used a computer can do that. This has enabled GitHub to dabble into
non-code territory, such as its
<a href="https://government.github.com/">GitHub and Government</a> initiative to
foster community involvement in government. (GitHub is really a platform
for easily seeing and changing <em>any</em> content or data. But, please, let
me continue using <em>code</em> as a stand-in, since I want to focus on the
developer audience.)</p>
<p>GitHub took an overly-complicated and fragmented world of varying
contribution processes and made the new world revolve around code and a
unified and simple process for change - the <em>pull request</em>.</p>
<p>Yes, there are other reasons for GitHub's success. You can make strong
arguments that GitHub has capitalized on the social and psychological
aspects of coding and human desire for success and happiness. I agree.</p>
<p>You can also argue GitHub succeeded because of Git. That statement is
more or less technically accurate, but I don't think it is a sound
argument. Git may have been the most feature complete open source
DVCS at the time GitHub came into existence. But that doesn't mean there
is something special about Git that no other DVCS has that makes GitHub
popular. Had another tool been more feature complete or had the backing
of a project as large as Linux at the time of GitHub's launch, we could
very well be looking at a successful service built on something that
isn't Git. Git had early market advantage and I argue its popularity
today - a lot of it via GitHub - is largely a result of its early
advantages over competing tools. And, I would go so far to say that when
you consider the poor usability of Git and the pain that its users go
through when first learning it, more accurate statements would be that
<em>GitHub succeeded in spite of Git</em> and <em>Git owes much of its success to
GitHub</em>.</p>
<p>When I look back at the rise of GitHub, I see a service that has
succeeded by putting people first by allowing them to capitalize
on more productive workflows and processes. They've done this by
emphasizing <em>code</em>, not process, as the means for change. Organizations
and projects should take note.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <author>
      <name>Gregory Szorc</name>
      <uri>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog</uri>
    </author>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On Monolithic Repositories]]></title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2014/09/09/on-monolithic-repositories" />
    <id>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2014/09/09/on-monolithic-repositories</id>
    <updated>2014-09-09T10:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2014-09-09T10:00:00Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Git" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Mercurial" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Mozilla" />
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[On Monolithic Repositories]]></summary>
    <content type="html" xml:base="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2014/09/09/on-monolithic-repositories"><![CDATA[<p>When companies or organizations deploy version control, they have to
make many choices. One of them is how many repositories to create.
Your choices are essentially a) a single, monolithic repository that
holds everything b) many separate, smaller repositories that hold
all the individual parts c) something in between.</p>
<p>The prevailing convention today (especially in the open source
realm) is to create many separate and loosely coupled repositories,
each repository mapping to a specific product or service. That does
seem reasonable: if you were organizing files on your filesystem,
you would group them by functionality or role (photos, music,
documents, etc). And, version control tools are functionally
filesystems. So it makes sense to draw repository boundaries at
directory/role levels.</p>
<p>Further reinforcing the separate repository convention is the
scaling behavior of our version control tools. Git, the popular
tool in open source these days, doesn't scale well to very large
repositories due to - among other things - not having narrow clones
(fetching a subset of files). It scales well enough to the
overwhelming majority of projects. But if you are a large
organization generating lots of data (read: gigabytes of data over
hundreds of thousands of files and commits) for version control,
Git is unsuitable in its current form. Other tools (like Mercurial)
don't currently fare that much better (although Mercurial has plans
to tackle these scaling vectors).</p>
<p>Despite popular convention and even limitations in tools, companies
like Google and Facebook opt to run large, monolithic repositories.
Google runs Perforce.
<a href="https://code.facebook.com/posts/218678814984400/scaling-mercurial-at-facebook/">Facebook is on Mercurial</a>,
or at least is in the process of migrating to Mercurial.</p>
<p>Why do these companies run monolithic repositories?
In <a href="http://www.perforce.com/sites/default/files/still-all-one-server-perforce-scale-google-wp.pdf">Google's words</a>:</p>
<p><em>We have a single large depot with almost all of Google's projects
on it. This aids agile development and is much loved by our users,
since it allows almost anyone to easily view almost any code, allows
projects to share code, and allows engineers to move freely from
project to project. Documentation and data is stored on the server
as well as code.</em></p>
<p>So, monolithic repositories are all about moving fast and getting things
done more efficiently. In other words, <strong>monolithic repositories
increase developer productivity.</strong></p>
<p>Furthermore, monolithic repositories are also more compatible with
the ebb and flow of large organizations and large software projects.
Components, features, products, and teams come and go, merge and split.
The only constant is change. And if you are maintaining separate
repositories that attempt to map to this ever-changing organizational
topology, you are going to have a bad time. Either you'll be
constantly copying, moving, merging, splitting, etc data and repositories.
Or your repositories will be organized in a very non-logical and
non-intuitive manner. That translates to overhead and lost productivity.
I think that monolithic repositories handle the realities of large
organizations much better. Big change or reorganization you want
to reflect? You can make a single, atomic, history-preserving commit
to move things around. I think that's much more manageable, especially
when you consider the difficulty and annoyance of history-preserving
changes across repositories.</p>
<p>Naysayers will decry monolithic repositories on principled and practical
grounds.</p>
<p>The principled camp will say that separate repositories
constitute a loosely coupled (dare I say service oriented) architecture
that maps better to how software is consumed, assembled, and deployed
and that erecting barriers in the form of separate repositories
deliberately enforces this architecture. I agree. However, you can
still maintain a loosely coupled architecture with monolithic
repositories. The Subversion model of checking out a single tree
<em>from a larger repository</em> proves this. Furthermore, I would say
architecture decisions should be enforced by people (via code review,
etc), not via version control repository topology. I believe this
principled argument against monolithic repositories to be rather weak.</p>
<p>The principled camp living in the open source realm may also decry
monolithic repositories as an affront to the spirit of open source.
They would say that a monolithic repository creates unfairly strong
ties to the organization that operates it and creates barriers to
forking, etc. This may be true. But monolithic repositories don't
intrinsically infringe on the
<a href="https://www.gnu.org/philosophy/free-sw.html">basic software freedoms</a>,
organizations do. Therefore, I find this principled argument rather
weak.</p>
<p>The practical camp will say that monolithic repositories just don't
scale or aren't suitable for general audiences. These concerns are
real.</p>
<p><em>Fully</em> distributed version control systems (every commit on every
machine) definitely don't scale past certain limits. Depending on your
repository and user base, your scaling limits include disk space
(repository data terabytes in size), bandwidth (repository data terabytes
in size), filesystem (repository hundreds of thousands or millions of
files), CPU and memory (operations on large repositories take too
many system resources), and many heads/branches (tools like Git and
Mercurial don't scale well to tens of thousands of heads/branches).
These limitations with fully distributed version
control are why distributed version control tools like Git and
Mercurial support a partially-distributed mode that behaves more like
your classical server-client model, like those employed by Subversion,
Perforce, etc. Git supports shallow clone and sparse checkout.
Mercurial supports shallow clone (via remotefilelog) and has planned
support for narrow clone and sparse checkout in the next release or
two. Of course, you can avoid the scaling limitations of distributed
version control by employing a non-distributed tool, such as Subversion.
Many companies continue to reach this conclusion today. However,
users adapted to the distributed workflow would likely be
up in arms (they would probably use tools like hg-subversion or git-svn
to maintain their workflows). So, while scaling of version control
can be a real concern, there are solutions and workarounds. However,
they do involve falling back to a partially-distributed model.</p>
<p>Another concern with monolithic repositories is user access control. You
inevitably have code or data that is more sensitive and want to limit
who can change or even access it. Separate repositories seem to
facilitate a simpler model: per-repository access control. With
monolithic repositories, you have to worry about per-directory/subtree
permissions, an increased risk of data leaking, etc. This concern is
more real with distributed version control, as distributed data and
access control aren't naturally compatible. But these issues can be
resolved. And if the tooling supports it, there is only a semantic
difference between managing access control between repositories versus
components of a single repository.</p>
<p>When it comes to repository hosting conversions, I agree with Google
and Facebook: <strong>I prefer monolithic repositories</strong>. When I am interacting
with version control, I just want to get stuff done. I don't want to
waste time dealing with multiple commands to manage multiple
repositories. I don't want to waste time or expend cognitive load
dealing with submodule, subrepository, or big files management. I
don't want to waste time trying to find and reuse code, data, or
documentation. I want everything at my fingertips, where it can be
easily discovered, inspected, and used. Monolithic repositories
facilitate these workflows more than separate repositories and make
me more productive as a result.</p>
<p>Now, if only all the tools and processes we use and love would work
with monolithic repositories...</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <author>
      <name>Gregory Szorc</name>
      <uri>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog</uri>
    </author>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Repository-Centric Development]]></title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2014/07/24/repository-centric-development" />
    <id>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2014/07/24/repository-centric-development</id>
    <updated>2014-07-24T20:23:00Z</updated>
    <published>2014-07-24T20:23:00Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Git" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Mercurial" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Mozilla" />
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Repository-Centric Development]]></summary>
    <content type="html" xml:base="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2014/07/24/repository-centric-development"><![CDATA[<p>I was editing a wiki page yesterday and I think I coined a new term
which I'd like to enter the common nomenclature: <em>repository-centric
development</em>. The term refers to development/version control
workflows that place repositories - not patches - first.</p>
<p>When collaborating on version controlled code with modern tools like
Git and Mercurial, you essentially have two choices on how to
share version control data: patches or repositories.</p>
<p>Patches have been around since the dawn of version control. Everyone
knows how they work: your version control system has a copy of
the canonical data and it can export a view of a specific change
into what's called a patch. A patch is essentially a diff with
extra metadata.</p>
<p>When distributed version control systems came along, they brought
with them an alternative to patch-centric development:
repository-centric development. You could still exchange patches if you
wanted, but distributed version control allowed you to <em>pull</em> changes
directly from multiple <em>repositories</em>. You weren't limited to a single
master server (that's what the <em>distributed</em> in <em>distributed version
control</em> means). You also didn't have to go through an intermediate
transport such as email to exchange patches: you communicate directly
with a peer repository instance.</p>
<p>Repository-centric development eliminates the <em>middle man</em> required
for patch exchange: instead of exchanging derived data, you exchange
the actual data, speaking the repository's native language.</p>
<p>One advantage of repository-centric development is it eliminates the
problem of patch non-uniformity. Patches come in many different flavors.
You have plain diffs. You have diffs with metadata. You have Git style
metadata. You have Mercurial style metadata. You can produce patches
with various lines of context in the diff. There are different methods
for handling binary content. There are different ways to express
file adds, removals, and renames. It's all a hot mess. Any system
that consumes patches needs to deal with the non-uniformity. Do you
think this isn't a problem in the real world? Think again. If you are
involved with an open source project that collects patches via email
or by uploading patches to a bug tracker, have you ever seen someone
accidentally upload a patch in the wrong format? That's patch
non-uniformity. New contributors to Firefox do this all the time. I
also see it in the Mercurial project. With repository-centric
development, patches never enter the picture, so patch non-uniformity
is a non-issue. (Don't confuse the superficial formatting of patches
with the content, such as an incorrect commit message format.)</p>
<p>Another advantage of repository-centric development is it makes the
act of exchanging data easier. Just have two repositories talk to
each other. This used to be difficult, but hosting services like
GitHub and Bitbucket make this easy. Contrast with patches, which
require hooking your version control tool up to wherever those patches
are located. The Linux Kernel, like so many other projects,
<a href="https://www.kernel.org/doc/Documentation/SubmittingPatches">uses email for contributing changes</a>.
So now Git, Mercurial, etc all fulfill Zawinski's law. This means your
version control tool is talking to your inbox to send and receive code.
Firefox development uses Bugzilla to hold patches as attachments. So now your
version control tool needs to talk to your issue tracker. (Not the worst
idea in the world I will concede.) While, yes, the tools around using
email or uploading patches to issue trackers or whatever else you are
using to exchange patches exist and can work pretty well, the grim
reality is that these tools are all reinventing the wheel of repository
exchange and are solving a problem that has already been solved by
<em>git push</em>, <em>git fetch</em>, <em>hg pull</em>, <em>hg push</em>, etc. Personally, I would
rather <em>hg push</em> to a remote and have tools like issue trackers and
mailing lists pull directly from repositories. At least that way they
have a direct line into the source of truth and are guaranteed a
consistent output format.</p>
<p>Another area where direct exchange is huge is multi-patch commits
(<em>branches</em> in Git parlance) or where commit data is fragmented. When
pushing patches to email, you need to insert metadata saying which patch
comes after which. Then the email import tool needs to reassemble things
in the proper order (remember that the typical convention is one email
per patch and email can be delivered out of order). Not the most
difficult problem in the world to solve. But seriously, it's been
solved already by <em>git fetch</em> and <em>hg pull</em>! Things are worse for
Bugzilla. There is no bullet-proof way to order patches there. The
convention at Mozilla is to add <em>Part N</em> strings to
commit messages and have the Bugzilla import tool do a sort (I assume it
does that). But what if you have a logical commit series spread across
multiple bugs? How do you reassemble everything into a linear series of
commits? You don't, sadly. Just today I wanted to apply a somewhat
complicated series of patches to the Firefox build system I was asked to
review so I could jump into a debugger and see what was going on so I
could conduct a more thorough review. There were 4 or 5 patches spread
over 3 or 4 bugs. Bugzilla and its patch-centric workflow prevented me
from importing the patches. Fortunately, this patch series was pushed to
Mozilla's Try server, so I could pull from there. But I haven't always
been so fortunate. This limitation means developers have to make
sacrifices such as writing fewer, larger patches (this makes code review
harder) or involving unrelated parties in the same bug and/or review.
In other words, deficient tools are imposing limited workflows. No bueno.</p>
<p>It is a fair criticism to say that not everyone can host a server or
that permissions and authorization are hard. Although I think concerns
about impact are overblown. If you are a small project, just create a
GitHub or Bitbucket account. If you are a larger project, realize that
people time is one of your largest expenses and invest in tools like
proper and efficient repository hosting (often this can be GitHub) to
reduce this waste and keep your developers happier and more efficient.</p>
<p>One of the clearest examples of repository-centric development is
GitHub. There are no patches in GitHub. Instead, you <em>git push</em>
and <em>git fetch</em>. Want to apply someone else's work? Just add a remote
and <em>git fetch</em>! Contrast with first locating patches, hooking up
Git to consume them (this part was always confusing to me - do you
need to retroactively have them sent to your email inbox so you can
import them from there), and finally actually importing them. Just
give me a URL to a repository already. But the benefits of
repository-centric development with GitHub don't stop at pushing and
pulling. GitHub has built code review functionality into pushes. They
call these <em>pull requests</em>. While I have significant issues with
GitHub's implemention of pull requests (I need to blog about those some
day), I can't deny the utility of the repository-centric workflow and
all the benefits around it. Once you switch to GitHub and its
repository-centric workflow, you more clearly see how lacking
patch-centric development is and quickly lose your desire to go back
to the 1990's state-of-the-art methods for software development.</p>
<p>I hope you now know what repository-centric development is and will join
me in championing it over patch-based development.</p>
<p>Mozillians reading this will be very happy to learn that work is under
way to shift Firefox's development workflow to a more repository-centric
world. Stay tuned.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <author>
      <name>Gregory Szorc</name>
      <uri>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog</uri>
    </author>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New Repository for Mozilla Version Control Tools]]></title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2014/02/05/new-repository-for-mozilla-version-control-tools" />
    <id>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2014/02/05/new-repository-for-mozilla-version-control-tools</id>
    <updated>2014-02-05T19:15:00Z</updated>
    <published>2014-02-05T19:15:00Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Git" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Mercurial" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Mozilla" />
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[New Repository for Mozilla Version Control Tools]]></summary>
    <content type="html" xml:base="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2014/02/05/new-repository-for-mozilla-version-control-tools"><![CDATA[<p>Version control systems can be highly useful tools.</p>
<p>At Mozilla, we've made numerous improvements and customizations to our
version control tools. We have <a href="https://hg.mozilla.org/hgcustom/hghooks/">custom hooks</a>
that run on the server. We have a <a href="https://hg.mozilla.org/hgcustom/hg_templates/">custom skin</a>
for Mercurial's web interface. Mozillians have written a handful of
Mercurial extensions to aid with common developer tasks, such as
<a href="https://bitbucket.org/sfink/trychooser">pushing to try</a>,
<a href="https://hg.mozilla.org/users/tmielczarek_mozilla.com/bzexport">interacting with Bugzilla</a>,
<a href="https://bitbucket.org/sfink/mqext">making mq more useful</a>, and more.</p>
<p>These have all come into existence in an organic manner, one after the
other. Individuals have seen an itch and scratched it. Good for them.
Good for Mozilla.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, the collection of amassed tools has become quite large.
They have become difficult to discover and keep up to date. The
consistency in quality and style between the tools varies. Each tool has
separate processes for updating and changing.</p>
<p>I contacted the maintainers of the popular version control tools at
Mozilla with a simple proposal: let's maintain all our tools under one
repo. This would allow us to increase cohesion, share code, maintain a
high quality bar, share best practices, etc. There were no major
objections, so we now have a <a href="https://hg.mozilla.org/hgcustom/version-control-tools/">unified repository</a>
containing our version control tools!</p>
<p>Currently, we only have a few Mercurial extensions in there. A goal is
to accumulate as much of the existing Mercurial infrastructure into
that repository as possible. Client code. Server code. All of the code.
I want developers to be able to install the same hooks on their clients
as what's running on the server: why should your local repo let you
commit something that the server will reject? I want developers to be
able to reasonably reproduce Mozilla's canonical version control server
configuration locally. That way, you can test things locally with a high
confidence that your changes will work the same way on production. This
allows deployments to move faster and with less friction.</p>
<p>The immediate emphasis will be on moving extensions into this repo and
deprecating the old homes on user repositories. Over time, we'll move
into consolidating server code and getting hg.mozilla.org and
git.mozilla.org to use this repository. But that's a lower priority: the
most important goal right now is to make it easier and friendlier for
people to run productivity-enhancing tools.</p>
<p>So, if you see your Mercurial extensions alerting you that they've been
moved to a new repository, now you know what's going on.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <author>
      <name>Gregory Szorc</name>
      <uri>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog</uri>
    </author>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Aggregating Version Control Info at Mozilla]]></title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2014/01/21/aggregating-version-control-info-at-mozilla" />
    <id>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2014/01/21/aggregating-version-control-info-at-mozilla</id>
    <updated>2014-01-21T10:50:00Z</updated>
    <published>2014-01-21T10:50:00Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Git" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Mercurial" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Mozilla" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Python" />
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Aggregating Version Control Info at Mozilla]]></summary>
    <content type="html" xml:base="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2014/01/21/aggregating-version-control-info-at-mozilla"><![CDATA[<p>Over the winter break, I set out on an ambitious project to create
a service to help developers and others manage the flury
of patches going into Firefox. While the project is far from complete,
I'm ready to unleash the first part of the project upon the world.</p>
<p>If you point your browsers to
<a href="http://moztree.gregoryszorc.com/">moztree.gregoryszorc.com</a>, you'll
hopefully see some documentation about what I've built.
<a href="https://bitbucket.org/indygreg/moz-tree-utopia">Source code</a> is
available and free, of course. Patches very welcome.</p>
<p>Essentially, I built a centralized indexing service for version
control repositories with Mozilla's extra metadata thrown in.
I tell it what repositories to mirror, and it clones everything,
fetches data such as the pushlog and Git SHA-1 mappings, and
stores everything in a central database. It then exposes this
aggregated data through world-readable web services.</p>
<p>Currently, I have the service indexing the popular project branches
for Firefox (central, aurora, beta, release, esr, b2g, inbound, fx-team,
try, etc). You can view the
<a href="http://moztree.gregoryszorc.com/api/repos">full list</a> via the web
service. As a bonus, I'm also serving these repositories via
<a href="http://hg.gregoryszorc.com/">hg.gregoryszorc.com</a>. My server appears
to be significantly faster than
<a href="https://hg.mozilla.org">hg.mozilla.org</a>. If you want to use it for
your daily needs, go for it. I make no SLA guarantees, however.</p>
<p>I'm also using this service as an opportunity to experiment with
alternate forms of Mercurial hosting. I have mirrors of mozilla-central
and the try repository with generaldelta and lz4 compression enabled.
I may blog about what those are eventually. The teaser is that they can
make Mercurial perform a lot faster under some conditions. I'm also
using ZFS under the hood to manage repositories. Each repository is a
ZFS filesystem. This means I can create repository copies on the server
(user repositories anyone?) at a nearly free cost. Contrast this to the
traditional method of full clones, which take lots of time, memory, CPU,
and storage.</p>
<p>Anyway, some things you can do with the existing web service:</p>
<ul>
<li>Obtain metadata about Mercurial changesets.
  <a href="http://moztree.gregoryszorc.com/api/changeset/940b2974f35b">Example</a>.</li>
<li>Look up metadata about Git commits.
  <a href="http://moztree.gregoryszorc.com/api/git-sha1/40438af67c321">Example</a>.</li>
<li>Obtain a <a href="http://moztree.gregoryszorc.com/api/spore">SPORE descriptor</a>
  describing the web service endpoints. This allows you to auto-generate
  clients from descriptors. Yay!</li>
</ul>
<p>Obviously, that's not a lot. But adding new endpoints is relatively
straightforward. See the <a href="https://bitbucket.org/indygreg/moz-tree-utopia/src/tip/repodata/web/app.py">source</a>.
It's literally as easy as defining a URL mapping and writing a
database query.</p>
<p>The performance is also not the best. I just haven't put in the effort
to tune things yet. All of the querying hits the database, not
Mercurial. So, making things faster should merely be a matter of
database and hosting optimization. Patches welcome!</p>
<p>Some ideas that I haven't had time to implement yet:</p>
<ul>
<li>Return changests in a specific repository</li>
<li>Return recently pushed changesets</li>
<li>Return pushes for a given user</li>
<li>Return commits for a given author</li>
<li>Return commits referencing a given bug</li>
<li>Obtain TBPL URLs for pushes with changeset</li>
<li>Integrate bugzilla metadata</li>
</ul>
<p>Once those are in place, I foresee this service powering a number of
dashboards. Patches welcome.</p>
<p>Again, this service is only the tip of what's possible. There's a lot
that could be built on this service. I have ideas. Others have ideas.</p>
<p>The project includes a Vagrant file and Puppet
manifests for provisioning the server. It's a one-liner to get a
development environment up and running. It should be really easy to
contribute to this project. Patches welcome.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <author>
      <name>Gregory Szorc</name>
      <uri>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog</uri>
    </author>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Importance of Hosting Your Version Control Server]]></title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2013/11/13/importance-of-hosting-your-version-control-server" />
    <id>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2013/11/13/importance-of-hosting-your-version-control-server</id>
    <updated>2013-11-13T09:25:00Z</updated>
    <published>2013-11-13T09:25:00Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Git" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Mercurial" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Mozilla" />
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Importance of Hosting Your Version Control Server]]></summary>
    <content type="html" xml:base="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2013/11/13/importance-of-hosting-your-version-control-server"><![CDATA[<p>The subject of where to host version control repositories comes up a lot
at Mozilla. It takes many forms:</p>
<ul>
<li>We should move the Firefox repository to GitHub</li>
<li>I should be allowed to commit to GitHub</li>
<li>I want the canonical repository to be hosted by Bitbucket</li>
</ul>
<p>When Firefox development is concerned, Release Engineerings puts down
their foot and insists the canonical repository be hosted by Mozilla,
under a Mozilla hostname. When that's not possible, they set up a mirror
on Mozilla infrastructure.</p>
<p>I think a
<a href="https://groups.google.com/d/topic/jenkinsci-dev/-myjRIPcVwU/discussion">recent issue with the Jenkins project</a>
demonstrates why hosting your own version control server is important.
The gist is someone force pushed to a bunch of repos hosted on GitHub.
They needed to involve GitHub support to recover from the issue. While
it appears they largely recovered (and GitHub support deserves kudos - I
don't want to take away from their excellence), this problem would have
been avoided or the response time significantly decreased if the Jenkins
people had direct control over the Git server: they either could have
installed a custom hook that would have prevented the pushes or had
access to the reflog so they could have easily seen the last pushed
revision and easily forced pushed back to it. GitHub doesn't have a
mechanism for defining pre-* hooks, doesn't allow defining custom
hooks (a security and performance issue for them), and doesn't
expose the reflog data.</p>
<p>Until repository hosting services expose full repository data (such as
reflogs) and allow you to define custom hooks, accidents like these will
happen and the recovery time will be longer than if you hosted the repo
yourself.</p>
<p>It's possible repository hosting services like GitHub and Bitbucket will
expose these features or provide a means to quickly recover. If so,
kudos to them. But larger, more advanced projects will likely employ
custom hooks and considering custom hooks are a massive security and
performance issue for any hosted service provider, I'm not going to
hold my breath this particular feature is rolled out any time soon.
This is unfortunate, as it makes projects seemingly choose between
low risk/low convenience and GitHub's vibrant developer community.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <author>
      <name>Gregory Szorc</name>
      <uri>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog</uri>
    </author>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Thoughts on Mercurial (and Git)]]></title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2013/05/12/thoughts-on-mercurial-(and-git)" />
    <id>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2013/05/12/thoughts-on-mercurial-(and-git)</id>
    <updated>2013-05-12T12:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2013-05-12T12:00:00Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Mozilla" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Mercurial" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Git" />
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Thoughts on Mercurial (and Git)]]></summary>
    <content type="html" xml:base="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2013/05/12/thoughts-on-mercurial-(and-git)"><![CDATA[<p>My first experience with Mercurial (Firefox development)
was very unpleasant. Coming from Git, I thought Mercurial was slow
and perhaps even more awkward to use than Git. I frequently
encountered repository corruption that required me to reclone. I thought
the concept of a patch queue was silly compared to Git branches. It
was all extremely frustrating and I dare say a hinderance to my
productivity. It didn't help that I was surrounded by a bunch of people
who had previous experience with Git and opined about every minute
difference.</p>
<p>Two years later and I'm on much better terms with Mercurial. I initially
thought it might be Stockholm Syndrome, but after reflection I can point
at specific changes and enlightenments that have reshaped my opinions.</p>
<h2>Newer versions of Mercurial are much better</h2>
<p>I first started using Mercurial in the 1.8 days and thought it was
horrible. However, modern releases are much, much better. I've noticed
a steady improvement in the quality and speed of Mercurial in the last
few years.</p>
<p><strong>If you aren't running 2.5 or later (Mercurial 2.6 was released earlier
this month), you should take the time to upgrade today.</strong> When you upgrade,
you should of course read the
<a href="http://mercurial.selenic.com/wiki/WhatsNew">changelog</a> and
<a href="http://mercurial.selenic.com/wiki/UpgradeNotes">upgrade notes</a> so you
can make the most of the new features.</p>
<h2>Proper configuration is key</h2>
<p>For <em>my</em> workflow, the default configuration of Mercurial out of the box
is... far from optimal. There are a number of basic changes that need to
be made to satisfy <em>my</em> expectations for a version control tool.</p>
<p>I used to think this was a shortcoming with Mercurial: why not ship a
powerful and useful environment out of the box? But, after talking to a
Mercurial core contributor, this is mostly by design. Apparently a
principle of the Mercurial project is that the CLI tool (<em>hg</em>) should be
simple by default and should minimize foot guns. They view actions like
rebasing and patch queues as advanced and thus don't have them enabled
by default. Seasoned developers may scoff at this. But, I see where
Mercurial is coming from. I only need to refer everyone to her first
experience with Git as an example of what happens when you don't aim for
simplicity. (I've never met a Git user who didn't think it overly
complicated at first.)</p>
<p>Anyway, to get the most out of Mercurial, it is essential to configure
it to your liking, much like you install plugins or extensions in your
code editor.</p>
<p><strong>Every person running Mercurial should go to
<a href="http://mercurial.selenic.com/wiki/UsingExtensions">http://mercurial.selenic.com/wiki/UsingExtensions</a>
and take the time to find extensions that will make your life better</strong>.
You should also run <em>hg help hgrc</em> to view all the configuration
options. There is a mountain of productivity wins waiting to be realized.</p>
<p>For reference, my <a href="https://gist.github.com/indygreg/5511712">~/.hgrc</a>.
Worth noting are some of the built-in externsions I've enabled:</p>
<ul>
<li>color - Colorize terminal output. Clear UX win.</li>
<li>histedit - Provides  <em>git rebase --interactive</em> behavior.</li>
<li>pager - Feed command output into a pager (like <em>less</em>). Clear UX win.</li>
<li>progress - Draw progress bars on long-running operations. Clear UX
  win.</li>
<li>rebase - Ability to easily rebase patches on top of other heads.
  This is a basic feature of patch management.</li>
<li>transplant - Easily move patches between repositories, branches, etc.</li>
</ul>
<p>If I were on Linux, I'd also use the <em>inotify</em> extension, which installs
filesystem watchers so operations like <em>hg status</em> are instantaneous.</p>
<p>In addition to the built-in extensions, there are a number of 3rd party
extensions that improve my Mozilla workflow:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://bitbucket.org/sfink/mqext">mqext</a> - Automatically commit to
  your patch queue when you qref, etc. This is a lifesaver. If that's
  not enough, it suggests reviewers for your patch, suggests a bug
  component, and let's you find bugs touching the files you are
  touching.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/pbiggar/trychooser">trychooser</a> - Easily push
  changes to Mozilla's Try infrastructure.</li>
<li><a href="https://hg.mozilla.org/users/robarnold_cmu.edu/qimportbz">qimportbz</a> -
  Easily import patches from Bugzilla.</li>
<li><a href="https://hg.mozilla.org/users/tmielczarek_mozilla.com/bzexport">bzexport</a> -
  Easily export patches to Bugzilla.</li>
</ul>
<p>I'm amazed more developers don't use these simple productivity wins.
Could it be that people simply don't realize they are available?</p>
<p>Mozilla has a <a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=794580">bug</a>
tracking easier configuration of the user's Mercurial environment. My
hope is one day people simply run a single command and get a
Mozilla-optimized Mercurial environment that <em>just works</em>. Along the same
vein, if your extensions are out of date, it prompts you to update them.
This is one of the benefits of a unified developer tool like mach: you
can put these checks in one place and everyone can reap the benefits
easily.</p>
<h2>Mercurial is extensible</h2>
<p>The major differentiator from almost every other version control system
(especially Git) is the ease and degree to which Mercurial can be
extended and contorted. <strong>If you take anything away from this
post it should be that Mercurial is a flexible and agile tool.</strong></p>
<p>If you want to change the behavior of a built-in command, you can write
an extension that monkeypatches that command. If you want to write a new
command, you can of course do that easily. You can have extensions
interact with one another - all natively. You can even override the wire
protocol to provide new <em>capabilities</em> to extend how peers communicate
with one another. You can leverage this to transfer additional metadata
or data types. This has nearly infinite potential. If that's not enough,
it's possible to create a new branching/development primitive through
just an extension alone! If you want to invent Git-style branches with
Mercurial, you could do that! It may require client and server support,
but it's possible.</p>
<p>Mercurial accomplishes this by being written (mostly) in Python (as
opposed to C) and by having a clear API on which extensions can be
built. Writing extensions in Python is huge. You can easily drop into
the debugger to learn the API and your write-test loop is much smaller.</p>
<p>By contrast, most other version control systems (including Git) require
you to parse output of commands (this is the UNIX piping principle).
Mercurial supports this too, but the native Python API is so much more
powerful. Instead of parsing output, you can just read the raw values
from a Python data structure. Yes please.</p>
<p>Since I imagine a lot of people at Mozilla will be reading this, here
are some ways Mozilla could leverage the extensibility of Mercurial:</p>
<ul>
<li>Command to create try pushes (it exists - see above).</li>
<li>Record who pushed what when (we have this - it's called the pushlog).</li>
<li>Command to land patches. If inbound1 is closed,
  automatically rebase on inbound2. etc. This could even be
  monkeypatched into <em>hg push</em> so pushes to inbound are automatically
  intercepted and magic ensues.</li>
<li>Record the automation success/fail status against individual
  revisions and integrate with commands (e.g. only pull up to the most
  recent stable changeset).</li>
<li>Command to create a review request for a patch or patch queue.</li>
<li>Command to assist with reviews. Perhaps a reviewer wants to make minor
  changes. Mercurial could download and apply the patch(es), wait for
  your changes, then reupload to Bugzilla (or the review tool)
  automatically.</li>
<li>Annotating commits or pushes with automation info (which jobs to
  run, etc).</li>
<li>Find Bugzilla component for patch (it exists - see above).</li>
<li>Expose custom protocol for configuring automation settings for a
  repository or a head. e.g. clients (with access) could reconfigure
  PGO scheduling, coalescing, etc without having to involve RelEng -
  useful for twigs and lesser used repositories.</li>
<li>So much more.</li>
</ul>
<p>Essentially, Mercurial itself could become the CLI tool code development
centers around. Whether that is a good idea is up for
debate. But, it can. And that says a lot about the flexibility of
Mercurial.</p>
<h2>Future potential of Mercurial</h2>
<p>When you consider the previous three points, you arrive at a new one:
Mercurial has a ton of future potential. The fact that extensions can
evolve vanilla Mercurial into something that resembles Mercurial in
name only is a testament to this.</p>
<p>When I sat down with a Mercurial core contributor, they reinforced this.
To them, Mercurial is a core library with a limited set of user-facing
commands forming the stable API. Since core features (like storage) are
internal APIs (not public commands - like Git), this means they aren't
bound to backwards compatibility and can refactor internals as needed
and evolve over time without breaking the world. That is a terrific
luxury.</p>
<p>An example of this future potential is
<a href="http://mercurial.selenic.com/wiki/ChangesetEvolution">changeset evolution</a>.
If you don't know what that is, you should because it's awesome. One of
the things they figured out is how to propagate rebasing between
clones!</p>
<h2>Comparing to Git</h2>
<p>Two years ago I would have said I would never opt to use Mercurial over
Git. I cannot say that today.</p>
<p>I do believe Git still has the advantage over Mercurial in a few areas:</p>
<ul>
<li>Branch management. Mercurial branches are a non-starter for
  light-weigh work. Mercurial bookmarks are kinda-sorta like Git
  branches, but not quite. I <em>really</em> like aspects of Git branches.
  Hopefully changeset evolution will cover the remaining gaps and more.</li>
<li>Patch conflict management. Git seems to do a better job of resolving
  patch conflicts. But, I think this is mostly due to Mercurial's patch
  queue extension not using the same merge code as built-in commands
  (this is a fixable problem).</li>
<li>Developer mind share and GitHub. The GitHub ecosystem makes up for
  many of Git's shortcomings. Bitbucket isn't the same.</li>
</ul>
<p>However, I believe Mercurial has the upper hand for:</p>
<ul>
<li>Command line friendliness. Git's command line syntax is notoriously
  awful and the concepts can be difficult to master.</li>
<li>Extensibility. It's so easy to program custom workflows and commands
  with Mercurial. If you want to hack your version control system,
  Mercurial wins hands down. Where Mercurial embraces extensibility, I
  couldn't even find a page listing all the useful Git <em>extensions</em>!</li>
<li>Open source culture. Every time I've popped into the Mercurial IRC
  channel I've had a good experience. I get a response quickly and
  without snark. Git by contrast, well, let's just say I'd rather be
  affiliated with the Mercurial crowd.</li>
<li>Future potential. Git is a content addressable key-value store with a
  version control system bolted on top. Mercurial is designed to be a
  version control system. Furthermore, Mercurial's code base is much
  easier to hack on than Git's. While Git has largely maintained feature
  parity in the last few years, Mercurial has grown new features. I see
  Mercurial evolving faster than Git and in ways Git cannot.</li>
</ul>
<p>It's worth calling out the major detractors for each.</p>
<p>I think Git's major weakness is its lack of extensibility and inability
to evolve (at least currently). Git will need to grow a better
extensibility model with better abstractions to compete with Mercurial
on new features. Or, the Git community will need to be receptive to
experimental features living in the core. All of this will require
some major API breakage. Unfortunately, I see little evidence this will
occur. I'm unable to find a <em>vision</em> document for the future of Git, a
branch with major new features, or interesting threads on the mailing
list. I tried to ask in their IRC channel and got crickets.</p>
<p>I think Mercurial's greatest weakness is lack of developer mindshare.
Git and GitHub are where it's at. This is huge, especially for projects
wanting collaboration.</p>
<p>Of all those points, I want to stress the extensibility and future
potential of Mercurial. If hacking your tools to maximize potential
and awesomeness is your game, Mercurial wins. End of debate. However,
if you don't want to harness these advantages, then I think Git and
Mercurial are mostly on equal footing. But given the rate of
development in the Mercurial project and relative stagnation of Git
(I can't name a major new Git feature in years), I wouldn't be
surprised if Mercurial's feature set obviously overtakes Git's in
the next year or two. Mind share will of course take longer and will
likely depend on what hosting sites like GitHub and Bitbucket do
(I wouldn't be surprised if GitHub rebranded as <em>CodeHub</em> or
something some day). Time will tell.</p>
<h2>Extending case study</h2>
<p><em>I have removed the case study that appeared in the original article
because as Mike Hommey observed in the comments, it wasn't a totally
accurate comparison. I don't believe the case study significantly added
much to the post, so I likely won't write a new one.</em></p>
<h2>Conclusion</h2>
<p>From where I started with Mercurial, I never thought I'd say this. But
here it goes: I like Mercurial.</p>
<p>I started warming up when it became faster and more robust in recent
versions in the last few years. When I learned about its flexibility and
the fundamentals of the project and thus its future potential, I became
a true fan.</p>
<p>It's easy to not like Mercurial if you are a new user coming
from Git and are forced to use a new tool. But, once you take the time to
properly configure it and appreciate it for what it is and what it
can be, Mercurial is easy to like.</p>
<p>I think Mercurial and Git are both fine version control systems. I would
happily use either one for a new project. If the social aspects of
development (including encouraging new contributors) were important to
me, I would likely select Git and GitHub. But, if I wanted something
just for me or I was a large project looking for a system that scales
and is flexible or was looking to the future, I'd go with Mercurial.</p>
<p>Mercurial is a rising star in the version control world. It's getting
faster and better and enabling others to more easily innovate through
powerful extensions. The future is bright for this tool.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <author>
      <name>Gregory Szorc</name>
      <uri>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog</uri>
    </author>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Making hg-git Faster]]></title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2013/04/14/making-hg-git-faster" />
    <id>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2013/04/14/making-hg-git-faster</id>
    <updated>2013-04-14T21:45:00Z</updated>
    <published>2013-04-14T21:45:00Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Mozilla" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Mercurial" />
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="Git" />
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Making hg-git Faster]]></summary>
    <content type="html" xml:base="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2013/04/14/making-hg-git-faster"><![CDATA[<p>When enterprising individuals at Mozilla
<a href="http://bluishcoder.co.nz/2011/02/10/git-conversion-of-mozilla-central.html">started maintaining</a>
a Git mirror of Firefox's main source repository (hosted in Mercurial),
they ran into a significant problem: conversion was slow. The initial
conversion apparently took over 6 days and used a lot of memory.
Furthermore, each subsequent commit took many seconds, even on modern
hardware. This meant that the they could only maintain a Git mirror of
a few project branches and that updates would be slow. Furthermore,
the slowness of the conversion significantly discouraged people
from using the tool locally as part of regular development.</p>
<p>I thought this was unacceptable. I wanted to enable people to use
their tool of choice (Git) to develop Firefox. So, I did what annoyed
engineers do when confronted with an itch: I scratched it.</p>
<h2>Diagnosing the Problem</h2>
<p>When I started tackling this problem, I had little knowledge of the
problem space other than the problem statement: <em>converting from
Mercurial to Git is prohibitively slow</em> and that the slow tool was
<a href="http://hg-git.github.io/">hg-git</a>. My challenge was thus to make
hg-git faster.</p>
<p>When confronted with a performance problem, one of the first things you
do is identify the source of the bad performance. Then, you need to
acertain whether that is something you have the ability to change.</p>
<p>This often starts by answering some high-level questions then drilling
down into more detail as necessary. For a long-running system tool like
hg-git, I start with the <em>top test</em>: how much CPU, memory, and I/O is
the process utilizing?</p>
<p>In the case of hg-git, we were CPU bound. The Python process was
consistently pegging a single CPU core while periodically incurring I/O
(but not nearly enough to saturate a magnetic disk). This told me a few
things. First, I should look for bottlenecks inside Python. Second, I
should investigate whether parallel execution would be possible. The
latter is especially important these days because the trend in
processors is towards more cores rather than higher clock speeds. It's
no longer acceptable to let increases in clock speed or cycle efficiency
bail you out: if you want a CPU bound process to run as fast as
possible, it's often necessary to involve all available CPU cores.</p>
<p>Once I diagnosed CPU as the limiting factor, I pulled out the next tool
in the arsenal: a code profiler. I quickly discovered exactly where the
conversion was taking the most CPU time. As feared, it was in the
<em>export Mercurial changeset to Git commit</em> function.
Specifically, profiling had flagged the conversion of Mercurial
manifests to Git trees and blobs. Furthermore, most of the time was
spent in functions in Mercurial itself (Mercurial is implemented in
Python and hg-git calls into it natively) and Dulwich (a pure Python
implementation of Git). So, I was either looking at deficiencies or
Mercurial and/or Dulwich, a bad conversion algorithm in hg-git, or both.
To know which, I would need a better grasp on the internal storage
models of Mercurial and Git.</p>
<h2>Learning about Mercurial's and Git's internal storage models</h2>
<p>To understand why conversion from Mercurial to Git was slow, I needed to
understand how each stored data internally. My hope was that if attained
better understanding I could apply the knowledge to assess the algorithm
hg-git was using and optimize it, hopefully introducing parallel
execution along the way.</p>
<h3>Git's internals</h3>
<p>I already had a fairly good understanding of how Git works internally.
And, it's quite simple really. The <a href="http://git-scm.com/book/en/Git-Internals">Git Internals</a>
chapter of the <em>Pro Git</em> is extremely useful. While I encourage readers
to read all of the <a href="http://git-scm.com/book/en/Git-Internals-Git-Objects">Git Objects</a>
section, the gist is:</p>
<ul>
<li>Git's core storage is a key-value data store. Keys are SHA-1 checksums
  of content. Each entity is storage in a <em>Git object</em>.</li>
<li>A <em>blob</em> is an object holding the raw content of a file.</li>
<li>A <em>tree</em> is an object holding a list of <em>tree entries</em>. Each tree entry
  defines a blob, another tree object, etc. A tree is essentially a
  directory listing.</li>
<li>A <em>commit</em> object holds metadata about an individual Git commit. Each
  commit object refers to a specific <em>tree</em> object.</li>
</ul>
<p>When you introduce a new file that hasn't been seen before, a new <em>blob</em>
is added to storage. That blob is referenced by a <em>tree</em>. When you
update a file, a new <em>tree</em> is created referring to the new <em>blob</em> that
was created.</p>
<p>Things get a little complicated when you consider directories. If you
update the file <em>foo/bar/baz.c</em>, the tree for <em>foo/bar</em> changes (because
the SHA-1 of <em>baz.c</em> changed). And, the SHA-1 for the <em>foo/bar</em> tree
changes, so the <em>bar</em> entry in <em>foo</em>'s tree changes, changing the SHA-1
for the root tree.</p>
<p>That's essentially how Git addresses commits, directories, and files. If
you don't grok this, please, please read the aforementioned page on it -
it may even help you better grok Git!</p>
<h3>Mercurial's internals</h3>
<p>Unlike Git, I didn't really have a clue how Mercurial worked internally.
So, I needed to do some self-education here.</p>
<p>The best resource for Mercurial's storage model I've found is the
<a href="http://hgbook.red-bean.com/read/behind-the-scenes.html">Behind the Scenes</a>
chapter from <em>Mercurial: The Definitive Guide</em>. The gist is:</p>
<ul>
<li>History for an individual file is stored in a <em>filelog</em>. Each
  <em>filelog</em> contains the history of a single file. Each file revision
  has a hash based on the file contents.</li>
<li>The <em>manifest</em> lists every file, its permissions, and its file
  revision for each changeset in the repository.</li>
<li>The <em>changelog</em> contains information about each changeset, including
  the revision of the <em>manifest</em> to use.</li>
<li>Each of these logs contain <em>revisions</em> and you can address an
  individual revision within the log.</li>
</ul>
<p>From a high level, Mercurial's storage model is very similar to Git's.
They both address files by hashing their content. Where Git uses
multiple tree objects to define every file in a commit, Mercurial has a
single manifest containing a flat list. Aside from that, the
differences are mostly in implementation details. These are important,
as we'll soon see.</p>
<h2>Analyzing hg-git's conversion algorithm</h2>
<p>Armed with knowledge of how Git and Mercurial internally store data, I
was ready to analyze how hg-git was performing conversion from Mercurial
to Git. Since profiling revealed it was the <em>convert a single changeset
into Git commit</em> function that was taking all the time, I started there.</p>
<p>In Python (but not the actual Python), the algorithm was essentially:</p>
<div class="pygments_murphy"><pre><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">export_changeset_to_git</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">changeset</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">git</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">already_converted</span><span class="p">):</span>
    <span class="sd">&quot;&quot;&quot;Receives the Mercurial changeset and a handle on a Git object storre.&quot;&quot;&quot;</span>
    <span class="c"># This is an entity that helps us build Git tree objects from</span>
    <span class="c"># paths and blobs. The logic is at</span>
    <span class="c"># https://github.com/jelmer/dulwich/blob/2a8548be3b1fd4a1ae7d0436dce91611112c47c2/dulwich/index.py#L298</span>
    <span class="n">tree_builder</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">TreeBuilder</span><span class="p">()</span>

    <span class="k">for</span> <span class="nb">file</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="n">changeset</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">manifest</span><span class="p">:</span>
        <span class="n">blob_id</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">already_converted</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">get</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">file</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">id</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="bp">None</span><span class="p">)</span>

        <span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">blob_id</span> <span class="ow">is</span> <span class="bp">None</span><span class="p">:</span>
            <span class="n">blob</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">Blob</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">file</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">data</span><span class="p">())</span>
            <span class="n">git</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">store</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">blob</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">id</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">blob</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">content</span><span class="p">)</span>
            <span class="n">already_converted</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="nb">file</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">id</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">blob</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">id</span>
            <span class="n">blob_id</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">blob</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">id</span>

        <span class="n">tree_builder</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">add_file</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">file</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">path</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">blob_id</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nb">file</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">mode</span><span class="p">)</span>

    <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">tree</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="n">tree_builder</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">all_trees</span><span class="p">():</span>
        <span class="n">git</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">store</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">tree</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">id</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">tree</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">content</span><span class="p">)</span>

    <span class="n">root_tree</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">tree_builder</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">root_tree</span>

    <span class="c"># And proceed to build the Git commit and insert it.</span>
</pre></div>

<p>On the face of it, this code doesn't seem too bad. If I were writing the
functionality from scratch, I'd likely do something very similar. So,
why is it so slow?</p>
<p>As I mentioned earlier, profiling results had identified Mercurial and
Dulwich as the hot spots. The Mercurial hotspot was in iteration over
the files in the manifest. And the Dulwich offender with Git <em>tree</em>
object construction. By why?</p>
<p>First, it turns out that iterating a manifest the way hg-git was isn't
exactly performant. I never traced all the gory details, but I'm pretty
sure every time it accessed the file context through the change context
there was I/O involved. Not good, especially if you may not need the
information contained if it was already cached!</p>
<p>Second, it turns out that creating Git <em>tree</em> objects in Dulwich is
rather slow. And, the problem is magnified when converting large
repositories - like mozilla-central (Firefox's canonical repository).</p>
<p>So, I was faced with a decision: make Mercurial and/or Dulwich faster or
change hg-git. Since improving these would have benefits outside of
hg-git, I initially went down those roads. However, I eventually
abandonded the effort because of effort involved. And, in the case of
Dulwich, improving things would likely require rewriting some pieces in
C - not something I cared to do nor something that the Dulwich people
would likely accept since Dulwich is all about being a pure Python
implementation of Git! And in hindsight, this was the right call.
Mercurial and Dulwich are fast enough - it's hg-git that was being
suboptimal.</p>
<p>I was faced with two problems: don't mass iterate over manifests and
don't mass generate Git trees. Both were seemingly impossible to avoid
because both are critical to converting a Mercurial changeset to Git.</p>
<p>I thought about this problem for a while. I experimented with numerous
micro benchmarks. I engaged the very helpful Mercurial developers on IRC
(thanks everyone!). And, I eventually arrived at what I think is an
elegant solution.</p>
<p>When I took a step back and looked at the larger problem of exporting
Mercurial changesets to Git, I realized it would be beneficial in terms
of efficiency for the conversion to be more aware of what had occurred
before. Before I came along, hg-git was asking Mercurial for the full
state of each changeset for each changeset conversion. When you think
about it in low-level operations, this is extremely inefficient. Let's
take Git trees as an example.</p>
<p>When you perform a commit, only the trees - and
their parents - that had modified files will change. All the
other trees will be identical across commits. For large repositories (in
terms of files and directories) like mozilla-central, the number of
<em>static</em> trees across small commits is quite significant compared to
changed trees. The overhead of computing all these trees is not
insignificant!</p>
<p>Instead of throwing away all the trees and file context information
between changeset exports, what if I preserved it and reused it for the
next changeset? I think I'm on to something...</p>
<h2>Implementing incremental changeset export</h2>
<p>To minimize the work performed when exporting Mercurial changesets to
Git, I <a href="https://github.com/indygreg/hg-git/commit/aef6eacf86fb08101ea98a7787f3b20dd67287c2">implemented</a>
a standalone class that can emit Mercurial changeset deltas in terms of
Git objects. Essentially, it caches a Git tree representation of a
Mercurial manifest. When you feed a new Mercurial changeset into it, it
asks Mercurial to compare those changesets using the same API used by
<em>hg status</em>. This API is efficient and returns the information I care
about: the paths that changed. Once we have the changed files, we
<em>simply</em> reflect those changes in terms of updating Git trees.</p>
<p>If a file changes or is added, we emit a <em>blob</em>. If a <em>tree</em> changes, we
emit the new <em>tree</em> object. When the consumer has finished writing the
set of new objects to Git, it asks for the SHA-1 of the root tree. (Up
until this point the consumer is not aware of what any of the emitted
objects actually are - just that they likely need to be added to
storage.) It then uses the SHA-1 of the root tree to construct the
commit. Then it moves on to the next changeset.</p>
<p>The impact of this change is significant. On my computer, converting
Mercurial's own Mercurial repository Git went from <strong>21:07</strong> to <strong>8:14</strong>
on my i7-2600k. mozilla-central is even more drastic. The first 200
commits (the first commit was a large dump from CVS) took <strong>8:17</strong>
before and now take <strong>2:32</strong>. I don't have exact numbers from newer
commits, but I do know they were at least twice as slow as the initial
commits and showed an even more drastic speedup.</p>
<p>But I was just getting started.</p>
<p>The initial implementation wasn't very efficient in terms of reducing
tree object calculations. I changed that earlier today when I
<a href="https://groups.google.com/d/msg/hg-git/I5w_FscF6lw/LAc0pw1iilQJ">submitted a patch for consideration</a>
that only calculates tree changes for trees that actually changed. I
also removed some needless sorting on the order of export operations.
This second patch reduced conversion of Mercurial's repository down to
<strong>5:33</strong>. Even more impressive is that <strong>mozilla-central's changesets are
now exporting almost 4x faster</strong> with this patch alone. The first 200
changesets now export in <strong>42s</strong> (down from <strong>2:32</strong> which is down from
<strong>8:17</strong>). This is mostly due to the overhead of reprocessing
non-dirty trees on every export.</p>
<p>And I'm not through.</p>
<p>As part of building the standalone incremental changeset exporter, one
of the goals in the back of my mind was to eventually have things
execute in parallel.</p>
<p>In my <a href="https://github.com/indygreg/hg-git/tree/performance-next">personal development branch</a>
I have a <a href="https://github.com/indygreg/hg-git/commit/e74641284fecc928b0b8f8dcc01ef9b99e09c3cc">patch</a>
to perform Mercurial changeset export on multiple cores. Essentially
hg-git fires up a bunch of worker processes and asks each to export a
consecutive range of changesets. The workers writes new Git objects into
Git and then tells the coordinator process the root tree SHA-1
corresponding to each Mercurial changeset. The coordinator process then
uses these root tree SHA-1's to derive Git commit objects (you can't
create the commit object until you know the SHA-1 of the commit's
parents).</p>
<p>The blob and tree exporting on separate processes makes Mercurial to Git
export scale out to however many cores you feel like throwing at it.
When 32 core machines come around, you can convert using all available
cores and the speedup should roughly be linear with the number of cores.</p>
<p>I'm still working out some kinks in the multiple processes patch
(the <em>multiprocessing</em> module is very difficult to get working on all
platforms and I don't want to break hg-git when it lands). But,
<a href="http://ehsanakhgari.org/">Ehsan Akhgari</a> has been using it to power the
<a href="https://github.com/mozilla/mozilla-central/">GitHub mirror</a> of
mozilla-central for months without issue. (His use of these patches
freed up the CPU required to support conversion of more project branches
on the Git mirror. And, he's still not using the 4x improvement patch I
wrote today - he will shortly - so who knows what improvements will stem
from that.)</p>
<p>With all the patches applied, hg-git now feels like a Ferrari when
exporting Mercurial changesets to Git. Conversion of Mercurial's
repository now takes <strong>1:25</strong> (down from <strong>21:07</strong>). <strong>Conversion of
mozilla-central has gone from 6+ days to about 3 hours!</strong> More
importantly, ongoing conversions feel somewhat snappy now.</p>
<h2>Making Git export even faster</h2>
<p>With the patch today, I'd say optimization of exporting Mercurial
changesets is nearing its limits. There are a few things I could try
that may net another 2 or 3x improvement. But, I think the ~50x
improvement I've already attained (at least for mozilla-central) is
pretty damn good and good enough for most users. (Part of performance
optimization is knowing when is good enough and stopping before you
invest excessive time in the long tail.)</p>
<p>There is one giant refactor that could likely net a significant win for
Git export. However, it requires optimizing for initial export over
recurring incremental export (which is why I have little interest in
it). Incremental export incurs a lot of <em>random</em> I/O accessing Mercurial
filelogs and extracting specific file revisions as they are needed. An
optimal export would iterate over the filelogs and export Git blobs from
each filelog in the sequence they occur in within the filelogs. It would
cache the file node to blob SHA-1. After all blobs are exported, the
mappings would be combined and distributed to all workers. Then, tree
export would occur in parallel largely under the existing model modulo
blob writing. This would minimize overall I/O and work in Mercurial and
would likely be significantly faster. However, it's mostly useful for
initial export and IMO not worth implementing. (It's possible to employ
a variation for incremental export that iterates over filelogs and
exports not-yet-seen revisions. Perhaps I will investigate this some
day.)</p>
<h2>What about converting Git to Mercurial?</h2>
<p>Now that I've tackled Mercurial to Git conversion, it's very tempting to
work magic on the inverse: converting Git commits to Mercurial
changesets. While I haven't looked at this problem in detail, I already
know it will be at least slightly more challenging.</p>
<p>The reason is parallelization. With Mercurial export, I have each child
process reading directly from Mercurial and writing directly to Git.
There are no locks involved. There is just a coordinator that ensures
minimum redundant work among workers. There is some redundant
work, sure. But, the alternative would be lots of locking and/or
exchange of state across processes - not cheap operations! Furthermore,
the writes into Git can occur in any order (since Git is just a
key-value store). The only hard requirement is a child commit must
come after its parent (because you need the parent commit's SHA-1).
And, single-threaded insert of commit objects isn't a big deal because
you can crank through hundreds of them per second (it might even be over
1000/s on my machine).</p>
<p>Mercurial's storage implementation does not afford me the same
<em>carelessness</em> with regards to writing into storage. Since Mercurial
uses shared files for individual file and manifest history, we have
a contention problem. We <em>could</em> lock files when writing to them.
However, these files (<em>revlogs</em> in Mercurial speak) also use
transparent delta compression. You get the best performance/compression
when changes are written in the order they actually occured in (at
least in the typical case).</p>
<p>To optimally write to Mercurial you need to order inserts. This means
parallel reads from Git (in separate worker processes) would be very
difficult to implement. Doable, sure, but you're looking at a lot of
transferred state and ordering. This likely involves a lot more memory
and CPU usage.</p>
<p>The best idea I've come up with so far is a single process
that reads off Git commits and iterates trees. It hashes the paths of
seen files to a consistent worker process which then pulls the blob from
Git's storage and inserts it into the filelog. You don't need to lock
filelogs because only one worker owns a specific path. Workers report
the blob's corresponding file node to another process which then
assembles manifests, writes manifests in order, and finally creates
and writes changesets. Unfortunately, the worker processes are just
doing blob I/O. There is no parallel processing of Git tree calculation
or Mercurial manifests. Given this was a significant source of slowness
exporting <em>to</em> Git, I worry the inverse will be true. Although, the
problem with Git was tree <em>creation</em> and it was due to the volume. Since
there is only 1 manifest per changeset, perhaps it won't be as bad.</p>
<p>While I've brainstormed a solution, I have no concrete plans to work on
Git to Mercurial conversion. The impetus for me working on Mercurial to
Git speedups was that I and a number of other Mozilla people were
personally impacted. If the same is true for Git to Mercurial slowness,
I could invest a few hours the next time I'm sick and bored over the
weekend.</p>
<h2>Conclusion</h2>
<p>Converting Mercurial repositories to Git with hg-git is now
significantly faster. If you thought it was too slow before, grab the
latest code (from either the official repository or my personal branch)
and enjoy.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
</feed>
