<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed
  xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:thr="http://purl.org/syndication/thread/1.0"
  xml:lang="en"
   >
  <title type="text">Gregory Szorc's Digital Home</title>
  <subtitle type="text">Rambling on</subtitle>

  <updated>2022-04-25T07:42:55Z</updated>
  <generator uri="http://blogofile.com/">Blogofile</generator>

  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" />
  <id>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/feed/atom/</id>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/feed/atom/" />
  <entry>
    <author>
      <name>Gregory Szorc</name>
      <uri>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog</uri>
    </author>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gone with the Wind Thoughts]]></title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2012/02/26/gone-with-the-wind-thoughts" />
    <id>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2012/02/26/gone-with-the-wind-thoughts</id>
    <updated>2012-02-26T14:30:00Z</updated>
    <published>2012-02-26T14:30:00Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog" term="movies" />
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Gone with the Wind Thoughts]]></summary>
    <content type="html" xml:base="http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2012/02/26/gone-with-the-wind-thoughts"><![CDATA[<p>I watched <em>Gone with the Wind</em>, the 1939 classic, a few days ago.
It is an amazing film. But, I was bothered by a number of plot points.</p>
<h2>On Scarlett</h2>
<p>How exactly am I supposed to feel about Scarlett? Sympathy? I hope not!
She is a manipulative, gold-digging woman. Yes, I do love her strength and
juxtaposition with men at times. But, she has no qualms about crying
to get her way. Screw that! I knew people like her- in high school! One
thing I learned was to keep as far away from people like this as you
can. Rhett apparently didn't get the memo.</p>
<h2>On Rhett Butler</h2>
<p>At times I was like, yes, he's the man of men: I want to be him. But,
there were a few things I couldn't get over.</p>
<p>First, the age gap with Scarlett was <em>creepy</em>. When they first meet at
Twelve Oaks, she's maybe 18 and he's what, 40? Maybe that was acceptable
in the 1800's and earlier this century. But, that doesn't change that
I'm freaked out by it. I'm 28 now and find 25 to be about the minimum
age I can tolerate. The gap between Rhett and Scarlett is Hugh Hefner
territory by 1800's standards.</p>
<p>Maybe I missed the line, but I don't think they attributed his wealth to
anything specific. Yes, they mentioned he was a blockade runner or
something (which immediately got me thinking that Han Solo might have
been modeled after him, which is an interesting train of thought). But,
I don't think that's enough to explain his grand fortune. Hmm.</p>
<p>He's cold. Too cold. After he drunkenly makes love to Scarlett near the
end (I dare say rape, but she appears to have loved it the next
morning, so maybe it was just aggressive - which I imagine Scarlett
might enjoy given her masculine qualities. Am I allowed to go there?),
she's feeling all good about things and then he comes in and is like
"I'm going to London for a while. Oh, and I'm taking our daughter too!"
What an asshole. I admire the consistency of his character, but he's
a jerk for the timing, even though the actions were probably justified
given the state of their relationship.</p>
<h2>Lack of Character Arcs</h2>
<p>In many great films, the protagonist goes through an arc to help the
audience connect the lows and the highs and to root for them. In this
film, our protagonist is Scarlett and her arc is questionable. Yes, she
goes from living a great lifestyle to poverty via the Civil War then to
lavishness after marrying Butler. But, the film revolves around
relationships. All that stuff about the Civil War and the lifestyle of
the south is just extra icing on the cake. Despite things around her
changing, Scarlett's relationships are quite consistent throughout the
film.</p>
<p>Even though her arc is tiny, it is still larger than anyone else's since
all the main characters were fairly rigid and hardly developed during
the film. Rhett was the rich playboy who enjoyed his independence ("I'm
not a marrying man"). Ashley was consistently ambiguous. Melanie was
steadfast. Mammy was Mammy. From a character development perspective,
not much went on in this film. It was simply an epic love story told in
the south during the Civil War.</p>
<h2>Misc Observations</h2>
<p>It bothers me they seemed to overlook the stigma of Scarlett being a
two-time widow. This is the deep south in the 1800's: her life would have
been over after her first husband died. She would be an outcast for
marrying again. Two, and she would be driven out of town, especially
since her actions got #2 shot through the head. They alluded to this at
times, but it was quickly moved faster. You'd think in a nearly 4 hour
film they could find more time to cover this.</p>
<p>Can you imagine people in 1939 watching two amazing (color) films with 2
strong, female protagonists (Vivien Leigh, Judy Garland)? I'm not an
expert on the history of cinema, but surely that year must have been a
turning point.</p>
<p>There are some incredible lines in this film. Obvious ones aside, I had
no clue that the "don't call me Shirley" line originated in this film
and not <em>Airplane!</em></p>
<p>"Great balls of fire!" I need to watch Top Gun now.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
</feed>
