<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"
     xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
     xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
     xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
     xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
     xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
     >
  <channel>
    <title>Gregory Szorc's Digital Home</title>
    <link>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog</link>
    <description>Rambling on</description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2013 17:54:57 GMT</pubDate>
    <generator>Blogofile</generator>
    <sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
    <sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on Mercurial (and Git)</title>
      <link>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2013/05/12/thoughts-on-mercurial-(and-git)</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 May 2013 12:00:00 PDT</pubDate>
      <category><![CDATA[Mozilla]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[Mercurial]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[Git]]></category>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2013/05/12/thoughts-on-mercurial-(and-git)</guid>
      <description>Thoughts on Mercurial (and Git)</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>My first experience with Mercurial (Firefox development)
was very unpleasant. Coming from Git, I thought Mercurial was slow
and perhaps even more awkward to use than Git. I frequently
encountered repository corruption that required me to reclone. I thought
the concept of a patch queue was silly compared to Git branches. It
was all extremely frustrating and I dare say a hinderance to my
productivity. It didn't help that I was surrounded by a bunch of people
who had previous experience with Git and opined about every minute
difference.</p>
<p>Two years later and I'm on much better terms with Mercurial. I initially
thought it might be Stockholm Syndrome, but after reflection I can point
at specific changes and enlightenments that have reshaped my opinions.</p>
<h2>Newer versions of Mercurial are much better</h2>
<p>I first started using Mercurial in the 1.8 days and thought it was
horrible. However, modern releases are much, much better. I've noticed
a steady improvement in the quality and speed of Mercurial in the last
few years.</p>
<p><strong>If you aren't running 2.5 or later (Mercurial 2.6 was released earlier
this month), you should take the time to upgrade today.</strong> When you upgrade,
you should of course read the
<a href="http://mercurial.selenic.com/wiki/WhatsNew">changelog</a> and
<a href="http://mercurial.selenic.com/wiki/UpgradeNotes">upgrade notes</a> so you
can make the most of the new features.</p>
<h2>Proper configuration is key</h2>
<p>For <em>my</em> workflow, the default configuration of Mercurial out of the box
is... far from optimal. There are a number of basic changes that need to
be made to satisfy <em>my</em> expectations for a version control tool.</p>
<p>I used to think this was a shortcoming with Mercurial: why not ship a
powerful and useful environment out of the box? But, after talking to a
Mercurial core contributor, this is mostly by design. Apparently a
principle of the Mercurial project is that the CLI tool (<em>hg</em>) should be
simple by default and should minimize foot guns. They view actions like
rebasing and patch queues as advanced and thus don't have them enabled
by default. Seasoned developers may scoff at this. But, I see where
Mercurial is coming from. I only need to refer everyone to her first
experience with Git as an example of what happens when you don't aim for
simplicity. (I've never met a Git user who didn't think it overly
complicated at first.)</p>
<p>Anyway, to get the most out of Mercurial, it is essential to configure
it to your liking, much like you install plugins or extensions in your
code editor.</p>
<p><strong>Every person running Mercurial should go to
<a href="http://mercurial.selenic.com/wiki/UsingExtensions">http://mercurial.selenic.com/wiki/UsingExtensions</a>
and take the time to find extensions that will make your life better</strong>.
You should also run <em>hg help hgrc</em> to view all the configuration
options. There is a mountain of productivity wins waiting to be realized.</p>
<p>For reference, my <a href="https://gist.github.com/indygreg/5511712">~/.hgrc</a>.
Worth noting are some of the built-in externsions I've enabled:</p>
<ul>
<li>color - Colorize terminal output. Clear UX win.</li>
<li>histedit - Provides  <em>git rebase --interactive</em> behavior.</li>
<li>pager - Feed command output into a pager (like <em>less</em>). Clear UX win.</li>
<li>progress - Draw progress bars on long-running operations. Clear UX
  win.</li>
<li>rebase - Ability to easily rebase patches on top of other heads.
  This is a basic feature of patch management.</li>
<li>transplant - Easily move patches between repositories, branches, etc.</li>
</ul>
<p>If I were on Linux, I'd also use the <em>inotify</em> extension, which installs
filesystem watchers so operations like <em>hg status</em> are instantaneous.</p>
<p>In addition to the built-in extensions, there are a number of 3rd party
extensions that improve my Mozilla workflow:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://bitbucket.org/sfink/mqext">mqext</a> - Automatically commit to
  your patch queue when you qref, etc. This is a lifesaver. If that's
  not enough, it suggests reviewers for your patch, suggests a bug
  component, and let's you find bugs touching the files you are
  touching.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/pbiggar/trychooser">trychooser</a> - Easily push
  changes to Mozilla's Try infrastructure.</li>
<li><a href="https://hg.mozilla.org/users/robarnold_cmu.edu/qimportbz">qimportbz</a> -
  Easily import patches from Bugzilla.</li>
<li><a href="https://hg.mozilla.org/users/tmielczarek_mozilla.com/bzexport">bzexport</a> -
  Easily export patches to Bugzilla.</li>
</ul>
<p>I'm amazed more developers don't use these simple productivity wins.
Could it be that people simply don't realize they are available?</p>
<p>Mozilla has a <a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=794580">bug</a>
tracking easier configuration of the user's Mercurial environment. My
hope is one day people simply run a single command and get a
Mozilla-optimized Mercurial environment that <em>just works</em>. Along the same
vein, if your extensions are out of date, it prompts you to update them.
This is one of the benefits of a unified developer tool like mach: you
can put these checks in one place and everyone can reap the benefits
easily.</p>
<h2>Mercurial is extensible</h2>
<p>The major differentiator from almost every other version control system
(especially Git) is the ease and degree to which Mercurial can be
extended and contorted. <strong>If you take anything away from this
post it should be that Mercurial is a flexible and agile tool.</strong></p>
<p>If you want to change the behavior of a built-in command, you can write
an extension that monkeypatches that command. If you want to write a new
command, you can of course do that easily. You can have extensions
interact with one another - all natively. You can even override the wire
protocol to provide new <em>capabilities</em> to extend how peers communicate
with one another. You can leverage this to transfer additional metadata
or data types. This has nearly infinite potential. If that's not enough,
it's possible to create a new branching/development primitive through
just an extension alone! If you want to invent Git-style branches with
Mercurial, you could do that! It may require client and server support,
but it's possible.</p>
<p>Mercurial accomplishes this by being written (mostly) in Python (as
opposed to C) and by having a clear API on which extensions can be
built. Writing extensions in Python is huge. You can easily drop into
the debugger to learn the API and your write-test loop is much smaller.</p>
<p>By contrast, most other version control systems (including Git) require
you to parse output of commands (this is the UNIX piping principle).
Mercurial supports this too, but the native Python API is so much more
powerful. Instead of parsing output, you can just read the raw values
from a Python data structure. Yes please.</p>
<p>Since I imagine a lot of people at Mozilla will be reading this, here
are some ways Mozilla could leverage the extensibility of Mercurial:</p>
<ul>
<li>Command to create try pushes (it exists - see above).</li>
<li>Record who pushed what when (we have this - it's called the pushlog).</li>
<li>Command to land patches. If inbound1 is closed,
  automatically rebase on inbound2. etc. This could even be
  monkeypatched into <em>hg push</em> so pushes to inbound are automatically
  intercepted and magic ensues.</li>
<li>Record the automation success/fail status against individual
  revisions and integrate with commands (e.g. only pull up to the most
  recent stable changeset).</li>
<li>Command to create a review request for a patch or patch queue.</li>
<li>Command to assist with reviews. Perhaps a reviewer wants to make minor
  changes. Mercurial could download and apply the patch(es), wait for
  your changes, then reupload to Bugzilla (or the review tool)
  automatically.</li>
<li>Annotating commits or pushes with automation info (which jobs to
  run, etc).</li>
<li>Find Bugzilla component for patch (it exists - see above).</li>
<li>Expose custom protocol for configuring automation settings for a
  repository or a head. e.g. clients (with access) could reconfigure
  PGO scheduling, coalescing, etc without having to involve RelEng -
  useful for twigs and lesser used repositories.</li>
<li>So much more.</li>
</ul>
<p>Essentially, Mercurial itself could become the CLI tool code development
centers around. Whether that is a good idea is up for
debate. But, it can. And that says a lot about the flexibility of
Mercurial.</p>
<h2>Future potential of Mercurial</h2>
<p>When you consider the previous three points, you arrive at a new one:
Mercurial has a ton of future potential. The fact that extensions can
evolve vanilla Mercurial into something that resembles Mercurial in
name only is a testament to this.</p>
<p>When I sat down with a Mercurial core contributor, they reinforced this.
To them, Mercurial is a core library with a limited set of user-facing
commands forming the stable API. Since core features (like storage) are
internal APIs (not public commands - like Git), this means they aren't
bound to backwards compatibility and can refactor internals as needed
and evolve over time without breaking the world. That is a terrific
luxury.</p>
<p>An example of this future potential is
<a href="http://mercurial.selenic.com/wiki/ChangesetEvolution">changeset evolution</a>.
If you don't know what that is, you should because it's awesome. One of
the things they figured out is how to propagate rebasing between
clones!</p>
<h2>Comparing to Git</h2>
<p>Two years ago I would have said I would never opt to use Mercurial over
Git. I cannot say that today.</p>
<p>I do believe Git still has the advantage over Mercurial in a few areas:</p>
<ul>
<li>Branch management. Mercurial branches are a non-starter for
  light-weigh work. Mercurial bookmarks are kinda-sorta like Git
  branches, but not quite. I <em>really</em> like aspects of Git branches.
  Hopefully changeset evolution will cover the remaining gaps and more.</li>
<li>Patch conflict management. Git seems to do a better job of resolving
  patch conflicts. But, I think this is mostly due to Mercurial's patch
  queue extension not using the same merge code as built-in commands
  (this is a fixable problem).</li>
<li>Developer mind share and GitHub. The GitHub ecosystem makes up for
  many of Git's shortcomings. Bitbucket isn't the same.</li>
</ul>
<p>However, I believe Mercurial has the upper hand for:</p>
<ul>
<li>Command line friendliness. Git's command line syntax is notoriously
  awful and the concepts can be difficult to master.</li>
<li>Extensibility. It's so easy to program custom workflows and commands
  with Mercurial. If you want to hack your version control system,
  Mercurial wins hands down. Where Mercurial embraces extensibility, I
  couldn't even find a page listing all the useful Git <em>extensions</em>!</li>
<li>Open source culture. Every time I've popped into the Mercurial IRC
  channel I've had a good experience. I get a response quickly and
  without snark. Git by contrast, well, let's just say I'd rather be
  affiliated with the Mercurial crowd.</li>
<li>Future potential. Git is a content addressable key-value store with a
  version control system bolted on top. Mercurial is designed to be a
  version control system. Furthermore, Mercurial's code base is much
  easier to hack on than Git's. While Git has largely maintained feature
  parity in the last few years, Mercurial has grown new features. I see
  Mercurial evolving faster than Git and in ways Git cannot.</li>
</ul>
<p>It's worth calling out the major detractors for each.</p>
<p>I think Git's major weakness is its lack of extensibility and inability
to evolve (at least currently). Git will need to grow a better
extensibility model with better abstractions to compete with Mercurial
on new features. Or, the Git community will need to be receptive to
experimental features living in the core. All of this will require
some major API breakage. Unfortunately, I see little evidence this will
occur. I'm unable to find a <em>vision</em> document for the future of Git, a
branch with major new features, or interesting threads on the mailing
list. I tried to ask in their IRC channel and got crickets.</p>
<p>I think Mercurial's greatest weakness is lack of developer mindshare.
Git and GitHub are where it's at. This is huge, especially for projects
wanting collaboration.</p>
<p>Of all those points, I want to stress the extensibility and future
potential of Mercurial. If hacking your tools to maximize potential
and awesomeness is your game, Mercurial wins. End of debate. However,
if you don't want to harness these advantages, then I think Git and
Mercurial are mostly on equal footing. But given the rate of
development in the Mercurial project and relative stagnation of Git
(I can't name a major new Git feature in years), I wouldn't be
surprised if Mercurial's feature set obviously overtakes Git's in
the next year or two. Mind share will of course take longer and will
likely depend on what hosting sites like GitHub and Bitbucket do
(I wouldn't be surprised if GitHub rebranded as <em>CodeHub</em> or
something some day). Time will tell.</p>
<h2>Extending case study</h2>
<p><em>I have removed the case study that appeared in the original article
because as Mike Hommey observed in the comments, it wasn't a totally
accurate comparison. I don't believe the case study significantly added
much to the post, so I likely won't write a new one.</em></p>
<h2>Conclusion</h2>
<p>From where I started with Mercurial, I never thought I'd say this. But
here it goes: I like Mercurial.</p>
<p>I started warming up when it became faster and more robust in recent
versions in the last few years. When I learned about its flexibility and
the fundamentals of the project and thus its future potential, I became
a true fan.</p>
<p>It's easy to not like Mercurial if you are a new user coming
from Git and are forced to use a new tool. But, once you take the time to
properly configure it and appreciate it for what it is and what it
can be, Mercurial is easy to like.</p>
<p>I think Mercurial and Git are both fine version control systems. I would
happily use either one for a new project. If the social aspects of
development (including encouraging new contributors) were important to
me, I would likely select Git and GitHub. But, if I wanted something
just for me or I was a large project looking for a system that scales
and is flexible or was looking to the future, I'd go with Mercurial.</p>
<p>Mercurial is a rising star in the version control world. It's getting
faster and better and enabling others to more easily innovate through
powerful extensions. The future is bright for this tool.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Making hg-git Faster</title>
      <link>http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2013/04/14/making-hg-git-faster</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Apr 2013 21:45:00 PDT</pubDate>
      <category><![CDATA[Mozilla]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[Mercurial]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[Git]]></category>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://gregoryszorc.com/blog/2013/04/14/making-hg-git-faster</guid>
      <description>Making hg-git Faster</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>When enterprising individuals at Mozilla
<a href="http://bluishcoder.co.nz/2011/02/10/git-conversion-of-mozilla-central.html">started maintaining</a>
a Git mirror of Firefox's main source repository (hosted in Mercurial),
they ran into a significant problem: conversion was slow. The initial
conversion apparently took over 6 days and used a lot of memory.
Furthermore, each subsequent commit took many seconds, even on modern
hardware. This meant that the they could only maintain a Git mirror of
a few project branches and that updates would be slow. Furthermore,
the slowness of the conversion significantly discouraged people
from using the tool locally as part of regular development.</p>
<p>I thought this was unacceptable. I wanted to enable people to use
their tool of choice (Git) to develop Firefox. So, I did what annoyed
engineers do when confronted with an itch: I scratched it.</p>
<h2>Diagnosing the Problem</h2>
<p>When I started tackling this problem, I had little knowledge of the
problem space other than the problem statement: <em>converting from
Mercurial to Git is prohibitively slow</em> and that the slow tool was
<a href="http://hg-git.github.io/">hg-git</a>. My challenge was thus to make
hg-git faster.</p>
<p>When confronted with a performance problem, one of the first things you
do is identify the source of the bad performance. Then, you need to
acertain whether that is something you have the ability to change.</p>
<p>This often starts by answering some high-level questions then drilling
down into more detail as necessary. For a long-running system tool like
hg-git, I start with the <em>top test</em>: how much CPU, memory, and I/O is
the process utilizing?</p>
<p>In the case of hg-git, we were CPU bound. The Python process was
consistently pegging a single CPU core while periodically incurring I/O
(but not nearly enough to saturate a magnetic disk). This told me a few
things. First, I should look for bottlenecks inside Python. Second, I
should investigate whether parallel execution would be possible. The
latter is especially important these days because the trend in
processors is towards more cores rather than higher clock speeds. It's
no longer acceptable to let increases in clock speed or cycle efficiency
bail you out: if you want a CPU bound process to run as fast as
possible, it's often necessary to involve all available CPU cores.</p>
<p>Once I diagnosed CPU as the limiting factor, I pulled out the next tool
in the arsenal: a code profiler. I quickly discovered exactly where the
conversion was taking the most CPU time. As feared, it was in the
<em>export Mercurial changeset to Git commit</em> function.
Specifically, profiling had flagged the conversion of Mercurial
manifests to Git trees and blobs. Furthermore, most of the time was
spent in functions in Mercurial itself (Mercurial is implemented in
Python and hg-git calls into it natively) and Dulwich (a pure Python
implementation of Git). So, I was either looking at deficiencies or
Mercurial and/or Dulwich, a bad conversion algorithm in hg-git, or both.
To know which, I would need a better grasp on the internal storage
models of Mercurial and Git.</p>
<h2>Learning about Mercurial's and Git's internal storage models</h2>
<p>To understand why conversion from Mercurial to Git was slow, I needed to
understand how each stored data internally. My hope was that if attained
better understanding I could apply the knowledge to assess the algorithm
hg-git was using and optimize it, hopefully introducing parallel
execution along the way.</p>
<h3>Git's internals</h3>
<p>I already had a fairly good understanding of how Git works internally.
And, it's quite simple really. The <a href="http://git-scm.com/book/en/Git-Internals">Git Internals</a>
chapter of the <em>Pro Git</em> is extremely useful. While I encourage readers
to read all of the <a href="http://git-scm.com/book/en/Git-Internals-Git-Objects">Git Objects</a>
section, the gist is:</p>
<ul>
<li>Git's core storage is a key-value data store. Keys are SHA-1 checksums
  of content. Each entity is storage in a <em>Git object</em>.</li>
<li>A <em>blob</em> is an object holding the raw content of a file.</li>
<li>A <em>tree</em> is an object holding a list of <em>tree entries</em>. Each tree entry
  defines a blob, another tree object, etc. A tree is essentially a
  directory listing.</li>
<li>A <em>commit</em> object holds metadata about an individual Git commit. Each
  commit object refers to a specific <em>tree</em> object.</li>
</ul>
<p>When you introduce a new file that hasn't been seen before, a new <em>blob</em>
is added to storage. That blob is referenced by a <em>tree</em>. When you
update a file, a new <em>tree</em> is created referring to the new <em>blob</em> that
was created.</p>
<p>Things get a little complicated when you consider directories. If you
update the file <em>foo/bar/baz.c</em>, the tree for <em>foo/bar</em> changes (because
the SHA-1 of <em>baz.c</em> changed). And, the SHA-1 for the <em>foo/bar</em> tree
changes, so the <em>bar</em> entry in <em>foo</em>'s tree changes, changing the SHA-1
for the root tree.</p>
<p>That's essentially how Git addresses commits, directories, and files. If
you don't grok this, please, please read the aforementioned page on it -
it may even help you better grok Git!</p>
<h3>Mercurial's internals</h3>
<p>Unlike Git, I didn't really have a clue how Mercurial worked internally.
So, I needed to do some self-education here.</p>
<p>The best resource for Mercurial's storage model I've found is the
<a href="http://hgbook.red-bean.com/read/behind-the-scenes.html">Behind the Scenes</a>
chapter from <em>Mercurial: The Definitive Guide</em>. The gist is:</p>
<ul>
<li>History for an individual file is stored in a <em>filelog</em>. Each
  <em>filelog</em> contains the history of a single file. Each file revision
  has a hash based on the file contents.</li>
<li>The <em>manifest</em> lists every file, its permissions, and its file
  revision for each changeset in the repository.</li>
<li>The <em>changelog</em> contains information about each changeset, including
  the revision of the <em>manifest</em> to use.</li>
<li>Each of these logs contain <em>revisions</em> and you can address an
  individual revision within the log.</li>
</ul>
<p>From a high level, Mercurial's storage model is very similar to Git's.
They both address files by hashing their content. Where Git uses
multiple tree objects to define every file in a commit, Mercurial has a
single manifest containing a flat list. Aside from that, the
differences are mostly in implementation details. These are important,
as we'll soon see.</p>
<h2>Analyzing hg-git's conversion algorithm</h2>
<p>Armed with knowledge of how Git and Mercurial internally store data, I
was ready to analyze how hg-git was performing conversion from Mercurial
to Git. Since profiling revealed it was the <em>convert a single changeset
into Git commit</em> function that was taking all the time, I started there.</p>
<p>In Python (but not the actual Python), the algorithm was essentially:</p>
<div class="pygments_murphy"><pre><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">export_changeset_to_git</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">changeset</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">git</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">already_converted</span><span class="p">):</span>
    <span class="sd">&quot;&quot;&quot;Receives the Mercurial changeset and a handle on a Git object storre.&quot;&quot;&quot;</span>
    <span class="c"># This is an entity that helps us build Git tree objects from</span>
    <span class="c"># paths and blobs. The logic is at</span>
    <span class="c"># https://github.com/jelmer/dulwich/blob/2a8548be3b1fd4a1ae7d0436dce91611112c47c2/dulwich/index.py#L298</span>
    <span class="n">tree_builder</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">TreeBuilder</span><span class="p">()</span>

    <span class="k">for</span> <span class="nb">file</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="n">changeset</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">manifest</span><span class="p">:</span>
        <span class="n">blob_id</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">already_converted</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">get</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">file</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">id</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="bp">None</span><span class="p">)</span>

        <span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">blob_id</span> <span class="ow">is</span> <span class="bp">None</span><span class="p">:</span>
            <span class="n">blob</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">Blob</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">file</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">data</span><span class="p">())</span>
            <span class="n">git</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">store</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">blob</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">id</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">blob</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">content</span><span class="p">)</span>
            <span class="n">already_converted</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="nb">file</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">id</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">blob</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">id</span>
            <span class="n">blob_id</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">blob</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">id</span>

        <span class="n">tree_builder</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">add_file</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">file</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">path</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">blob_id</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nb">file</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">mode</span><span class="p">)</span>

    <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">tree</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="n">tree_builder</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">all_trees</span><span class="p">():</span>
        <span class="n">git</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">store</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">tree</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">id</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">tree</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">content</span><span class="p">)</span>

    <span class="n">root_tree</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">tree_builder</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">root_tree</span>

    <span class="c"># And proceed to build the Git commit and insert it.</span>
</pre></div>

<p>On the face of it, this code doesn't seem too bad. If I were writing the
functionality from scratch, I'd likely do something very similar. So,
why is it so slow?</p>
<p>As I mentioned earlier, profiling results had identified Mercurial and
Dulwich as the hot spots. The Mercurial hotspot was in iteration over
the files in the manifest. And the Dulwich offender with Git <em>tree</em>
object construction. By why?</p>
<p>First, it turns out that iterating a manifest the way hg-git was isn't
exactly performant. I never traced all the gory details, but I'm pretty
sure every time it accessed the file context through the change context
there was I/O involved. Not good, especially if you may not need the
information contained if it was already cached!</p>
<p>Second, it turns out that creating Git <em>tree</em> objects in Dulwich is
rather slow. And, the problem is magnified when converting large
repositories - like mozilla-central (Firefox's canonical repository).</p>
<p>So, I was faced with a decision: make Mercurial and/or Dulwich faster or
change hg-git. Since improving these would have benefits outside of
hg-git, I initially went down those roads. However, I eventually
abandonded the effort because of effort involved. And, in the case of
Dulwich, improving things would likely require rewriting some pieces in
C - not something I cared to do nor something that the Dulwich people
would likely accept since Dulwich is all about being a pure Python
implementation of Git! And in hindsight, this was the right call.
Mercurial and Dulwich are fast enough - it's hg-git that was being
suboptimal.</p>
<p>I was faced with two problems: don't mass iterate over manifests and
don't mass generate Git trees. Both were seemingly impossible to avoid
because both are critical to converting a Mercurial changeset to Git.</p>
<p>I thought about this problem for a while. I experimented with numerous
micro benchmarks. I engaged the very helpful Mercurial developers on IRC
(thanks everyone!). And, I eventually arrived at what I think is an
elegant solution.</p>
<p>When I took a step back and looked at the larger problem of exporting
Mercurial changesets to Git, I realized it would be beneficial in terms
of efficiency for the conversion to be more aware of what had occurred
before. Before I came along, hg-git was asking Mercurial for the full
state of each changeset for each changeset conversion. When you think
about it in low-level operations, this is extremely inefficient. Let's
take Git trees as an example.</p>
<p>When you perform a commit, only the trees - and
their parents - that had modified files will change. All the
other trees will be identical across commits. For large repositories (in
terms of files and directories) like mozilla-central, the number of
<em>static</em> trees across small commits is quite significant compared to
changed trees. The overhead of computing all these trees is not
insignificant!</p>
<p>Instead of throwing away all the trees and file context information
between changeset exports, what if I preserved it and reused it for the
next changeset? I think I'm on to something...</p>
<h2>Implementing incremental changeset export</h2>
<p>To minimize the work performed when exporting Mercurial changesets to
Git, I <a href="https://github.com/indygreg/hg-git/commit/aef6eacf86fb08101ea98a7787f3b20dd67287c2">implemented</a>
a standalone class that can emit Mercurial changeset deltas in terms of
Git objects. Essentially, it caches a Git tree representation of a
Mercurial manifest. When you feed a new Mercurial changeset into it, it
asks Mercurial to compare those changesets using the same API used by
<em>hg status</em>. This API is efficient and returns the information I care
about: the paths that changed. Once we have the changed files, we
<em>simply</em> reflect those changes in terms of updating Git trees.</p>
<p>If a file changes or is added, we emit a <em>blob</em>. If a <em>tree</em> changes, we
emit the new <em>tree</em> object. When the consumer has finished writing the
set of new objects to Git, it asks for the SHA-1 of the root tree. (Up
until this point the consumer is not aware of what any of the emitted
objects actually are - just that they likely need to be added to
storage.) It then uses the SHA-1 of the root tree to construct the
commit. Then it moves on to the next changeset.</p>
<p>The impact of this change is significant. On my computer, converting
Mercurial's own Mercurial repository Git went from <strong>21:07</strong> to <strong>8:14</strong>
on my i7-2600k. mozilla-central is even more drastic. The first 200
commits (the first commit was a large dump from CVS) took <strong>8:17</strong>
before and now take <strong>2:32</strong>. I don't have exact numbers from newer
commits, but I do know they were at least twice as slow as the initial
commits and showed an even more drastic speedup.</p>
<p>But I was just getting started.</p>
<p>The initial implementation wasn't very efficient in terms of reducing
tree object calculations. I changed that earlier today when I
<a href="https://groups.google.com/d/msg/hg-git/I5w_FscF6lw/LAc0pw1iilQJ">submitted a patch for consideration</a>
that only calculates tree changes for trees that actually changed. I
also removed some needless sorting on the order of export operations.
This second patch reduced conversion of Mercurial's repository down to
<strong>5:33</strong>. Even more impressive is that <strong>mozilla-central's changesets are
now exporting almost 4x faster</strong> with this patch alone. The first 200
changesets now export in <strong>42s</strong> (down from <strong>2:32</strong> which is down from
<strong>8:17</strong>). This is mostly due to the overhead of reprocessing
non-dirty trees on every export.</p>
<p>And I'm not through.</p>
<p>As part of building the standalone incremental changeset exporter, one
of the goals in the back of my mind was to eventually have things
execute in parallel.</p>
<p>In my <a href="https://github.com/indygreg/hg-git/tree/performance-next">personal development branch</a>
I have a <a href="https://github.com/indygreg/hg-git/commit/e74641284fecc928b0b8f8dcc01ef9b99e09c3cc">patch</a>
to perform Mercurial changeset export on multiple cores. Essentially
hg-git fires up a bunch of worker processes and asks each to export a
consecutive range of changesets. The workers writes new Git objects into
Git and then tells the coordinator process the root tree SHA-1
corresponding to each Mercurial changeset. The coordinator process then
uses these root tree SHA-1's to derive Git commit objects (you can't
create the commit object until you know the SHA-1 of the commit's
parents).</p>
<p>The blob and tree exporting on separate processes makes Mercurial to Git
export scale out to however many cores you feel like throwing at it.
When 32 core machines come around, you can convert using all available
cores and the speedup should roughly be linear with the number of cores.</p>
<p>I'm still working out some kinks in the multiple processes patch
(the <em>multiprocessing</em> module is very difficult to get working on all
platforms and I don't want to break hg-git when it lands). But,
<a href="http://ehsanakhgari.org/">Ehsan Akhgari</a> has been using it to power the
<a href="https://github.com/mozilla/mozilla-central/">GitHub mirror</a> of
mozilla-central for months without issue. (His use of these patches
freed up the CPU required to support conversion of more project branches
on the Git mirror. And, he's still not using the 4x improvement patch I
wrote today - he will shortly - so who knows what improvements will stem
from that.)</p>
<p>With all the patches applied, hg-git now feels like a Ferrari when
exporting Mercurial changesets to Git. Conversion of Mercurial's
repository now takes <strong>1:25</strong> (down from <strong>21:07</strong>). <strong>Conversion of
mozilla-central has gone from 6+ days to about 3 hours!</strong> More
importantly, ongoing conversions feel somewhat snappy now.</p>
<h2>Making Git export even faster</h2>
<p>With the patch today, I'd say optimization of exporting Mercurial
changesets is nearing its limits. There are a few things I could try
that may net another 2 or 3x improvement. But, I think the ~50x
improvement I've already attained (at least for mozilla-central) is
pretty damn good and good enough for most users. (Part of performance
optimization is knowing when is good enough and stopping before you
invest excessive time in the long tail.)</p>
<p>There is one giant refactor that could likely net a significant win for
Git export. However, it requires optimizing for initial export over
recurring incremental export (which is why I have little interest in
it). Incremental export incurs a lot of <em>random</em> I/O accessing Mercurial
filelogs and extracting specific file revisions as they are needed. An
optimal export would iterate over the filelogs and export Git blobs from
each filelog in the sequence they occur in within the filelogs. It would
cache the file node to blob SHA-1. After all blobs are exported, the
mappings would be combined and distributed to all workers. Then, tree
export would occur in parallel largely under the existing model modulo
blob writing. This would minimize overall I/O and work in Mercurial and
would likely be significantly faster. However, it's mostly useful for
initial export and IMO not worth implementing. (It's possible to employ
a variation for incremental export that iterates over filelogs and
exports not-yet-seen revisions. Perhaps I will investigate this some
day.)</p>
<h2>What about converting Git to Mercurial?</h2>
<p>Now that I've tackled Mercurial to Git conversion, it's very tempting to
work magic on the inverse: converting Git commits to Mercurial
changesets. While I haven't looked at this problem in detail, I already
know it will be at least slightly more challenging.</p>
<p>The reason is parallelization. With Mercurial export, I have each child
process reading directly from Mercurial and writing directly to Git.
There are no locks involved. There is just a coordinator that ensures
minimum redundant work among workers. There is some redundant
work, sure. But, the alternative would be lots of locking and/or
exchange of state across processes - not cheap operations! Furthermore,
the writes into Git can occur in any order (since Git is just a
key-value store). The only hard requirement is a child commit must
come after its parent (because you need the parent commit's SHA-1).
And, single-threaded insert of commit objects isn't a big deal because
you can crank through hundreds of them per second (it might even be over
1000/s on my machine).</p>
<p>Mercurial's storage implementation does not afford me the same
<em>carelessness</em> with regards to writing into storage. Since Mercurial
uses shared files for individual file and manifest history, we have
a contention problem. We <em>could</em> lock files when writing to them.
However, these files (<em>revlogs</em> in Mercurial speak) also use
transparent delta compression. You get the best performance/compression
when changes are written in the order they actually occured in (at
least in the typical case).</p>
<p>To optimally write to Mercurial you need to order inserts. This means
parallel reads from Git (in separate worker processes) would be very
difficult to implement. Doable, sure, but you're looking at a lot of
transferred state and ordering. This likely involves a lot more memory
and CPU usage.</p>
<p>The best idea I've come up with so far is a single process
that reads off Git commits and iterates trees. It hashes the paths of
seen files to a consistent worker process which then pulls the blob from
Git's storage and inserts it into the filelog. You don't need to lock
filelogs because only one worker owns a specific path. Workers report
the blob's corresponding file node to another process which then
assembles manifests, writes manifests in order, and finally creates
and writes changesets. Unfortunately, the worker processes are just
doing blob I/O. There is no parallel processing of Git tree calculation
or Mercurial manifests. Given this was a significant source of slowness
exporting <em>to</em> Git, I worry the inverse will be true. Although, the
problem with Git was tree <em>creation</em> and it was due to the volume. Since
there is only 1 manifest per changeset, perhaps it won't be as bad.</p>
<p>While I've brainstormed a solution, I have no concrete plans to work on
Git to Mercurial conversion. The impetus for me working on Mercurial to
Git speedups was that I and a number of other Mozilla people were
personally impacted. If the same is true for Git to Mercurial slowness,
I could invest a few hours the next time I'm sick and bored over the
weekend.</p>
<h2>Conclusion</h2>
<p>Converting Mercurial repositories to Git with hg-git is now
significantly faster. If you thought it was too slow before, grab the
latest code (from either the official repository or my personal branch)
and enjoy.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
